<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The bucolicks of Baptist Mantuan in ten eclogues. / Translated out of Latine into English, by Tho: Harvey Gent.</title>
            <title>Adulescentia. English</title>
            <author>Baptista, Mantuanus, 1448-1516.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 207 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 58 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93591</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4791</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1640_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203615</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863511</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863511</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115715</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93591)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115715)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 206:E1640[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The bucolicks of Baptist Mantuan in ten eclogues. / Translated out of Latine into English, by Tho: Harvey Gent.</title>
                  <title>Adulescentia. English</title>
                  <author>Baptista, Mantuanus, 1448-1516.</author>
                  <author>Harvey, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 104 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Humphrey Moseley, and are to be sold at his shop at the Princes Armes in S. Pauls Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656. [i.e. 1655]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "3 Nouemb. 1655."; the second 6 in the imprint date has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Latin poetry --  Translations into English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115715:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE BUCOLICKS OF BAPTIST MANTUAN IN <hi>TEN ECLOGUES.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of Latine into ENGLISH, BY <hi>THO: HARVEY</hi> Gent.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Hor. de Art. Poet.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Nec verbum Verbo curabis reddere—</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Humphrey Moſeley,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the <hi>Princes Armes</hi> in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:115715:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115715:2"/>
            <head>TO The moſt Accompliſh'd and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable, The LADY <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RANIA,</hi> Divineſt of the Nine Siſters The <hi>MUSES.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Exquiſite Lady,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hoſe ſingular Perfections are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lim'd beyond your Sex; Becauſe the Dedication of Books is almoſt out of faſhion with us (<hi>Auguſtus</hi> and <hi>Moecenas</hi> being long ſince extinct) and few favourers of Learning (eſpecially divine Poëſie) ſurviving, except your noble ſelf, I have preſumed to dedicate to your hand and Patronage, the Verſion of thoſe <hi>Juvenalia,</hi> compos'd by the (women-diſpleaſing) Poët <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuan,</hi> and by him diſpoſed into Ten Eclogues. And although (perhaps) I might have found ſome eminent Ladies for my Patroneſſes nearer
<pb facs="tcp:115715:3"/>
home, yet very few I doubt (ſcarce one of a thouſand) but would have conceiv'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo deeply concern'd in the fourth Eclogue, that theſe my labours muſt have deſpair'd of any benigne aſpect from them. But your Excellent ſelf (inhabiting another Region, ſoaring on the top of <hi>Pernaſſus,</hi> and rarified with the Soveraigne Influence of that perfu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Aire) is ſo free from Paſsion, clear in Judgement, and candid in Cenſure, that I nothing doubt of your Acceptance, Protection and Pardon. To you therefore (my tutelary Patroneſs) I dedicate theſe my Labours, which under your Name and Patronage ſhall be tranſmitted unto the courteous acceptance of the benevolent Reader,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>BY Your La: moſt humble Servant, <hi>Tho: Harvey.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:115715:3"/>
            <head>TO THE LEARNED AND JUDICIOUS, Sir <hi>Marmaduke Lloyd</hi> KNIGHT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT was mine hap (rather happineſs) not long ſince to preſent you with the Poet <hi>Mantuan</hi> accoutred in his owne weeds and language. I then told you my deſire to render him in Engliſh: It is now done; and repreſented to your judicious view: Whence it is derived to the Reader,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>BY Your humble Servant, <hi>Tho: Harvey.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:115715:4"/>
            <head>TO THE <hi>READER</hi> in generall.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Generous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Here preſent to thy peruſal the Ten Eclogues of the Poet <hi>Mantuan;</hi> wherein are many remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able paſſages, as well Divine as Morall, not found (perhaps) in any other Author of this kinde: All which I leave unto thy judicious obſervation in reading over the Book it ſelf. For I love not to prejudice the matter by a too tedious Epiſtle, which dulls the appetite, and defers expectancy: Both which I diſlike in my ſelf and others. Yet at preſent, for avoiding of violent Cenſures and virulent aſperſions, which ſome women (not half ſo candid as many of their Sex) might perhaps blurre me with for this my labour; give me leave (for this once onely to inlarge my ſelf a little by way of Apology, That in ſome ſort I may vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the Author and my ſelf (his Interpreter) for being ſo (ſeeming) Satyrically invective againſt that Sex in the fourth Eclogue. For I would not that either of us ſhould be miſtaken: Becauſe I (charitably) ſuppoſe, that the Author did not thunder out thoſe Epithetes in that Eclogue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>All women</hi> in general, but againſt <hi>Ill women</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:115715:4"/>
in particular. Howſoever, for mine own part, I clearly declare, That I publiſh this Verſion of theſe Eclogues, with this animadverſion to the Reader, That I doe it neither invectively againſt, nor with prejudice to any woman whatſoever, (for I honour the Sex.) But I could not diſmem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Book, by leaving out that fourth Eclogue; neither was it neceſſary I ſhould: For I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, That no diſcreet or vertuous woman will frown upon me or it. And if any other ſhould, I thus anſwer for my ſelf. That I intend not <hi>All,</hi> but <hi>Ill women.</hi> And as Contraries compared are more illuſtrated; ſo the diſpraiſe of a vicious wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is a praiſe to the vertuous. That inſatiable proſtitution of <hi>Fauſtina</hi> did, and doth with grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter luſtre exemplifie the chaſtity of <hi>Lucretia.</hi> But if any ſelf-will'd woman be diſpleaſed hereat, I wiſh, That ſhe would firſt reform her ſelf (and then ſhe is none of the number intended by the Poet) before ſhe cenſure the Author or me: Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſhe concludes her ſelf one of the Poets Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue. And having thus (with what conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſuccinctneſs I could) apologiz'd for us both, I commend the Book to thy reading and civill ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation, ſubmitting it to thy benevolent and candid conſtruction: Subſcribing alſo my ſelf to be</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy well-wiſhing friend, <hi>Tho: Harvey.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:115715:5"/>
            <head>TO The Candid and Intelligent <hi>Women Readers.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>LADIES,</salute>
            </opener>
            <l>THat rather unto Women, then to Men</l>
            <l>I dedicate theſe iſſues of my Pen,</l>
            <l>I muſt Apologize ere I begin,</l>
            <l>For Féeminines are moſt concern'd therein;</l>
            <l>Their Loves, their Paſſions, their Infirmities</l>
            <l>Too much diſclos'd to ſupercilious eyes.</l>
            <l>Yet (Ladies) be not angry, nor the Book</l>
            <l>With Prejudice or Paſſion overlook.</l>
            <l>There's ſomething in it worth your beſt regard;</l>
            <l>
               <hi>All Women</hi> are not cenſur'd by the Bard,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Ill Women</hi> onely: Theſe illuſtre thoſe,</l>
            <l>As Foiles the Diamonds, or as Thornes the Roſe.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>The honourer of your Vertues, <hi>Tho: Harvey.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115715:5"/>
            <head>THE ECLOGUES OF BAPTIST MANTUAN</head>
            <byline>Engliſhed by <hi>Tho: Harvey.</hi>
            </byline>
            <div type="eclogue">
               <head>ECLOGUE I. <hi>Treating of honeſt Love and its happy ſucceſs</hi> Intituled FAUSTUS.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <l>Here <hi>Fortunatus</hi> doth deſire</l>
                  <l>To talk of Love: his reaſons why.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fauſtus</hi> aſſents; declares his fire,</l>
                  <l>His Bride and Epithalamy.</l>
               </argument>
               <stage>The Speakers <hi>Fortunatus</hi> and <hi>Fauſtus.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fo.</speaker>
                  <l>I Pray thee <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> while the cattel chew</l>
                  <l>In the cool ſhade their cud; let us review</l>
                  <l>Our former loves? leſt idle while we ſtay,</l>
                  <l>Or fall aſleep, ſome cruel beaſts of prey</l>
                  <l>Amid the rip'ned Corn that ſlily creep</l>
                  <l>Seize on our Cattel: better wake then ſleep.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fauſt.</speaker>
                  <l>This place, this tree where-under we reſide,</l>
                  <l>Well knows what cares me griev'd, what ſires me fry'd,</l>
                  <l>Three years, or (as I take it) four years paſt.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:115715:6"/>But ſith thou pleaſeſt, ſith thou leiſure haſt,</l>
                  <l>From the beginning (here while we repoſe)</l>
                  <l>The Matter and the Manner I'le diſcloſe.</l>
                  <l>Here on theſe Plaines while I my Cattel fed,</l>
                  <l>When firſt Loves flames aſſail'd mine heart-mine head,</l>
                  <l>Upon my Coat outſpread (full many a day)</l>
                  <l>Caſt careleſs on the ground I cureleſs lay,</l>
                  <l>With ſighes and tears my ſad—ſad fates recounting,</l>
                  <l>No reſt to me, no labour ſweet amounting;</l>
                  <l>Dull were my Senſes in my ſenſeleſs breaſt,</l>
                  <l>My reſtleſs minde was buried in unreſt.</l>
                  <l>Like ſick mens ſtomachs, whoſe dull appetite</l>
                  <l>No Cates to feed, no delicates invite:</l>
                  <l>My Poeſie deceas'd, no Pipe of mine</l>
                  <l>Sounded at all; I did my Bowe decline:</l>
                  <l>My Sling was hateful, hateful were my Dogs,</l>
                  <l>Hateful was Fowling, Nutting; All were clogs.</l>
                  <l>To weave a twiggen Basket, or with Hook</l>
                  <l>To catch the Fiſh, or Sparrows neſts to look,</l>
                  <l>To wreſtle, or with fingers up to ſport</l>
                  <l>At Odde or Even (ah) I car'd not for't,</l>
                  <l>Though pleaſing one, while I (my ſelf above)</l>
                  <l>Was uninfected with this ſickneſs, Love.</l>
                  <l>But irkſome are thoſe ſports which pleas'd of late;</l>
                  <l>To gather Strawberries and Grapes, I hate.</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Philomel</hi> I mourn'd, when ſhe with food</l>
                  <l>Returning in her beak to feed her brood,</l>
                  <l>Findes robb'd her Neſt, and emptied of her young;</l>
                  <l>Which ſeeing, ſhe (poor wretch) with ſorrow ſtung</l>
                  <l>Lets fall the meat, and ſits (as if forlorn)</l>
                  <l>Right o're againſt her Neſt upon ſome Thorn;</l>
                  <l>Where, in ſad tunes and melancholly tones</l>
                  <l>Her hapleſs ſelf, her Mate and young bemones.</l>
                  <l>Or as when ſome fair Heifer is bereft</l>
                  <l>Of her firſt Calf (which in a Brake ſhe left)</l>
                  <l>When, after ſhe hath rang'd the groves, the grounds,</l>
                  <l>Making them all re eccho with the ſounds</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:115715:6"/>Of her loud lowing; down ſhe ſits alone</l>
                  <l>In ſome ſad ſhape at laſt, and gives a grone,</l>
                  <l>Careleſs of food, ſitting as if forſook,</l>
                  <l>Nor eating graſs, nor drinking of the brook.</l>
                  <l>But why with vain circuities am I</l>
                  <l>So long, ſo tedious? ſith I loſe thereby</l>
                  <l>My words, my time, while here and there I glance,</l>
                  <l>Leaving the Subſtance for the Circumſtance.</l>
                  <l>The ſumme is this: I liv'd againſt my will.</l>
                  <l>Now the particulars of this mine ill,</l>
                  <l>If thou perhaps wouldſt know, thou then maiſt ſay't,</l>
                  <l>What wind (O <hi>Fauſtus</hi>) drove thee to this ſtrait?</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Galla</hi> me (for I'le confeſs the truth</l>
                  <l>To thee my <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> deareſt youth)</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Galla</hi> me with her ſerener ſhine,</l>
                  <l>With her moſt ſweet aſpect ſo did intwine,</l>
                  <l>So did intangle, as the Spider draws</l>
                  <l>The captiv'd Fly ſurrounded in her claws.</l>
                  <l>For her fair face was ruddy, plump and round:</l>
                  <l>And though one eye did ſeem almoſt unſound;</l>
                  <l>Yet while I did admire her face, her years,</l>
                  <l>I ſaid, <hi>Diana's</hi> beauty lack'd of hers.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fo.</speaker>
                  <l>Love mocks the Senſes, blindes our eyes, beguiles</l>
                  <l>Our Souls, befools us with bewitching wiles.</l>
                  <l>I think ſome Devil, creeping in our veins,</l>
                  <l>Inflames our hearts, and ſets on ſire our reins,</l>
                  <l>Our mindes unhingeth, and our thoughts diſtracts.</l>
                  <l>Nor is this Love (which thus theſe things tranſacts)</l>
                  <l>A God, as ſome affirm: I rather gueſs</l>
                  <l>It is an Errour, and a bitterneſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Adde, that I hopeleſs was t'injoy my Love,</l>
                  <l>Though ſhe compaſſionate and kinde did prove;</l>
                  <l>Though ſhe with ſignes and glances of her eyes</l>
                  <l>Expreſs'd her love with mine to ſympathize.</l>
                  <l>For alwayes whereſoere ſhe went, there went</l>
                  <l>Her married Siſter, ſpy-like alwayes ſent;</l>
                  <l>Her crabbed Mother follow'd: Thus our fires</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:115715:7"/>Were ſtill oppos'd with oppoſite deſires;</l>
                  <l>Like Cat and Rat: This ſeeks for meat, and that</l>
                  <l>Quick ſighted guards the chinks to catch the Rat.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fo.</speaker>
                  <l>Full bellies Faſts commend; and thoſe are worſt</l>
                  <l>Unto the thirſty, that endure no thirſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>'Twas Harveſt; and full time with crooked hook</l>
                  <l>To reap the Corn, the fields did yellow look</l>
                  <l>With ripened Barley: Then (as 'twas their uſe)</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Galla</hi>'s Mother did her ſelf produce</l>
                  <l>With her two Daughters, here and there to glean</l>
                  <l>What Corn the Reapers had not gather'd clean.</l>
                  <l>For or her Mother knew not of our flame,</l>
                  <l>Or did diſſemble that ſhe knew the ſame.</l>
                  <l>I think ſhe did diſſemble: For ſhe knew</l>
                  <l>(Though from her ſight my tokens I withdrew)</l>
                  <l>I gave her Daughter (her good will to get)</l>
                  <l>A pair of Pidgeons, and a Leveret.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fo.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis onely poverty that doth oppoſe</l>
                  <l>Good natures and good manners: Theſe and thoſe</l>
                  <l>It ſhames; 'tis too propenſe for any vice,</l>
                  <l>And doth to wickedneſs, to ſins intice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>The Maid was gleaning Corn; and, as before,</l>
                  <l>The more I went, ſhe follow'd me the more.</l>
                  <l>Her feet were bare, her boſome looſely dreſt,</l>
                  <l>Her arms half naked, and in all the reſt,</l>
                  <l>Befitting Summers heat ſhe was yclad;</l>
                  <l>Green boughes in wreath upon her head ſhe had</l>
                  <l>To ſhade her from the Sun, leſt burn'd thereby</l>
                  <l>Her face ſhould leſs delight a Lovers eye.</l>
                  <l>Now cloſe behinde me, ſometimes near my ſide</l>
                  <l>She glean'd the Corn, I did of purpoſe ſlide.</l>
                  <l>A woman can nor conquer, nor defer,</l>
                  <l>Nor hide her love; ſuch levity's in her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fo.</speaker>
                  <l>All Lovers have their levity; nor have</l>
                  <l>This frailty women onely, but the grave,</l>
                  <l>The great, the wiſe, they that would ſeem t'excel</l>
                  <l>All other mortals, have this fault as well.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:115715:7"/>They that are clad with Robes of Tyrian dye,</l>
                  <l>That walk in State, in King-like Majeſty.</l>
                  <l>Affected ſo thou waſt then her more mad,</l>
                  <l>Perhaps more light: The Maid (no doubt) was glad</l>
                  <l>To glean the Corn was given her; but thou</l>
                  <l>Didd'ſt give the Corn: Speak, who was maddeſt now?</l>
                  <l>But on. I muſt my turn in talking keep,</l>
                  <l>Leſt peradventure elſe I fall aſleep.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>When us her peeviſh Mother did behold,</l>
                  <l>She took it ill, and thus began to ſcold;</l>
                  <l>Now whither go'ſt thou? why do'ſt wander from</l>
                  <l>Thy company? Come hither <hi>Galla,</hi> come.</l>
                  <l>Here near theſe Alders is a cooling ſhade,</l>
                  <l>The milder aire here gently doth invade</l>
                  <l>The trembling leaves with murmurs (pleaſing prate)</l>
                  <l>Here gentle gales refreſh, refrigerate.</l>
                  <l>O hateful voice unto mine ears (ſaid I)</l>
                  <l>Go, go ye ſtrongeſt winds that ſwifteſt flie,</l>
                  <l>Go with a miſchief, and that voice diſperſe;</l>
                  <l>If any Shepherd be ſo much averſe,</l>
                  <l>As when his Sheep to paſture forth he leads,</l>
                  <l>He would not ſuffer them to graſe the Meads:</l>
                  <l>Or fed, ſhould drive them to the Rivers brink,</l>
                  <l>And then deny their thirſty mouthes to drink;</l>
                  <l>Would not, O would not you that Shepherd call</l>
                  <l>Hard-hearted, mercileſs, unnaturall?</l>
                  <l>That voice ſeem'd worſe to me, then when in ire</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jove</hi> rattles out his Thunders mixt with fire;</l>
                  <l>Or as when angry with our Earth, the Skies</l>
                  <l>Pour Cataracts of Waters from their eyes.</l>
                  <l>I could not chooſe, though loth I was to frown:</l>
                  <l>The Maid her vail from under (which hung down</l>
                  <l>Over her eye brows) me beheld the while,</l>
                  <l>And glanc'd upon me with a pleaſing ſmile.</l>
                  <l>Which when her pettiſh Mother did yken,</l>
                  <l>She <hi>Calla</hi> call'd, <hi>Galla</hi> ſhe call'd agen.</l>
                  <l>But on her gleaning, <hi>Galla</hi> more intent,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:115715:8"/>Heeds not her words: And as I forward went</l>
                  <l>She follow'd, as by ſteps, ſo by deſire;</l>
                  <l>I careful then to ſet her ſpark on fire,</l>
                  <l>(For ſubtile Love with cunning Complements</l>
                  <l>Vents fine deceits, and pretty frauds invents)</l>
                  <l>By ſinging now, and then with hollowing</l>
                  <l>Chearing the Reapers, I conceal'd the thing,</l>
                  <l>That Mother both, and Siſter therewithall</l>
                  <l>Might think that <hi>Galla</hi> did not hear their call.</l>
                  <l>I put the Thorns aſide, leſt they ſhould meet</l>
                  <l>The Maidens naked legs, and tender feet.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fo.</speaker>
                  <l>All Lovers are inſlav'd, and captiv'd all,</l>
                  <l>With yielding necks they bear the yoke of thrall:</l>
                  <l>Their backs bear ſharp-ſweet ſtripes, and ſuch as prick,</l>
                  <l>Oxe-like they draw the Plough, yet never kick.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſee thou then haſt ſomething known of Love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fo.</speaker>
                  <l>O 'tis a Common evil, it doth move</l>
                  <l>In ev'ry ſphere; the wiſeſt man that is</l>
                  <l>One time or other hath been mad in this.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fo.</speaker>
                  <l>This then ſo bad a good, ſo ſweet a ſowre</l>
                  <l>Increas'd more cruell ev'ry day and hour,</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Titans</hi> ſcorching heat till noon be paſt.</l>
                  <l>At length I pallid look'd like one agaſt,</l>
                  <l>Like a Lymphatick or a Frantick Ghoſt,</l>
                  <l>My Memory, my Sleep at laſt were loſt.</l>
                  <l>Nor was it difficult my grief to know,</l>
                  <l>The Face, the Minde, the Look the love doth ſhow:</l>
                  <l>Which when my Father found, he grew more kinde</l>
                  <l>Then was his uſe: perhaps he call'd to minde</l>
                  <l>His own experiments of love, whoſe fate</l>
                  <l>Made him anothers love commiſerate.</l>
                  <l>At length indulgent he thus kindly ſaid,</l>
                  <l>Tell, <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> tell me, ſpeak, be not afraid,</l>
                  <l>What troubles thee? what thoughts perplex thy breaſt?</l>
                  <l>Poor Boy, thy very looks doe Love atteſt;</l>
                  <l>Come, tell me; nor be baſhful to declare</l>
                  <l>To me thy Father what thy ſorrows are.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:115715:8"/>
                  <speaker>Fo.</speaker>
                  <l>Though Fathers to their Sons may ſeem auſtere,</l>
                  <l>Though (ſupercilious) they may look ſevere,</l>
                  <l>Yet ever candid is their minde, their will</l>
                  <l>Is ever loving and indulgent ſtill.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>When thus my Father had himſelf expreſs'd,</l>
                  <l>I fully, freely my deſires confeſs'd.</l>
                  <l>I crav'd his aid, he promis'd it; and e're</l>
                  <l>The Winter froſts did in the fields appear,</l>
                  <l>My Parents and the Maids conſented both,</l>
                  <l>And her to me did ſolemnly betroth.</l>
                  <l>Yet could I not without ſome witneſs by</l>
                  <l>Be near the Maid, or in her company.</l>
                  <l>Inflam'd the while with thirſt, I gaping ſtood,</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Tantalus</hi> amid the Chryſtal flood.</l>
                  <l>How often, O! have I ſent home the Plow</l>
                  <l>Alone with th'Oxen (or I car'd not how)</l>
                  <l>While to my Dear I went, in hope to finde</l>
                  <l>All gone from home, her ſolely left behinde?</l>
                  <l>I wanted not excuſes, nor pretence</l>
                  <l>Of wanting ſomething for convenience;</l>
                  <l>Plough-handle, Harrows, Plough-ſtaff, Thongs or Yoke,</l>
                  <l>And though all wanting were for which I ſpoke</l>
                  <l>At the Maids Fathers houſe, yet (truth to grant)</l>
                  <l>I nothing but the Maid her ſelf did want.</l>
                  <l>I was not wanting to my ſelf; for I</l>
                  <l>Reſum'd my former ſports, and did apply</l>
                  <l>My ſelf to Fiſhing, Fowling, Hunting, and</l>
                  <l>What e're I took with mine induſtrious hand,</l>
                  <l>Or caught by chance, the Maid did thither draw,</l>
                  <l>I was a moſt officious Son in law.</l>
                  <l>At midnight once I ſtealing through the door</l>
                  <l>(For ſo the Maid and I agreed before)</l>
                  <l>The Dogs deſcri'd me, took me for a Thief,</l>
                  <l>Upon me fell: I forc'd (for my relief)</l>
                  <l>Leap'd o're an high grown hedge without demurs,</l>
                  <l>But ſcarce ſcap'd biting of thoſe barking Curs,</l>
                  <l>And thus with theſe delights (befit a Lover)</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:115715:9"/>At length (though long) we paſt that Winter over.</l>
                  <l>The Spring return'd, perfum'd with Eglantine,</l>
                  <l>Green grew the Trees, and flouriſhing the Vine.</l>
                  <l>Now <hi>Ceres</hi> ruſſel'd in her briſtling Corn</l>
                  <l>With pendant eares; and when it muſt be ſhorn</l>
                  <l>The Mower thinks; for nightly now the skies</l>
                  <l>With Glow-worms ſhine, and gliſt'ring Butterflies:</l>
                  <l>Loe now my Marriage, now my genial day</l>
                  <l>Approach'd, appear'd; when I (without delay)</l>
                  <l>The Maid eſpous'd; what need I more recite?</l>
                  <l>At night we found our long expected night,</l>
                  <l>When with ſucceſsful winds (thank <hi>Hymen</hi> for't)</l>
                  <l>My ſhip arriv'd at the deſired Port.</l>
                  <l>Then having kill'd an Oxe, we did diſplay,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe it was a double Holy-day,</l>
                  <l>A double Feaſt; the Tables full were ſpread,</l>
                  <l>Under a broad green Tree, with meat and bread.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oenophilus</hi> was there, who fill'd with wine,</l>
                  <l>Made welcome ſports for all that there did dine;</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Tonius;</hi> whoſe Pipe of Boxen wood</l>
                  <l>Bor'd full of holes, made Muſick paſſing good.</l>
                  <l>At length, when all had eat and drank their fill,</l>
                  <l>His party-coloured bagge and Pipe moſt ſhrill</l>
                  <l>He took; his ruddy cheeks began to ſwell,</l>
                  <l>His eyes to ſtare, his eye-lids roſe and fell.</l>
                  <l>Then with an oft and deep extracted blaſt</l>
                  <l>From's hollow lungs, the bagge's inflate at laſt,</l>
                  <l>Which with his elbow ſqueez'd, and having found</l>
                  <l>Vent through the Pipe, did make the Pipe reſound.</l>
                  <l>Now here, now there his nimble finges skip</l>
                  <l>From top to bottom, from his hand t'his lip;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe jolly Muſick all the Yonkers calls</l>
                  <l>Away to Dancing from their Feſtivals.</l>
                  <l>Where on the Green, that day was ſweetly ſpent</l>
                  <l>In Piping, Dancing, Sporting, Merriment.</l>
                  <l>And now three years are paſt, the fourth is nigh,</l>
                  <l>Since chanted was mine Epithalamy.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:115715:9"/>Thus our delightful dayes with poſting houres</l>
                  <l>Are quickly paſt; what pleaſeth, flies, what lowres,</l>
                  <l>Adheres more cloſe, and longer doth abide</l>
                  <l>Then twenty dayes of jollity beſide.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fo</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fauſtus</hi> do'ſt ſee? look how the Cattel break</l>
                  <l>Into the Vineyards, while we ſporting ſpeak,</l>
                  <l>We muſt be gone; leſt if we longer ſtay,</l>
                  <l>Our Purſes for the Treſpaſs ſoundly pay.</l>
               </sp>
               <trailer>The End of the firſt Eclogue.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="eclogue">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:115715:10"/>
               <head>ECLOGUE II. <hi>Treating of the Madneſs of Love.</hi> Intituled FORTUNATUS.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <l>Firſt <hi>Fortunatus</hi> doth relate</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Po</hi>'s inundation, with th'event.</l>
                  <l>Next of <hi>Amyntas</hi> Love and Fate</l>
                  <l>He treats, and doth his caſe lament.</l>
               </argument>
               <stage>The Speakers <hi>Fortunatus</hi> and <hi>Fauſtus.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fauſt.</speaker>
                  <l>WHy com'ſt ſo late? what kept thee thus from hence</l>
                  <l>So long a while? Now 'tis a ſe'night ſince</l>
                  <l>Thy flock was here: Where do'ſt thy Cattel keep?</l>
                  <l>What, are theſe Paſtures hurtful for thy Sheep?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fort.</speaker>
                  <l>No, <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> no: The River <hi>Po</hi> which glides</l>
                  <l>With ſilver ſtreams along our Meadows ſides,</l>
                  <l>Grew late ſo proud, that uncontroll'd he laves</l>
                  <l>The levell'd Banks with his inſulting Waves.</l>
                  <l>We leaving then the Flock, and careleſs of it,</l>
                  <l>Urg'd by the publick and our private profit,</l>
                  <l>By day, by night did labour to make good</l>
                  <l>The ruin'd banks againſt the raging flood.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Our <hi>Tityrus,</hi> who ſweetly ſang the praiſe</l>
                  <l>Of Fields and Paſtures in his learned Layes,</l>
                  <l>Reports for certain; That the River <hi>Po</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Brings oft ill fortune with its overflow.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fo.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis true perhaps, when unindifferent</l>
                  <l>The River with unlimited extent</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:115715:10"/>Doth timeleſs, meanleſs, boundleſs floods repeat,</l>
                  <l>High ſwelling on a ſudden, after heat.</l>
                  <l>And now's the time: For now the Winter ſnow</l>
                  <l>From Hills high tops diſſolves, and runs below,</l>
                  <l>Which empty Rivers fills. And thus thoſe Hills</l>
                  <l>Unload themſelves, and load the leſſer Rills;</l>
                  <l>Theſe load the Rivers, and the Rivers caſe</l>
                  <l>Themſelves, and are disburthen'd in the Seas.</l>
                  <l>Men do the like; each doth himſelf unpack,</l>
                  <l>And caſts the burthen on anothers back.</l>
                  <l>But now the River with a fair retreat</l>
                  <l>Is recontracted in its proper ſeat.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>True: but (a wonder 'tis to ſpeak) when <hi>Po</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Did ebbe, our Brook the more did overflow:</l>
                  <l>The City ſwims, the Cellars are afloat,</l>
                  <l>They row unto the veſſels in a Boat:</l>
                  <l>The ſervant, ſent to draw for ſuch as dine,</l>
                  <l>Laughs while he ſwims unto the Butts of Wine.</l>
                  <l>And from the Cellars deep and wat'ry Vault,</l>
                  <l>A great black Jack of Wine at length is brought.</l>
                  <l>Thus Citizens, though born they ſeem (perhaps)</l>
                  <l>To better fortunes, have ſome after-claps:</l>
                  <l>They many diſcommodities abide,</l>
                  <l>Yea manifold ſometimes, and great beſide.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fo.</speaker>
                  <l>No profit here, but ſome diſprofit brings,</l>
                  <l>(Like Bees, that with their honey have their ſtings)</l>
                  <l>Here's nothing perfect; fulneſs here doth want,</l>
                  <l>All joyes have here ſome ſad Concomitant.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Thus farre <hi>Eridanus.</hi> And now from <hi>Po</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Let's on, and chant our loves before we go.</l>
                  <l>Sith now fair <hi>Venus</hi> all things moves to mirth,</l>
                  <l>The skies are clear and warm; the verdant earth</l>
                  <l>Is clad in green, the Birds with vernal ſong</l>
                  <l>Now clear the fields, and all are big with yong.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fo.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou thine haſt chanted: Others, not mine own</l>
                  <l>I will relate; yet ones, to thee well known,</l>
                  <l>A Shepherds; once well known he was to thee,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:115715:11"/>While from inchanting <hi>Venus</hi> he was free:</l>
                  <l>That I may teach, and (teaching) plainly prove,</l>
                  <l>That nothing is more violent then Love.</l>
                  <l>Pooreſt <hi>Amyntas,</hi> but unhappy more,</l>
                  <l>Under ſome ill aſpected <hi>Planet bore,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Driving ſix Bullocks, Heifers ſix to graſs,</l>
                  <l>With a ſtout Bull that their Conducter was,</l>
                  <l>Chief Captain of the Drove; at laſt did come</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Coitus,</hi> where, with a Snow-like ſome</l>
                  <l>The ſilver ſtream of <hi>Mincius</hi> doth dye</l>
                  <l>The Meadows, as it ſwiftly runneth by</l>
                  <l>A new built Caſtle, whoſe high walls around</l>
                  <l>With Turrets and with Battlements are crown'd,</l>
                  <l>Is <hi>Coitus;</hi> built in a Mooriſh ſoil,</l>
                  <l>But near the River, a moſt ſtately Pile.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Amyntas</hi> here repoſing (where the Vine</l>
                  <l>With large imbraces doth the Trees intwine</l>
                  <l>Near to the glaſſy River, where it made</l>
                  <l>Along the Bank an over-hanging ſhade)</l>
                  <l>Sought to ſurpriſe with angling Rod and Hook</l>
                  <l>The ſilver Fiſhes in the Chryſtal Brook.</l>
                  <l>'Twas Harveſt time; and <hi>Titans</hi> ſcorching force</l>
                  <l>Had ſing'd the fields: The Nightingale was hoarſe,</l>
                  <l>And ceas'd to ſing: Nor could the Sheep by day</l>
                  <l>Be fed with graſs, becauſe 'twas burn'd away:</l>
                  <l>Nor were the skipping Graſhoppers (though few)</l>
                  <l>Refreſh'd with moiſture of the nigthly dew.</l>
                  <l>But on the waters while he was intent,</l>
                  <l>And in a fruitleſs ſport his ſtudy ſpent,</l>
                  <l>The Bull (as is reported) ſtung at firſt</l>
                  <l>With Waſps, next cours'd with Dogs, with Curs accurſt,</l>
                  <l>Then hid by thieviſh Souldiers in a grove,</l>
                  <l>At laſt was loſt, and vaniſh'd from the Drove.</l>
                  <l>Which when <hi>Amyntas</hi> knew, he climb'd an hill,</l>
                  <l>And looking round about him, with a ſhrill</l>
                  <l>And hollow voice he call'd the Bull: but when</l>
                  <l>With long ſurvey the Bull he could not ken.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:115715:11"/>When loſt he found his labour, up he takes</l>
                  <l>His Bow and Quiver, and purſuance makes</l>
                  <l>After the Bull through wayes unknown and known</l>
                  <l>Him ſeeking all the Paſtures up and down,</l>
                  <l>Among the Stalls of Beaſts and Cotes of Sheep,</l>
                  <l>Among thine hills <hi>Benacus;</hi> through the deep</l>
                  <l>Fat Olive fields, through grounds beſet (by line)</l>
                  <l>With frondent Fig trees, and the fruitful Vine.</l>
                  <l>He came at length unto the lofty Creſt</l>
                  <l>Of an high Mountain (higher then the reſt)</l>
                  <l>Where Rocks of Sulphur are, which doth reflect</l>
                  <l>Upon <hi>Benacus</hi> with a fair proſpect,</l>
                  <l>Whence all the Meadows here and there that lie</l>
                  <l>Preſented are apparent to your eye.</l>
                  <l>'Twas then S. <hi>Peters</hi> Feſtival, and there</l>
                  <l>Under a broad green Elme aſſembled were</l>
                  <l>From all the villages a luſty Crew</l>
                  <l>Of youthful Men and Maids, who thither drew</l>
                  <l>When all had din'd: where, when the Pipe did ſound</l>
                  <l>They mixt together, danc'd a jolly round.</l>
                  <l>The Ruſticks are a people of that guiſe,</l>
                  <l>Whom no Civility can civilize:</l>
                  <l>A reſtleſs and indomitable Creature,</l>
                  <l>Whom neither Art can qualife nor Nature.</l>
                  <l>They love to labour, ſweating doth them pleaſe;</l>
                  <l>On Holy dayes (when others take their eaſe)</l>
                  <l>The morning paſt they gormandiſe and feaſt,</l>
                  <l>Impatient of hunger and of reſt.</l>
                  <l>And when their Paunch is cramm'd, and dinner done,</l>
                  <l>Hearing the Pipe, away to the th' Elme they run:</l>
                  <l>Here rageth one, another danceth there,</l>
                  <l>Who like an Oxe moſt nimbly doth careero;</l>
                  <l>And with his clouted Shoon, and lob-like lond</l>
                  <l>He tears and tires that Earth, which with his goad,</l>
                  <l>His Plough and Harrows, 'twere a ſin (they ſay)</l>
                  <l>To till or teare upon an Holy day:</l>
                  <l>And all that day he ſpends, till night recalls.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:115715:12"/>In bonny Belly cheer and Bacchanals,</l>
                  <l>With Singing, Laughing, Dancing, merrily,</l>
                  <l>Carouſing till the Pots and Cups be dry.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Fool, why do'ſt prattle thus? Thou do'ſt condemn</l>
                  <l>The Countrey ſports, when thou art one of them:</l>
                  <l>Thou to thy friends art bad, but (fooliſh Elſe)</l>
                  <l>In this th'art worſe, and worſt unto thy ſelfe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fo.</speaker>
                  <l>I did but jeſt. Come, let's proceed to tell</l>
                  <l>Of our <hi>Amyntas,</hi> and what him befell.</l>
                  <l>He coming thither in the cooling ſhade,</l>
                  <l>And leaning on his ſtaff of Maple made,</l>
                  <l>There ſtopp'd his paſſage, there his journey ſtaid,</l>
                  <l>Until the ſcorching heat were more allaid.</l>
                  <l>Ah hapleſs Lad! though in the ſhade thou lie,</l>
                  <l>A greater heat then <hi>Titans</hi> will thee frie.</l>
                  <l>Shut, ſhut thine eyes; leſt, Oh if they diſmount,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſee <hi>Diana</hi> naked in the Fount.</l>
                  <l>Stop, ſtop thine ears; O liſten not at all</l>
                  <l>To the bewitching <hi>Syrens</hi> flatt'ring call.</l>
                  <l>Thou like <hi>Narciſſus</hi> art: <hi>Narciſſus</hi> firſt</l>
                  <l>But ſeeking at the Found to quench his thirſt,</l>
                  <l>Thirſted the more. And thou, while thou do'ſt fly</l>
                  <l>An outward heat, with inward flames wilt fry.</l>
                  <l>O how much, how much better had it been</l>
                  <l>(If ſo thy fates had pleas'd) t'have never ſeen</l>
                  <l>That luckeſs Bull, t'have preſently return'd</l>
                  <l>To th'other Cattel (e're thou thus had'ſt burn'd)</l>
                  <l>T'have kept thoſe heifers that were left behinde,</l>
                  <l>T'have loſt thy Bull with a contented minde;</l>
                  <l>Rather, then while thy labour thou do'ſt waſte,</l>
                  <l>Nothing to loſe, to loſe thy ſelf at laſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>But after loſſes who becomes not wiſe?</l>
                  <l>We ſhould not after, but before, adviſe:</l>
                  <l>Vain is all after-counſel, and as vain</l>
                  <l>As, after fruits are ripe, a ſhower of rain.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fo.</speaker>
                  <l>Among the Maiden company was one,</l>
                  <l>One fairer then the reſt, whoſe beauty ſhone</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:115715:12"/>Amid her flaxen Treſſes, nearly dreſt,</l>
                  <l>A Virgin fairer, taller then the reſt,</l>
                  <l>Some twenty years of age, of lovely face,</l>
                  <l>One, that the City Beauties would diſgrace</l>
                  <l>If but conteſting, or compar'd with them,</l>
                  <l>For Beauty, ſhe would win the Diadem</l>
                  <l>From all the City Nymphs: A fillet round</l>
                  <l>Beſet with golden glitt'ring Aglets bound</l>
                  <l>Her Temples; whence a pendant vail inclos'd</l>
                  <l>Her ſhoulders, which amid her breaſts repos'd,</l>
                  <l>There faſt'ned with a yellow tach, and here</l>
                  <l>Clos'd with an iron button ſhining cleere;</l>
                  <l>A linnen garment white ſhe wore, and new,</l>
                  <l>Laid thick of pleats, moſt comely to the view,</l>
                  <l>Hanging ſo long, ſo low, that it did meet,</l>
                  <l>And ſweep the ground beneath her tender feet.</l>
                  <l>Aſſoon as her <hi>Amyntas</hi> did eſpy,</l>
                  <l>He periſh'd by the ſight: his raviſh'd eye</l>
                  <l>Ingulph'd fierce flames: his amorous deſire</l>
                  <l>Suck'd in a ſecret unſuſpected fire;</l>
                  <l>A fire that having once inflam'd his heart,</l>
                  <l>Could nor in whole b'extinguiſh'd, nor in part</l>
                  <l>By floods of water, or by ſhowres of rain:</l>
                  <l>Vain was Herbs force, and Magick Spells were vain.</l>
                  <l>Forgetful of his flocks, and careleſs frown</l>
                  <l>Of his domeſtick things (as not his own)</l>
                  <l>He's all inflam'd, and (empti'd of delights)</l>
                  <l>Expends the long, the melancholly nights</l>
                  <l>In bitterneſs and mourning: O how oft,</l>
                  <l>Aſſaying with kinde words, and language ſoft,</l>
                  <l>To quench his raging flame, to cool his heat,</l>
                  <l>His frantick, furious heat, did I repeat</l>
                  <l>My words, and thus did ſay, Diſtreſſed Boy,</l>
                  <l>Deſerving pity, what doth thee deſtroy.</l>
                  <l>What God in theſe perplexities involv'd</l>
                  <l>Thy troubled minde? But (ah) 'tis ſoon reſolv'd:</l>
                  <l>It was not God, it was the Devil rather,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:115715:13"/>Satan himſelf, the worſt of all; the Father</l>
                  <l>Of all thoſe wicked ſpirits<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> which they ſay</l>
                  <l>In thrice three nights, atd thrice a trebled day</l>
                  <l>From the Supernall Heavens headlong fell</l>
                  <l>To th' Earth, or lower, to the loweſt hell.</l>
                  <l>Tell me, go too: when thou did'ſt any know</l>
                  <l>Or doſt remember any that did grow</l>
                  <l>To wealth or credit thus, that in this wiſe</l>
                  <l>Inlarg'd his houſe, or did to greatneſſe riſe?</l>
                  <l>That thus with greater heaps of Corn did fill</l>
                  <l>His garners, or more ameld Fields did till?</l>
                  <l>That by ſuch courſes did increaſe his Flock,</l>
                  <l>Or wiſh more Cattle did his paſtures ſtock?</l>
                  <l>Among ſo many multitudes of Nations</l>
                  <l>That on the ſpacious Earth have habitations</l>
                  <l>Are ſome, who to their execrable Feaſts</l>
                  <l>Serve up mens Bodies for their bloody gueſts,</l>
                  <l>Who tear them with their teeth, and as their Food</l>
                  <l>Devour their Fleſh: There are I ſay a brood</l>
                  <l>Of ſuch curſt vipers, whom the furies haunt,</l>
                  <l>And with ſo many miſchiefes them inchant.</l>
                  <l>But ther's no kind ſo ſavage, none ſo bad</l>
                  <l>No Nation's there ſo barbarous, ſo mad,</l>
                  <l>But as an execrable thing doth hate</l>
                  <l>To be by love of women Captivate.</l>
                  <l>Hence come contentions, hence comes ſtrife and warrs,</l>
                  <l>And ofttimes death with many bloody ſcarrs:</l>
                  <l>Hence Cities have been ruin'd, raz'd their wall:</l>
                  <l>Yea, the ſage Lawes, and ſolemn decretalls</l>
                  <l>Bound in red leather-volumes diſapprove</l>
                  <l>This wanton ſin, and hate unlawfull love.</l>
                  <l>When thus <hi>Amyntas</hi> heard me ſpeak of Lawes</l>
                  <l>He made this anſwer (and without a pauſe,</l>
                  <l>For he was civiliz'd, and did converſe</l>
                  <l>Within the City) Thou do'ſt this rehearſe</l>
                  <l>Quoth he, that by theſe warnings thou might'ſt ſeem</l>
                  <l>Wiſe, Circumſpect, and of diſcreet eſteem:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:115715:13"/>Thus thinking to be thought t'excell the wiſe</l>
                  <l>The ſupercilious <hi>Catoes</hi> for adviſe.</l>
                  <l>This errour, this wiſe madneſs reigns too much<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Himſelf man flatters, and would fain be ſuch</l>
                  <l>As he conceits himſelf, he fain would ſeem</l>
                  <l>A witty Creature, of a vaſt eſteem:</l>
                  <l>But unadviſed yet he ſpreads, he ſets</l>
                  <l>To catch himſelf a thouſand ſnares and Nets,</l>
                  <l>And oftentimes himſelf at unawares</l>
                  <l>Falls in his own digg'd pits, his ownrſpread ſnares.</l>
                  <l>Once he was free, but brought himſelf in thrall,</l>
                  <l>And made the ſlaviſh yok<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> he draw withall,</l>
                  <l>That is the burden of the Lawes (For I)</l>
                  <l>Have ſeen thoſe volumes) which ſo pond'rous lie,</l>
                  <l>That neither our Forefathers, nor their heirs,</l>
                  <l>Nor we, nor our Poſterity, nor theirs</l>
                  <l>Could, or can ever keep in act or awe</l>
                  <l>According to the letter of the Law.</l>
                  <l>Behold how fooliſh is Mans wiſdom; Man</l>
                  <l>At heaven levells, and believes he can</l>
                  <l>Tranſcend the Starres, or in a Ranck with them</l>
                  <l>Inveſted, wear a ſtar-like Diadem,</l>
                  <l>When as his body dead, perhaps his ſoul</l>
                  <l>May tranſmigrate into ſome winged foul,</l>
                  <l>And Feather'd ſo may ſore aloft, and fly</l>
                  <l>With nimble plumes amid the middle sky.</l>
                  <l>Thus He: Then I reply'd, why do'ſt repine?</l>
                  <l>Why do'ſt thus ſnarle? The Lawes are things divine.</l>
                  <l>God is their Author, them to diſobey</l>
                  <l>Doth too-too great impiety bewray.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Theſe arguments are great, and treat (like Kings)</l>
                  <l>Of weighty matters, of myſterious things.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fo.</speaker>
                  <l>Why what do'ſt think I was; though now ('tis true)</l>
                  <l>My Coat is patch'd, my face of ſordid hue,</l>
                  <l>Yet then in ſtrength, wit, language I was rare,</l>
                  <l>None other Shepheard could with me compare.</l>
                  <l>And now, if thou would'ſt go with Front erect,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:115715:14"/>With upright body, thou for thine aſpect,</l>
                  <l>For thy comportment, ſhalt in ſome degree</l>
                  <l>Another <hi>Marius</hi> or <hi>Carbo</hi> be.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fo.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Amyntas</hi> thus reprov'd, did thus reply;</l>
                  <l>God envy'd Man created, when his eye</l>
                  <l>View'd with what happineſs his gifts began,</l>
                  <l>He thought that good, to be too good for man:</l>
                  <l>He quaſh'd his wiſh, and limited his will</l>
                  <l>By new made Laws, which curb mans nature ſtill,</l>
                  <l>And bridle him, as horſemen when they ride</l>
                  <l>Bridle their horſes, leſt they ſtart aſide.</l>
                  <l>My love compels my judgement to diſcloſe,</l>
                  <l>And makes me freely ſpeak: who doth oppoſe</l>
                  <l>The common uſe of Wives, that man (in truth)</l>
                  <l>Is envious; but honeſty (forſooth)</l>
                  <l>His envy muſt excuſe: an honeſt thought</l>
                  <l>Which evil cuſtome of long envy brought;</l>
                  <l>For while each man t'himſelf alone confines</l>
                  <l>His own delights, and with diſdain repines</l>
                  <l>To make them publick: This became a ſage,</l>
                  <l>A common cuſtome, honeſt made with age:</l>
                  <l>And jealous Madneſs by degrees did draw</l>
                  <l>This but a Cuſtome to be made a Law.</l>
                  <l>Love is malignant, Pleaſure is no leſs;</l>
                  <l>Both murmure at anothers happineſs.</l>
                  <l>Then I, not daring longer to conteſt</l>
                  <l>Againſt a man with Paſſion ſo poſſeſt,</l>
                  <l>Leſt him inflam'd with Love, with Choller burn'd,</l>
                  <l>And from the frantick Lover home return'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>See'ſt how this fond, this mad affection blindes</l>
                  <l>The ſoundeſt judgements of the ſageſt mindes,</l>
                  <l>Us leading in a voluntary way</l>
                  <l>To groſſeſt errours at the mid of day?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fo.</speaker>
                  <l>Seeſt how the Clouds on <hi>Baldus</hi> top condenſe</l>
                  <l>In black agglomerations? Come, let's hence;</l>
                  <l>'Twill hail, 'tis time to go; leſt (if it riſe)</l>
                  <l>The tempeſt our diſperſed Sheep ſurpriſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <trailer>The End of the ſecond Eclogue.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="eclogue">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:115715:14"/>
               <head>ECLOGUE III. Treating of the hapleſs event of Frantick Love. <hi>Intituled AMYNTAS.</hi>
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <l>What Loſſes husbandmen attend,</l>
                  <l>What rage <hi>Amyntas</hi> did aſſail,</l>
                  <l>His death and lamantable end</l>
                  <l>Here <hi>Fortunatus</hi> doth bewail.</l>
               </argument>
               <stage>The Speakers, <hi>Fauſtus</hi> and <hi>Fortunatus.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fauſt.</speaker>
                  <l>THat ratling ſtorm of hail, which yeſternight</l>
                  <l>Came ruſhing down from <hi>Baldus,</hi> did affright,</l>
                  <l>But did not hurt us with its ſuddain ſhowers,</l>
                  <l>Thanks to thoſe tutelary Saints of ours</l>
                  <l>That guard our Fruits: but yet thoſe boiſterous ſtorms</l>
                  <l>(As <hi>Harculus,</hi> who came from thence, informes)</l>
                  <l>O <hi>Fortunatus</hi> ſpoil'd <hi>Verona</hi>'s Fields:</l>
                  <l>The Sheep and Cattle, with what elſe it yields,</l>
                  <l>The Country Cottages and Shepheards Cotts</l>
                  <l>Are batter'd ſo with thoſe tempeſtuous ſhots,</l>
                  <l>Are ſo demoliſh'd, that ſmall hope remains,</l>
                  <l>Or rather none to thoſe poor Country Swains</l>
                  <l>For Corn and Cattle, all the riches are</l>
                  <l>Of Husbandmen, ſtill ſubject, as to care</l>
                  <l>So to miſchances; Citizens the while</l>
                  <l>A maſſe of Treaſure in their Coffers pile.</l>
                  <l>Which neither Hail, Dew, Froſt, nor irefull aire</l>
                  <l>Can daſh, diſſolve, diminiſh, or impair.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fort.</speaker>
                  <l>I know not who the winds and ſtorms Commands,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:115715:15"/>I know I know not; Nor, if I thoſe hands</l>
                  <l>Did know, know I enough: but yet I dare</l>
                  <l>Speak what I know: my mind I will declare.</l>
                  <l>What? ſhall my life be thus imbitter'd here?</l>
                  <l>Shall I here be ſo laſh'd, and ſo ſevere?</l>
                  <l>If (as they ſay) the Gods above the skies</l>
                  <l>Do rule the world, I think their deities</l>
                  <l>Take little care, or elſe but little know</l>
                  <l>The miſerable toyl of Men below.</l>
                  <l>See with what daily paines and hourly ſweat</l>
                  <l>A poor a ſlender living here we get:</l>
                  <l>How many miſeries within a year</l>
                  <l>For Wives, Flocks, Children do poor Shepheards bear?</l>
                  <l>With Summer heat we fry, with winters cold</l>
                  <l>We freeze: When <hi>Boreas</hi> with his blaſts growes bold,</l>
                  <l>We ſleep in ragged Cots upon the ground;</l>
                  <l>A thouſand Peſts, a thouſand ſores confound</l>
                  <l>Our Cattle, and a thouſand things prevail</l>
                  <l>Againſt them: Here the ſheepfold Theeves aſſail,</l>
                  <l>Wolves there; The Souldier yonder is as brief</l>
                  <l>To ſteal us both; Nay more then Wolfe or thief.</l>
                  <l>Our hands with daily toyl are ſtiff and hard,</l>
                  <l>Our face is rivell'd, rugged is our Beard,</l>
                  <l>Our skin is parch'd with heat; and yet at laſt</l>
                  <l>One ſuddain ſtorm of hail doth all lay waſt.</l>
                  <l>The Gods do this, before whoſe ſhrines we bow,</l>
                  <l>And on whoſe Altars (with a ſolemn vow)</l>
                  <l>We ſacrifice our Lamps, and <hi>voted</hi> lights</l>
                  <l>Of wax, <hi>devoted</hi> to Religious rites.</l>
                  <l>I know not what Indulgence, or what love</l>
                  <l>What Piety, what Pity from above</l>
                  <l>Involves poor Shepheards (poor by frequent loſſes)</l>
                  <l>With theſe ſo great miſhaps, ſo grievous croſſes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fauſt.</speaker>
                  <l>This dammage, this unhappineſſe proceeds</l>
                  <l>O <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> from our own miſdeeds:</l>
                  <l>Gods Judgements all are alwaies juſt: Our ſin,</l>
                  <l>Our wickedneſs theſe plagues hath uſher'd in.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:115715:15"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fort.</speaker>
                  <l>What wickedneſs? What have we yet aſſaid</l>
                  <l>To murther Chriſt? what, have we Chriſt betray'd?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fauſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh, our repinings, Robberies, and rages,</l>
                  <l>Our veneries, lies, ſtrifes, produce theſe ſtrages.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fort.</speaker>
                  <l>What have the good deſerved, for I ſuppoſe</l>
                  <l>All are not evill; yet both theſe and thoſe</l>
                  <l>Suffer alike? One puniſhment is had</l>
                  <l>A like for all together, good and bad.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fauſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Alaſs, what know'ſt thou not (preſumptuous clod)</l>
                  <l>'Tis impious to think amiſſe of God?</l>
                  <l>But leaving theſe Myſterious things, too great</l>
                  <l>To know, which muſt be ſecret: Let's repeat</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Amyntas</hi> Love: Come, let's repeat again</l>
                  <l>Thoſe care, which vex'd his heart, which craz'd his brain,</l>
                  <l>Which all have tri'd, which are unknown to none.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fort.</speaker>
                  <l>Love is a common thing, the wonted tone</l>
                  <l>Of youth, it is their ſtudy, their delight.</l>
                  <l>But grief and perturbations blind the ſight</l>
                  <l>With paſſion, which doth oft unhing the mind,</l>
                  <l>Thus ſad expreſſions from ſad hearts we find.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fauſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Things known and underſtood, Thou maiſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</l>
                  <l>For matter and for time, but never prate</l>
                  <l>Of things unknown, or of uncertainties:</l>
                  <l>(For ſo great <hi>Coſmas</hi> was accounted wiſe)</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fort.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fauſtus</hi> the'art wiſe: Let's then known Loves re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat:</l>
                  <l>It reſts, that of <hi>Amyntas</hi> now we treat,</l>
                  <l>Of his mad Love, his laſt ſad Fate, and ſpend</l>
                  <l>Some tears upon his lamentable end,</l>
                  <l>A little after, paſſing by that way,</l>
                  <l>I ſaw the man again, who Frantick lay:</l>
                  <l>I, pitying his folly, Thus began:</l>
                  <l>O thou (quoth I) moſt miſerable Man</l>
                  <l>Moſt miſadvis'd whom fatall Aconite</l>
                  <l>Intoxicates, now made the common ſpite,</l>
                  <l>The Common ſport of people: doſt not yet</l>
                  <l>Repent thy love? Doſt yet thy ſelf forget?</l>
                  <l>Yet buried in Love do'ſt ſnatch from hence</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:115715:16"/>Thy ſelf, and thine with thee (by violence)</l>
                  <l>Thy Cottages and Cattle, as of y'ore</l>
                  <l>Expiring <hi>Sampſon</hi> all things with him bore?</l>
                  <l>When old thou grow'ſt (if ſo the Fates be pleas'd)</l>
                  <l>Who ſhall ſuſtain thee then? then when diſeas'd,</l>
                  <l>Dull, Sleepy, poor, if now thy ſtrength and wit</l>
                  <l>Decay, decline, if now thy Senſes flit?</l>
                  <l>All theſe (like waters through an open Sluce)</l>
                  <l>If death prevent not, Age will introduce.</l>
                  <l>Keep home, be vigilant, obſervant be;</l>
                  <l>But chiefly whither thou doſt tend, foreſee:</l>
                  <l>Beware thou go not thither, whither come,</l>
                  <l>Thou maiſt deplore, thy moſt unhappy doom:</l>
                  <l>Diſcern thy waies; Remember Man was born</l>
                  <l>Not to delights or pleaſures, but to ſcorn</l>
                  <l>Thoſe flattering effoeminate deceits</l>
                  <l>Which ſpoil unſtable youth with ſugred baits,</l>
                  <l>I, I that Cattle have, and Milk, and Cheeſe,</l>
                  <l>Do ſcarce ſubſiſt in ſuch hard times as theſe;</l>
                  <l>The want's ſo great in all our Fields and Tents,</l>
                  <l>Things have ſo many ſad and bad events.</l>
                  <l>So great diſprofits ev'ry where diſperſe,</l>
                  <l>So many things <hi>adverſe</hi> in th' <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hear an unheard of thing, a thing unknown</l>
                  <l>Of yore, which now to me theſe times have ſhown:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Autumne</hi> approaching, as it is our uſe,</l>
                  <l>I ſhore my ſheep; which done, I did produce</l>
                  <l>At mornings Market, and expos'd to ſale</l>
                  <l>Twice thirty pound of Wooll (nor is't a tale)</l>
                  <l>Expecting ſtore of money for the ſame,</l>
                  <l>But ſhort mine hope, mine expectation came:</l>
                  <l>'Twill ſcarce preſerve my Flock 'twill ſcarce provide</l>
                  <l>Hay for the Winter: which way then beſide</l>
                  <l>My Family ſhall be maintain'd as well,</l>
                  <l>Indeed <hi>Amyntas,</hi> yet I cannot tell.</l>
                  <l>He that's a Lover muſt himſelf improve</l>
                  <l>By gifts unto the Miſtreſs of his love.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:115715:16"/>But thou whom fickle Fortune hath bereft</l>
                  <l>Almoſt of all, to whom ſhe ſcarce hath left</l>
                  <l>A Cottage, under which thy poorneſſe may</l>
                  <l>Be lodg'd at Night, or be receiv'd by day.</l>
                  <l>What canſt thou give which may be gratefull ſaid</l>
                  <l>Unto the wiſh of thy beloved Maid?</l>
                  <l>'Twas once enough to ſend thoſe Loves of ours</l>
                  <l>Ten pleaſant apples, or ſome purple flowers,</l>
                  <l>A Birds Neſt, or ſweet graſſe: when theſe were thought</l>
                  <l>Great gifts I wel remember; But 'tis brought</l>
                  <l>From graſſe to gold; Love is a coſtly thing,</l>
                  <l>A dear bought ſweet too great expence doth bring</l>
                  <l>In theſe our times; Old cuſtomes are refus'd,</l>
                  <l>And now new Lawes of Love, but worſe, are us'd.</l>
                  <l>While thus I did perſwade, He caſt aſide</l>
                  <l>His irefull eyes, and (frowning) thus repli'd:</l>
                  <l>If thou O <hi>Fortunatus</hi> do'ſt deſire</l>
                  <l>My wiſh'd for health, Then give what I require,</l>
                  <l>Give me my <hi>Love:</hi> No Medicine but this one</l>
                  <l>Can cure my grief: This is the Cure alone:</l>
                  <l>Thoſe other things, which thou ſo much do'ſt name,</l>
                  <l>Do but torment me more: This ſcorching flame,</l>
                  <l>This Fury which ſo rageth in my breaſt.</l>
                  <l>Can never thence be pull'd or diſpoſſeſt;</l>
                  <l>For ſtill my mind as preſent doth ſuppoſe</l>
                  <l>The Virgins ſhape, with me ſhe comes, ſhe goes,</l>
                  <l>She ſtaies, wakes, ſleeps with me: mine heart, mine head,</l>
                  <l>My bones, my reins are all Invironed</l>
                  <l>With her fair Form: Nor from my melting heart</l>
                  <l>Can ſhe, before my life departs, depart.</l>
                  <l>As when a Syence from one ſtock is cut,</l>
                  <l>And graff'd upon another, Both do ſhut</l>
                  <l>And joyn ſo cloſe, That their two Natures grow</l>
                  <l>Together mixt, and Flouriſh in one bough:</l>
                  <l>So the beloved Image of my dear,</l>
                  <l>My lovely Miſtreſſe doth my ſoul adhere,</l>
                  <l>Is there immerg'd: makes both our hearts but one,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:115715:17"/>But one makes both our ſouls: in us alone</l>
                  <l>The Spirit and the Senſes are the ſame.</l>
                  <l>O happy ſhould I be, if when my flame,</l>
                  <l>My ſpark of life expires, I might (at leaſt)</l>
                  <l>Upon the tender lap, the milk white breaſt,</l>
                  <l>The ſnow-like armes of my moſt honoured,</l>
                  <l>And deareſt Love but lay my dying head.</l>
                  <l>She with her hands would cloſe my dying eyes,</l>
                  <l>She with ſad voice, with lamentable cries</l>
                  <l>Would wail my Funeralls: and whether I</l>
                  <l>Deceaſing to th' Elyſian Fields ſhall flye,</l>
                  <l>Or whether I be rapp'd and hurl'd upon</l>
                  <l>The burning Streams of Flaming <hi>Phlegeton,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I cannot happy be without thee, neither</l>
                  <l>Unhappy with thee; Might we be together.</l>
                  <l>Ye <hi>Dryades,</hi> and Goddeſſes of Flowers,</l>
                  <l>O ye fair Nymphes, and O of Woods and Bowers,</l>
                  <l>Thou Guardian <hi>Sylvanus,</hi> keep I pray,</l>
                  <l>Keep on your hills and Valleyes all the gay,</l>
                  <l>The gallant Flowers of your woods and Fields,</l>
                  <l>Or of what ſweets beſide the Country yields:</l>
                  <l>Hedge in your groves, and thence the Cattle ſtop,</l>
                  <l>Leſt they ſhould brouze the buds, or flowers ſhould crop</l>
                  <l>Keep, keep I pray theſe Flowers, Theſe ſweets, Theſe all,</l>
                  <l>To Celebrate my loves ſad Funerall:</l>
                  <l>Then all the ground about where ere you tread,</l>
                  <l>With Flowers ſweetly ſmelling ſhall be ſpread:</l>
                  <l>Weave Garlands you: Garlands for ſight, for ſent,</l>
                  <l>Fair, fragrant to ſurround her Monument:</l>
                  <l>Garlands my Miſtreſſes dead Corpes to cover</l>
                  <l>Untill interr'd; Then to be Pendant over.</l>
                  <l>The Maiden <hi>Muſes</hi> ſhall attend her hearſe,</l>
                  <l>And weeping ſing an Elegiack verſe:</l>
                  <l>Shall on her grave ingrave in ſtone or lead</l>
                  <l>This Epitaph for after-times to read,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Here lies a Maid; Who, but ſhe cruell was,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Might among Mortalls for Immmortall paſſe:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:115715:17"/>
                     <hi>Might have been Natures Paragon and Jewel,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Had ſhe not to her Lover been too cruel.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>O maid, if ſuch a ſcorching flame as mine</l>
                  <l>Did but inflame that breaſt, that heart of thine,</l>
                  <l>An hundred gulphes, a thouſand raging Seas</l>
                  <l>I would ſwim o're, to give thy paſſions eaſe:</l>
                  <l>But thou more cruel, thou more ſerpentine</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Hydra,</hi> do'ſt my ſelf, my love decline.</l>
                  <l>But (ah) the maid is blameleſſe, for as yet</l>
                  <l>She knows me not: and doubtleſſe could ſhe get</l>
                  <l>But knowledge of my love, ſhe would afford</l>
                  <l>My love ſome comfort of her own accord.</l>
                  <l>Nor can I think that <hi>Nature</hi> e're did place</l>
                  <l>So harde an heart under ſo ſweet a face.</l>
                  <l>But faces are deceitful; for the while</l>
                  <l>They ſeem moſt beautiful, they moſt beguile:</l>
                  <l>A cruel mind hath oft a Candid skin;</l>
                  <l>Fair looks without, conceal foul hearts within.</l>
                  <l>Yet I will ſpeak, and make her know my love:</l>
                  <l>But ſhould ſhe then repulſe me, ſhould ſhe prove</l>
                  <l>Unkind, mine eyes would melt in tears, mine heart,</l>
                  <l>My mourning heart with deep fetch'd grones would part</l>
                  <l>Would break in twain, and though ſhe ſtill deteſt,</l>
                  <l>And fly me following her with my requeſt,</l>
                  <l>Yet whither ever I ſhall carried be,</l>
                  <l>Theſe cares, theſe thoughts for her will follow me.</l>
                  <l>Hence, O far hence Phyſicians with your art,</l>
                  <l>For (ah) incurable's my grief, my ſmart:</l>
                  <l>Hence, O far hence Magicians, you whoſe ſpells</l>
                  <l>Can raiſe (they ſay) pale Ghoſts from <hi>Pluto</hi>'s Cells:</l>
                  <l>Hence, O far hence you, that the Pow'rs Divine,</l>
                  <l>Suppoſe your vain Petitions can incline:</l>
                  <l>Your Orizons (alas) are deſpicable</l>
                  <l>Averſe is Heaven and inexorable:</l>
                  <l>Impatience and madneſſe me from hence</l>
                  <l>Tranſport with rage, and rap with violence:</l>
                  <l>I like to trace the ſolitary Creſts</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:115715:18"/>Of craggy Mountains, and the Dens of Beaſts.</l>
                  <l>While thus he ſpake, with friendly words I tride</l>
                  <l>T' aſſwage him, but my words were miſappli'd.</l>
                  <l>For nothing, ah there could be nothing found</l>
                  <l>To cure his never to be cured wound.</l>
                  <l>Amid the ſilent Fields in diſcontent</l>
                  <l>The long, the melancholy night he ſpent,</l>
                  <l>And from the dawning to the cloſe of day</l>
                  <l>Among the Brakes and Buſhes hid he lay:</l>
                  <l>He never ſlept, and did but ſeldome eat,</l>
                  <l>Water his drink, wild apples were his meat.</l>
                  <l>After long grones at length, and mournfull cries,</l>
                  <l>Exhauſting with continuall tears his eies,</l>
                  <l>After moſt ſad laments, with griefs o'reworn,</l>
                  <l>His heart within often ſighes aſunder torne</l>
                  <l>He died, ending, with his life, his love.</l>
                  <l>His liveleſſe body left the ground above</l>
                  <l>Without interment, and neglected quite,</l>
                  <l>The Birds devour'd by day, the Beaſts by night.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Ah, <hi>Cupids</hi> deadly dram, ah fatall gin,</l>
                  <l>Which whoſoevers heart it enters in</l>
                  <l>Doth wholy Captivate that wretched heart,</l>
                  <l>Transfixing it with an invenom'd dart,</l>
                  <l>Men equalling with Beaſts: what worſe Receits,</l>
                  <l>What more impoyſon'd, or bewitching baits</l>
                  <l>Could <hi>Circe,</hi> could <hi>Calypſo</hi> give then theſe?</l>
                  <l>What Styx, what <hi>Phlegeton</hi> could more diſeaſe?</l>
                  <l>What Furies more torment? O moſt unwiſe</l>
                  <l>You were, what e're you were, that did diſguiſe</l>
                  <l>Blind <hi>Cupid</hi> with a godhead; what is <hi>Nature</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A God, that hurts or Nullifies a Creature?</l>
                  <l>Where e're there is a God, him think we muſt</l>
                  <l>To be to man indulgent, harmleſſe, juſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fo.</speaker>
                  <l>Ah ſweet, and ever to be pitied youth,</l>
                  <l>Surpriz'd thus in thy prime, thy lives chief growth;</l>
                  <l>What fatall ſtar did on thy Birth reflect?</l>
                  <l>What part of heaven with ſo dire aſpect</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:115715:18"/>So much malign'd thee, that It made thy Fate</l>
                  <l>(Though cauſeleſſe) from thy Birth unfortunate?</l>
                  <l>Yet from thee was not heav'ns ſweet influence</l>
                  <l>Wholy declin'd, but that thou wert from thence</l>
                  <l>Inſpir'd with ſacred Poeſie, with skill</l>
                  <l>To ſing ſweet Sonnets on thine Oaten quill:</l>
                  <l>And, but for timeleſſe death, thy learned laies</l>
                  <l>Ivie deſerv'd, deſerv'd <hi>Parnaſsus</hi> Bayes:</l>
                  <l>Nor did our <hi>Tytirus</hi> ſo well belov'd</l>
                  <l>Of great <hi>Alexis,</hi> better ſing ('tis prov'd)</l>
                  <l>Of Wars, Corn, Tillage, Paſtures, ev'ry thing,</l>
                  <l>Then thou thy ſelf, then thou thy ſelf didſt ſing.</l>
                  <l>For thy Mature, propenſe and active Mind,</l>
                  <l>(Which we long ſince obſerv'd, to good inclin'd)</l>
                  <l>Began to Fructifie, began t' impart</l>
                  <l>No vulgar ſhowers of thy rare gifts and art.</l>
                  <l>Thou maiſt be ſtil'd to thine etern renown</l>
                  <l>The Countries honour, and our ages Crown;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Po</hi> with our <hi>Mincius</hi> in doleful tone</l>
                  <l>With all their Nymphes ſhall thee bewail, bemoan,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Thrac' an Hebrus Orpheus</hi> did lament:</l>
                  <l>Thee the ſad Shepheards full of diſcontent</l>
                  <l>Bewail, as <hi>Daphnis</hi> once they did bewail;</l>
                  <l>For thee, like diſcontents aſſault, aſſail,</l>
                  <l>The grounds and Paſtures all untill'd and til'd.</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſad complaints are heard in every field,</l>
                  <l>Ye Shepheards with ſweet Flow'rs his grave beſtrew,</l>
                  <l>And yearly there his memory renue</l>
                  <l>With Elegies and Frankincenſe: with them</l>
                  <l>Sing there the Poets endleſs <hi>Requiem.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>But thou the while <hi>Amyntas</hi> doſt poſſeſſe</l>
                  <l>A better place, a place of happineſſe;</l>
                  <l>Here we bewail thee, thou the while art come</l>
                  <l>Into the pleaſures of <hi>Elyſium.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fo.</speaker>
                  <l>And he this day ſhould be bewail'd of us:</l>
                  <l>For I laſt night beheld an Ominous,</l>
                  <l>I know not what ſad-ſeeming apparition</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:115715:19"/>To me preſented in a mournful viſion.</l>
                  <l>But now 'tis evening: and the ſetting Sun</l>
                  <l>Declining in a cloud doth rain forerun,</l>
                  <l>Foreſhews our husbandmen that ſtorms are near;</l>
                  <l>'Tis therefore time before the ſtorm appear</l>
                  <l>To recollect our Cattle: come (foretold)</l>
                  <l>Let's drive our ſheep and Cattle to the Fold.</l>
               </sp>
               <trailer>The End of the third Eclogue.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="eclogue">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:115715:19"/>
               <head>ECLOGUE IV. Treating of the Nature of Women. <hi>Intituled ALPHUS.</hi>
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Janus</hi> relates his Lad, his Goat</l>
                  <l>How firſt he loſt, and then did find:</l>
                  <l>Whence <hi>Alphus</hi> doth proceed to note</l>
                  <l>The Properties of womenkind.</l>
               </argument>
               <stage>The Speakers <hi>Alphus</hi> and <hi>Janus.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>I <hi>Anus,</hi> I ſee thy Goat is lean, which wont</l>
                  <l>To be more brisk, and with his horned Front</l>
                  <l>Sky-ward erected wont to ſtalk in ſcorn:</l>
                  <l>Dull and dejected now (like one forlorne)</l>
                  <l>He flaggs his ears, the graſſe but ſmells, ornips</l>
                  <l>Or doth but touch it with his outer lips.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
                  <l>He languiſheth, and from that languiſhing</l>
                  <l>Ariſeth mirth: which, when to mind I bring,</l>
                  <l>It makes me laugh; the jeſt is yet unſhown,</l>
                  <l>But all the world will wonder, when 'tis known.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Janus,</hi> thy pleaſing tongue was us'd to vent</l>
                  <l>Moſt wittily, neat jeſts with merriment;</l>
                  <l>Tell therefore, tell me now (here's none but us)</l>
                  <l>What made thy luſty Goat to languiſh thus.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
                  <l>I'l tell thee, God's my witneſſe 'tis no Fable.</l>
                  <l>'Twas lately done, 'tis truth and warrantable.</l>
                  <l>But I for nothing will not this report,</l>
                  <l>What's my reward what wilt thou giveme for't?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ianus,</hi> i'l ſhew the buſh, i'l ſhew the Field</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:115715:20"/>Where a ſweet-ſinging Nightingale doth build.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
                  <l>Who ſlightly promiſe, lightly they Beguile.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Who credits not is faithleſs; but the while</l>
                  <l>To make thee ſure, loe, from my quiver drawn</l>
                  <l>A pair of arrows; Take them for a pawn.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
                  <l>I'l then begin: Ye <hi>Muſes</hi> move my tongue,</l>
                  <l>Revive my memory, that I the wrong,</l>
                  <l>The ſad misfortune of my Goat may tell;</l>
                  <l>And t' <hi>Alphus</hi> grant the Neſt of <hi>Philomel.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I hir'd a boy, and plac'd him o're my ſheep:</l>
                  <l>He daily fed them, and did duly keep</l>
                  <l>My Goate, my Kidds; his ſervice for a while</l>
                  <l>Was grateful to me, till he ſaw the ſmile</l>
                  <l>Of a fair Virgin, who to theſe our ſprings</l>
                  <l>For water came: But ſince with languiſhing.</l>
                  <l>He pines, now ſottiſh is become, neglects</l>
                  <l>To feed the ſheep, the ſheepcotes diſreſpects,</l>
                  <l>And all his buſineſs in a giddy vain</l>
                  <l>Turns topſy-turvy with his empty brain.</l>
                  <l>Him, while he ſlept, one would have thought awake,</l>
                  <l>For waking idly with himſelf he ſpake;</l>
                  <l>He ſleeping us'd and waking in extreams,</l>
                  <l>His body dull, his mind was full of dreams.</l>
                  <l>He loy'tring, in a grove, this Goate of mine</l>
                  <l>Ti'd by the hornes with a ſtrong twiggen line</l>
                  <l>Among the buſh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s; (now 'tis four daies ſince)</l>
                  <l>Aſſaying if the Goat could break from thence</l>
                  <l>By ſtrength of neck, or hardneſſe of his horns.</l>
                  <l>The Boy mean while among the brakes and thorns,</l>
                  <l>Stalkes wandring up and down the wood to ſeek,</l>
                  <l>To find a birds neſt in ſome buſh or Creek.</l>
                  <l>His mind is on the maid, his thoughts reflect</l>
                  <l>Upon her beautifull-belov'd aſpect,</l>
                  <l>Her Face, breaſts, other parts, which here for ſhame</l>
                  <l>My bluſhing modeſty forbears to name.</l>
                  <l>Day flyes the while: The boy comes home at night</l>
                  <l>But left the Goat behind, forgot him quite.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:115715:20"/>At Midnight he bethought him, and aroſe</l>
                  <l>To ſeek the Goat: goes out, and as he goes</l>
                  <l>Half trembling in the dark, he falls at laſt</l>
                  <l>In a deep pit, whoſe mouth was overcaſt</l>
                  <l>With boughes and ſtraw, ſo cover'd to betray,</l>
                  <l>To take wild Beaſts that on our Cattle prey.</l>
                  <l>Deep was the Pit, and ſteep wherein he fell,</l>
                  <l>Returnles like the bottom of a wel.</l>
                  <l>The Goat's in bonds, in priſon is the boy,</l>
                  <l>No ſhepheard guards the ſheep, though Wolves deſtroy,</l>
                  <l>'Twas the third hour next morn, I wond'red, I</l>
                  <l>My ſheep review'd, recounted, ('tis no lie)</l>
                  <l>Miſſing the Goat amaz'd I ſtood, I call'd</l>
                  <l>The Boy, the ſheepcotes ſearch'd, and much appall'd,</l>
                  <l>I fear'd leſt 'nointed with inchanted oyl,</l>
                  <l>And mounting on my Goat, he from the ſoyl,</l>
                  <l>Had leap'd, and travell'd through the pathleſſe air:</l>
                  <l>For witches ſo (they ſay) by ni<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ht repair,</l>
                  <l>Uſing like magick ointments, and are hurl'd</l>
                  <l>To certain feaſts far off, about the world.</l>
                  <l>Amaz'd, at length my ſheep to graſſe I drove,</l>
                  <l>And muſing with my ſelf, while I the grove</l>
                  <l>Did enter in; Behold far off, behold</l>
                  <l>My Goat amid the buſhes in the cold</l>
                  <l>And dusky ſhadow brayes, and ſtriving ſtands</l>
                  <l>Butting with horns oppos'd againſt his bands,</l>
                  <l>This ſuddain apparition of my Goat,</l>
                  <l>This unexpected comming e're I thought,</l>
                  <l>Affrighted me: yet with couragious heart</l>
                  <l>At length I knew the Beaſt, I plaid my part,</l>
                  <l>I went among the Brakes, and cut in twain</l>
                  <l>Thoſe rigid bands that did my Goat detain,</l>
                  <l>Returning homewards late, I ſpi'd afar</l>
                  <l>Among the Paſtures that adjoyning are</l>
                  <l>A multitude of jolly-merry Boyes,</l>
                  <l>leaping and laughing loud with youthful noiſes</l>
                  <l>When near we came together me they knew,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:115715:21"/>Saluted, and thus ſaid, O <hi>Ianus</hi> view,</l>
                  <l>View here thy Boy, but newly from the ſnares</l>
                  <l>Of Wolves drawn out, wherein at unawares</l>
                  <l>Headlong he tell, walking by night the ground;</l>
                  <l>And thus my Goat and Shepheard both were found.</l>
                  <l>The Goat thus wrong'd ſtill pines: The fooliſh lad</l>
                  <l>More pining is, and then the Goat more mad.</l>
                  <l>The maid once hearing that ſhe was belov'd,</l>
                  <l>Grew quickly proud; and ſeeming nothing mov'd</l>
                  <l>Diſſembles it, diſſembles that ſhe knew</l>
                  <l>The Lads affection, ſtill her ſelf withdrew,</l>
                  <l>As if abaſh'd, and (like a ſubtil Trul)</l>
                  <l>To make her beauty ſeem more beautiful,</l>
                  <l>Her head, her breaſts ſhe decks, ſhe bluſhing jetts</l>
                  <l>Down looking on the growing violets:</l>
                  <l>And cunningly ſhe doth the thing diſguiſe</l>
                  <l>With ſample ſhews, but Fox-like ſubtleties.</l>
                  <l>Theſe are the womens ſtudies, gins and arms.</l>
                  <l>My ſhepheard thus bewitch'd with theſe her charms,</l>
                  <l>Yet hoping that he ſhould at length injoy</l>
                  <l>His love, his <hi>Galatea:</hi> (fooliſh Boy)</l>
                  <l>Diſdain'd his wages, and my ſervice left,</l>
                  <l>Onely purſu'd his love: I, thus bereft,</l>
                  <l>Was forc'd to leave mine oxen, plough and wayn,</l>
                  <l>And t' undertake the ſhepheards trade again.</l>
                  <l>Youths levity to madneſſe thus propenſe</l>
                  <l>Infeſts all Countries in aequivalence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>What wit effects not, Fortune doth advance:</l>
                  <l>O ſtrange aſtoniſhment, O witty chance,</l>
                  <l>O pretty things deſerving two months laughter.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ianus,</hi> I'l keep my word: <hi>Pandions</hi> daughter</l>
                  <l>Doth for thee labour, builds her neſt for thee.</l>
                  <l>But now thou ſpeak'ſt of this ſo crafty ſhe,</l>
                  <l>This ſubtile-wily maid, I call to mind</l>
                  <l>What <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mber</hi>'s of the frauds of women kind</l>
                  <l>Us'd oft of yore to ſing in learned verſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ia.</speaker>
                  <l>Tel me (pr'y thee) tel, if ought thou canſt rehearſe</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:115715:21"/>Of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mber,</hi> weigh his words, his verſe awhile,</l>
                  <l>All <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbers</hi> verſes were of lofty ſtyle,</l>
                  <l>Were memorable all, and worth regard.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>They be, thou ſaiſt, but not without reward</l>
                  <l>To be repeated: What reward, what pay?</l>
                  <l>What wilt thou give me? ſpeak, and then I'le ſay.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
                  <l>I from thy promiſe thee releaſe; and (more)</l>
                  <l>Here, take, thy pair of Arrows I reſtore.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>While I behinde theſe ſedges go t'untruſs,</l>
                  <l>Look to my Cattel, <hi>Janus,</hi> leſt they thus</l>
                  <l>Stragling abroad ſhould break (beyond their lines)</l>
                  <l>Into the Vineyards, and there ſpoil the Vines.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
                  <l>O Ram, thou Ram that with thy crooked horns,</l>
                  <l>Like a black Devil, look'ſt among the thorns,</l>
                  <l>Entring the Vineyards ſtill; thou'lt not forbear,</l>
                  <l>Till from thy forhead both thine eyes I tear.</l>
                  <l>Are not thoſe Paſtures, which in meaſure be</l>
                  <l>An hundred Acres, large enough for thee,</l>
                  <l>But that thou muſt deſtroy, thou muſt deſpoil</l>
                  <l>The Vines and Vineyards (that incloſed ſoil?)</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Janus,</hi> I thee remember, and return:</l>
                  <l>But I perhaps can tell (that thou maiſt learn)</l>
                  <l>Things yet unknown to thee: for <hi>Umber</hi> knew</l>
                  <l>All that was lawful for a man to view,</l>
                  <l>All that was lawful for a man to know;</l>
                  <l>He knew the world above, the world below,</l>
                  <l>The skies, ſtars, earth, winds, rivers ſeas and fountains;</l>
                  <l>He travell'd and had ſeen thoſe lofty Mountains</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oſsa, ceraunia, Rhodope;</hi> beſides</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Gallick</hi> Kingdome, <hi>Araris,</hi> The tides</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Rhene, Po, Tiber:</hi> And his witty pate</l>
                  <l>Greek Verſes into Latine did tranſlate.</l>
                  <l>In either tongue he ſecond was to none,</l>
                  <l>But in each language learn'd. Him, him alone</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Greece</hi> envi'd us: Him, him (that learned race)</l>
                  <l>Th' <hi>Arcadians</hi> themſelves, with thoſe of <hi>Thrace,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:115715:22"/>That chant it in the Groves did emulate, <hi>Theſſaliam Temple</hi> did maligne his fate.</l>
                  <l>If thou perhaps doſt more deſire to know,</l>
                  <l>Our Neighbours <hi>Candidus</hi> that lives below,</l>
                  <l>That follow'd ſtill his Precepts, will impart</l>
                  <l>Us to; for he remembers it, his art.</l>
                  <l>But now the ſev'n hol'd Pipe let's try, let's ſound:</l>
                  <l>Yet I the Muſes firſt implore around</l>
                  <l>To daigne their preſence, but my chiefeſt gueſt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Polymna,</hi> more remembring then the reſt.</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">What the Author meant of all, the Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor intends onely of ill women.</note>The female Sex is ſervile, cruel, proud,</l>
                  <l>Wanting law, meaſure, reaſon, very loud;</l>
                  <l>The bounds of right omits, extremes admits,</l>
                  <l>Doth all things unadviſedly by fits:</l>
                  <l>Or it will ſlowly creep, or ſwiftly run,</l>
                  <l>Or cold it is as Ice, or hot as Sun:</l>
                  <l>Never well temper'd, never moderate,</l>
                  <l>Or ſhe will dearly love, or deadly hate.</l>
                  <l>Would ſhe ſeem grave? Too ſullenly ſhe lowres:</l>
                  <l>Would ſhe leſs grave ſeem plauſible? She tow'rs</l>
                  <l>On levity, and with a wanton ſmile</l>
                  <l>Diſplays immodeſt Impudence the while.</l>
                  <l>She weeps and laughs, fears, dares, is wiſe, unwiſe,</l>
                  <l>Will, will not: All things doth by contraries.</l>
                  <l>Flitting, inconſtant, wand'ring, pratling, vain,</l>
                  <l>Two-tongued, threatning, of imperious ſtrain;</l>
                  <l>Angry, blood-thirſty, wicked, avaricious,</l>
                  <l>Catching, complaining, credulous, malicious,</l>
                  <l>Lying, impatient, burd'nous, tipling all,</l>
                  <l>Raſh, taunting, light, ambitious, magicall;</l>
                  <l>She-Pander, ſuperſtitious, ſlothful, prone</l>
                  <l>To goſſip, ſtudious of the Stews, alone</l>
                  <l>Of dainty palate, wanton, malapert,</l>
                  <l>Addict to tenderneſs, addict (with art)</l>
                  <l>To ſmooth-fac'd Adulation, and addict</l>
                  <l>To trim her face, to make her beauty trickt:</l>
                  <l>She, wrath and hate retaining, doth defer</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:115715:22"/>Till opportunity produce for her</l>
                  <l>Deſir'd revenge, ungrateful, truſtleſs, ſwelling,</l>
                  <l>Bold, cruel, wrangling, violent, rebelling,</l>
                  <l>Upbraideth others, but her owne offence</l>
                  <l>Excuſeth with her whining eloquence;</l>
                  <l>Murmurs, accends debate, regards no ties</l>
                  <l>Of amity, ſcoffs friendſhip, alwayes eyes</l>
                  <l>Her own advantage, onely careful of it,</l>
                  <l>Onely reſpecting her own proper profit;</l>
                  <l>Flatters, deludes, delayes, too cloſely bites</l>
                  <l>With bitter jeſts, and to divulge, delights,</l>
                  <l>Vain fables addes to that which others ſpake,</l>
                  <l>And of a Mole-hill doth a Mountain make.</l>
                  <l>Feigns things are not, diſſembles things that are,</l>
                  <l>Moſt learn'd to frame excuſes, and moſt rare</l>
                  <l>To forge deceits; her face ſhe fits for wiles,</l>
                  <l>Her face all imitating, frowns or ſmiles.</l>
                  <l>Her ſnares thou can'ſt not ſcape, thou can'ſt not fly,</l>
                  <l>Thou can'ſt not overcome her ſubtlety,</l>
                  <l>So great's her diligence, her skill ſo great</l>
                  <l>To work a miſchief if ſhe pleaſe to cheat.</l>
                  <l>And though thou ſee'ſt it with thine eyes, ſhe dares</l>
                  <l>Excuſe the wickedneſs: Her potent ſnares</l>
                  <l>Delude the Senſes with her active minde.</l>
                  <l>In nothing thou can'ſt credit her, ſo blinde</l>
                  <l>She'll make thee, yet ſhe'll make thee that thy faith</l>
                  <l>Muſt credit ev'ry thing ſhe doth, or ſaith.</l>
                  <l>Examples this confirm: What horrid Crimes</l>
                  <l>Have not bold Females acted in their times?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tarpeia</hi> for a Bracelet did betray</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Romes</hi> proud foes the Port, the Cities Key.</l>
                  <l>Bloody <hi>Medea</hi> did her hands imbrew</l>
                  <l>In her own childrens blood, whom (ah) ſhe ſlew.</l>
                  <l>Adult rous <hi>Helen</hi> fill'd th' <hi>Aegean</hi> Seas</l>
                  <l>With Ships of Warre. <hi>Scylla</hi> the foe to pleaſe</l>
                  <l>Betraid her Father, ſtole his purple hair,</l>
                  <l>Fled with the foe, o'return'd his Regal Chair.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:115715:23"/>
                     <hi>Biblis</hi> her Brother with baſe Luſt pollutes,</l>
                  <l>Her ſelf t'her Father <hi>Myrrha</hi> proſtitutes.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Semiramis</hi> for her own Son did luſt:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Amphiaraus</hi> was reduc'd to duſt</l>
                  <l>By means of his unfaithful wife: The Daughters</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Danaus</hi> kill'd, with unheard of ſlaughters,</l>
                  <l>Their husbands in one night. A bloody Crew</l>
                  <l>Of women the ſweet Poet <hi>Orpheus</hi> ſlew,</l>
                  <l>And him in pieces cruelly did cut.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Paſiphae</hi> with <hi>Taurus</hi> plaid the ſlut.</l>
                  <l>Immodeſt <hi>Phoedra</hi> full of impudence</l>
                  <l>With Chaſtity did moſt unchaſte diſpence.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rebeccah</hi> did with ſubtlety beguile</l>
                  <l>Her husband, and her elder ſon, the while</l>
                  <l>She covered the youngers ſmoother skin</l>
                  <l>With Kid-skins: ſo the Bleſſing he did win.</l>
                  <l>Stout <hi>Hercules</hi> was poiſon'd by his wife;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hippodame</hi> betraid her Fathers life.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lavinia</hi> (to palliate a jarre)</l>
                  <l>Involv'd the <hi>Trojans</hi> in a doubtful warre.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bryſeis</hi> from the Camp <hi>Achilles</hi> drew.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Chryſeis</hi> with her Love-tricks overthrew</l>
                  <l>The noble <hi>Agamemnon,</hi> who, with Love</l>
                  <l>Mad and inrag'd, was puniſh'd from above</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Phoebus,</hi> for his too too bold device:</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Eve</hi> Mankinde expell'd from Paradice.</l>
                  <l>Believe it ſhepherds (for I here atteſt</l>
                  <l>The Countrey Gods) if you deſire your reſt,</l>
                  <l>If you the Paſtures would ſhould harmleſs prove</l>
                  <l>Unto your flocks, if you your flocks doe love,</l>
                  <l>If Reſt, Peace, Life be grateful to you; Chace</l>
                  <l>All wanton Wenches from your dwelling-place.</l>
                  <l>Away with <hi>Theſtilis</hi> far hence, away</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Phillis,</hi> and let her no longer ſtay</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Neaera, Galatea,</hi> nor their mate</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lycoris;</hi> for they'll ſpend your whole eſtate.</l>
                  <l>If you in your eſtates deſire to thrive,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:115715:23"/>Far from your ſheep cotes all thoſe Laſſes drive.</l>
                  <l>Tell me what woman ever paſt the Chain</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Pluto's</hi> Cell, and thence return'd again?</l>
                  <l>Had not <hi>Euridice</hi> been mad, ſhe might</l>
                  <l>Have back return'd through thoſe black ſhades of night</l>
                  <l>By which ſhe thither went: And <hi>Proſerpine</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Had not the luck thoſe Dungeons to decline.</l>
                  <l>But dutiful <hi>Aeneas</hi> ſafely came</l>
                  <l>From thoſe dark Dens; and <hi>Orpheus</hi> did the ſame.</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Hercules</hi> from thence again, unburn'd;</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Theſeus,</hi> and the Brethren two return'd,</l>
                  <l>Both equal expert (brother like to brother)</l>
                  <l>In Riding th'one, in Fights and Wreſtling th'other.</l>
                  <l>And our Redeemer did return from thence,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe riſing brought the ſweeteſt influence</l>
                  <l>Of Life and of Salvation. Shepherds, O</l>
                  <l>Theſe, theſe are Myſteries for us to know,</l>
                  <l>For us to ponder: Let mans noble minde</l>
                  <l>Fly things obſcene for better things deſign'd.</l>
                  <l>Let Foeminines themſelves delight, delude</l>
                  <l>With things and places infamous and rude.</l>
                  <l>As when a Sailer, forc'd with winds and tide</l>
                  <l>Hath daſh'd his ſhip againſt a Rock, can guide</l>
                  <l>Unheedy Sailers to decline that Rock.</l>
                  <l>So man grown old and wiſer, can unlock</l>
                  <l>By long experience the Chance of things</l>
                  <l>That are to come, and his Remembrance brings</l>
                  <l>Things that are paſt to light, and ſhews thereby</l>
                  <l>The many dangers of Mortality.</l>
                  <l>If Fowl, the Cruel Eagle, N<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts the Deere,</l>
                  <l>The Lamb the Wolf, Does Dogs do fly, do feare.</l>
                  <l>VVhy do'ſt thou not, O ſhepherd, fear and fly</l>
                  <l>VVomens inticements, hurt ſo much thereby.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hyaena</hi>-like th'are crafty to beguile,</l>
                  <l>And pious are, as is the <hi>Crocodile,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhen flattering ſhe weeps, ſhe thee beſets:</l>
                  <l>Fly, ſhepherd, womens looks, they be but Nets.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:115715:24"/>Truſt not to courage, valour, nor to ſtrength,</l>
                  <l>Nor to that Buckler, whoſe unwonted length</l>
                  <l>Did <hi>Perſeus</hi> guard, that without hurt or dread</l>
                  <l>He ſaw the Snakes upon <hi>Meduſa</hi>'s head:</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Snakes that metamophos'd into ſtone</l>
                  <l>All that beheld her face, but him alone.</l>
                  <l>Many have Monſters kill'd, have Giants tam'd,</l>
                  <l>Have Cities overturned, have been fam'd</l>
                  <l>To bound the Seas proud waves, and at their wills</l>
                  <l>To ſtop the floods, to top the ſharpeſt hills.</l>
                  <l>The ſolemn Games to their immortal praiſe</l>
                  <l>Have crown'd the Victors brows with frondent bayes.</l>
                  <l>But all thoſe Conquerors that others ſpoil'd,</l>
                  <l>By women conquer'd were themſelves and foil'd.</l>
                  <l>He that was firſt a Shepherd, then a King,</l>
                  <l>Renowned for his Lion and his Sling;</l>
                  <l>His Son that after his devout example</l>
                  <l>Erected ſacred <hi>Zions</hi> ſtately Temple:</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Sampſon,</hi> whoſe unconquered ſtrength excell'd</l>
                  <l>All others, were by women captives held.</l>
                  <l>Fire, Stones, Swords, Spears leſs hinder our deſignes,</l>
                  <l>Yea Death leſs hurts us then thoſe Foeminines.</l>
                  <l>Nor with her native beauty pleas'd, ſhe will</l>
                  <l>A thouſand wayes augment it with her skill:</l>
                  <l>Gold decks her forehead; and to make her fair,</l>
                  <l>She paints her face, and neatly curls her hair.</l>
                  <l>With art ſhe goes, with art ſhe guides her eyes:</l>
                  <l>She runs, and (ſporting) from her lover flies</l>
                  <l>Among the buſhes, that ſhe thither may</l>
                  <l>Seduce her lover; willing ſhe's to play,</l>
                  <l>But ſimple yet, and honeſt ſhe would ſeem;</l>
                  <l>She's negative, and ſtrives, but her eſteem</l>
                  <l>Prefers this one thing; all things elſe above</l>
                  <l>To be ſubjected in the fights of Love.</l>
                  <l>A woman ('tis a wonder) doth preſent</l>
                  <l>The North-weſt wind, which in the firmament</l>
                  <l>Condenſeth clouds, and ſcatt'reth them again</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:115715:24"/>In furious tempeſtuous ſtorms of Rain.</l>
                  <l>O whoſoe're thou be, I thee forwarn</l>
                  <l>This leſſon from mine own experience learn;</l>
                  <l>Try not, whilſt thou maiſt chooſe, how many ſorts</l>
                  <l>Of dangers this frail ſex with it comports,</l>
                  <l>What deep diſdains it hath: It is a Creature</l>
                  <l>That is imperfect, and immund by Nature,</l>
                  <l>But cures it ſelf with Art; ſhe works by day,</l>
                  <l>And wakes by night to waſh thoſe blurs away.</l>
                  <l>She waſhes, ſhaves, paints, prints, anoints, adorns,</l>
                  <l>She's all deceit, all skill, all fill'd with ſcorns.</l>
                  <l>Like Mymick Players, ſhe's all Aconite,</l>
                  <l>Her Looking-glaſs ſhe doth conſult for right,</l>
                  <l>All things ſhe doth thereby; ſhe learns thereby</l>
                  <l>To move her lips, to frame her face, her eye:</l>
                  <l>She learns thereby to flatter with her lips,</l>
                  <l>To laugh, to ſport; her ſhoulders and her hips</l>
                  <l>She learns thereby to wriggle as ſhe goes,</l>
                  <l>All by the Looking glaſs ſhe doth compoſe.</l>
                  <l>What mean thoſe naked breaſts? what means (I pray)</l>
                  <l>That little-open chink above? the way</l>
                  <l>That like a cloven Valley down directs</l>
                  <l>Upon her naked boſome vain reflects?</l>
                  <l>Doubtleſs for nothing elſe, but that th'aduſt</l>
                  <l>And penetrable poiſon of hot Luſt</l>
                  <l>Should more oppreſs the ſenſes with deſire,</l>
                  <l>And ſet mens hearts with <hi>Stygian</hi> flames on fire:</l>
                  <l>Theſe are to young men rocks and ſands and ſeas;</l>
                  <l>Theſe are the <hi>Scylla's,</hi> the <hi>Charybdes</hi> theſe;</l>
                  <l>Theſe are thoſe <hi>Harpyes,</hi> beaſtly Birds that flew</l>
                  <l>About King <hi>Phineus</hi> houſe, and did beſpew</l>
                  <l>His Table wîth their odious excrements:</l>
                  <l>Theſe did defile his Chambers, Tables, Tents,</l>
                  <l>His Feaſting-rooms: Nor freed were from theſe ills</l>
                  <l>Pathes, Temples, wayes, fields, rivers, ſeas or hills.</l>
                  <l>Theſe are thoſe <hi>Gorgons,</hi> each with monſtrous head,</l>
                  <l>In the remoteſt parts of <hi>Africk</hi> bred;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:115715:25"/>VVho with their horrid looks and helliſh tones</l>
                  <l>Did living men transform to liveleſs ſtones.</l>
                  <l>Learn'd <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mber's</hi> Verſes we recited have,</l>
                  <l>VVhich if they ſeem more tedious, or leſs grave,</l>
                  <l>Think then (for briefly we did them rehearſe)</l>
                  <l>The fault is in the Matter, not the Verſe.</l>
                  <l>'Tis VVomens Madneſs, 'tis not ô the Song,</l>
                  <l>'Tis not the Verſe that tedious is or long.</l>
                  <l>O memorable, grave and aged man,</l>
                  <l>Of whom old <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbria</hi> ſo much began</l>
                  <l>To boaſt it ſelf: whom (to thy City near)</l>
                  <l>Ev'n <hi>Tiberis</hi> it ſelf accounted dear.</l>
                  <l>Thee warlike <hi>Rome,</hi> not without pregnant cauſe</l>
                  <l>Did call ſo much: She knew (to thine applauſe)</l>
                  <l>Thy skill, thy Verſes of Heroick ſtyle:</l>
                  <l>For thee, when thou didſt die, the Nymphs of <hi>Nile,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Latine <hi>Naiades</hi> and Greek did mourn.</l>
                  <l>O may thy bones lie ſoft within thine Urn;</l>
                  <l>O may thy purer ſoul for ever, even</l>
                  <l>For ever reſt in th'Empiraeal Heaven.</l>
               </sp>
               <trailer>The End of the fourth Eclogue.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="eclogue">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:115715:25"/>
               <head>ECLOGUE V. Treating of the Behaviour of Rich men to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Poets; <hi>Intituled CANDIDUS.</hi>
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sylanus</hi> here the Poets dull</l>
                  <l>And ſluggiſh life doth diſallow.</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Candidus</hi> complains at full</l>
                  <l>How Poets are contemned now.</l>
               </argument>
               <stage>The Speakers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Sylvanus</hi> and <hi>Candidus.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                  <l>O <hi>Candidus,</hi> once thou didſt uſe to feed</l>
                  <l>Thy Cattel here with us; and on thy reed</l>
                  <l>Didſt warble out among our Countrey Swains</l>
                  <l>In theſe cool ſhades ſweet ſongs, melodious ſtrains;</l>
                  <l>Ear-pleaſing witty verſes; and withall</l>
                  <l>Waſt wont to wreſtle ſtoutly for a fall:</l>
                  <l>But alt'red now, as if thou didſt dereſt</l>
                  <l>The Shepherds Calling, and the Countries reſt,</l>
                  <l>The Paſtures leav'ſt, thy ſelf doſt idle keep,</l>
                  <l>Suff'ring thy Songs to ceaſe, thy Pipe to ſleep.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ca.</speaker>
                  <l>You that have wealth enough at home, whoſe kine</l>
                  <l>Strut with full Udders, whoſe white flocks reſign</l>
                  <l>Each milking their full Dugs, whoſe Milk like ſnow</l>
                  <l>Fills full the Milkpails with its overflow.</l>
                  <l>You whoſe fat dinners on the Table ſmoke,</l>
                  <l>Our verſes praiſe; if any thing be ſpoke</l>
                  <l>More witty, 'tis applauded, and you lend</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:115715:26"/>Your well-pleas'd ears with joy: but while we ſpend</l>
                  <l>Our verſe in vain (by which we wont to live)</l>
                  <l>Some flatt'ring praiſe, and empty words you give,</l>
                  <l>But nothing elſe: Mean-while the Poet's poor,</l>
                  <l>Thirſts, hungers, ſtarves with cold, ev'n at your door.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, can'ſt not heed thy flock, and verſify</l>
                  <l>When leiſure is; and, caſting ſorrows by,</l>
                  <l>Lead on a pleaſing life exempt from care?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <l>He that's a ſhepherd muſt no labours ſpare,</l>
                  <l>But all his care about his flock muſt ſtay,</l>
                  <l>To go, to come, to chace the Wolves away,</l>
                  <l>T'incloſe his Cottage with an hedge, to buy</l>
                  <l>Fodder and ſtraw for's ſheep, himſelf t'apply</l>
                  <l>To ſeek food for himſelf: which done remains</l>
                  <l>But little leiſure for Poetick ſtrains.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sylvan,</hi> a commendable verſe doth task</l>
                  <l>All our endeavours, all our wits doth ask:</l>
                  <l>Both theſe, to Poetize, and ſheep to feed,</l>
                  <l>Are grand imployments, and my ſtrength exceed.</l>
                  <l>When I did ſing, I thirſted; but (accurſt)</l>
                  <l>None gave a cup of drink to quench my thirſt:</l>
                  <l>Some mock'd, and ſaid, Thy Cloak is over-worn,</l>
                  <l>Thy knees are bare, thy rough-grown Beard's unſhorn.</l>
                  <l>O <hi>Candidus,</hi> Now leaveleſs were the Trees,</l>
                  <l>Cold Winter made the whited Mountains freeze.</l>
                  <l>I ſtorm'd, griev'd, ſcorn'd: Victual for us and ours</l>
                  <l>Devours up all; Male-lambs and wooll devours;</l>
                  <l>Our Female-lambs we fold not, but for breed</l>
                  <l>Reſerv'd them: And becauſe on Milk they feed,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe we kept them for the flocks ſupply,</l>
                  <l>Our Ewes we milk'd not; ſo their dugs grew dry.</l>
                  <l>I now repent my wit, if any part</l>
                  <l>Of wit I had, I now repent mine art:</l>
                  <l>My life repents me; ſith among ſo many</l>
                  <l>Reſplendent ſtars that nightly ſhine, not any</l>
                  <l>With favourable influence doth ſhine</l>
                  <l>Upon mine head, nor to my good incline.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:115715:26"/>Thou know'ſt I ſang till now without reward;</l>
                  <l>My youth not much in want, but little car'd:</l>
                  <l>But the condition of old age, which ſince</l>
                  <l>Hath ſeiz'd upon me, makes a difference</l>
                  <l>Far greater, and doth render me more poor,</l>
                  <l>More wanting neceſſaries then before,</l>
                  <l>More weak's my ſtrength (that ſtrength which doth remain)</l>
                  <l>And ſo cuts off all hopes of future gain.</l>
                  <l>But what I gain'd in youth, I muſt with ſpeed</l>
                  <l>Make uſe of (now's the time) to ſerve my need.</l>
                  <l>Behold the little Piſmire, prudent Creature,</l>
                  <l>And provident, doth by th'inſtinct of Nature</l>
                  <l>Within her hollow Cells, while Summer laſts,</l>
                  <l>Hoord up new Corn againſt cold Winters blaſts:</l>
                  <l>And leſt her hoorded Corn the ground hid under</l>
                  <l>Should grow, ſhe bites it with her mouth aſunder.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                  <l>They the Nativities can calculate</l>
                  <l>Do know (they ſay) the Stars of each mans fate:</l>
                  <l>For under <hi>Mercury</hi> they Poets place,</l>
                  <l>And under <hi>Jupiter</hi> the Royal Race</l>
                  <l>Of Kings and Potentates: <hi>Joves</hi> influence</l>
                  <l>To theſe gives gold and rich magnificence;</l>
                  <l>To thoſe doth nimble <hi>Mercury</hi> deviſe</l>
                  <l>Wit, Language, Muſick, Art to Poetize;</l>
                  <l>Theſe things are thine: Why ſeek'ſt thou riches then?</l>
                  <l>God all things doth divide amongſt all men</l>
                  <l>As moſt is for their good. O then ('tis beſt)</l>
                  <l>Go with thy lot content; leave us the reſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou riches do'ſt poſſeſs, I verſes have;</l>
                  <l>Why then <hi>Sylvanus</hi> do'ſt my verſes crave?</l>
                  <l>Why do'ſt intrude upon anothers part?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                  <l>I nor thy verſes, nor <hi>Apollo's</hi> art</l>
                  <l>Deſire to take from thee; but I deſire</l>
                  <l>To pleaſe mine ears with thy melodious Lyre,</l>
                  <l>With thy ſweet ſounding, ſweet reſounding verſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <l>If this thou wiſh, 'twere fit we did commerce;</l>
                  <l>That as <hi>(Sylvanus)</hi> thou my verſes haſt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:115715:27"/>I of thy riches ſo might have a taſte.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                  <l>He taſtes my wealth that loves me: but the kinde</l>
                  <l>That envies, hates; and with malignant minde</l>
                  <l>Repines at others goods, at others good.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <l>My verſe might thus be likewiſe underſtood</l>
                  <l>Enough by thee, though far remote I, and thus</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhalt of verſes have enough from us.</l>
                  <l>Verſe is our ears, Cheeſe is our mouths repaſt;</l>
                  <l>If thou thine ears wilt pleaſe, then pleaſe my taſte.</l>
                  <l>This Love, this Piety, this God commands:</l>
                  <l>God gives not all men all things in their hands,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe none ſhould ſuppoſe he doth exceed,</l>
                  <l>But one anothers ſuccour we ſhould need;</l>
                  <l>Which doth all Nations joyn through th'Univerſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>French, Moores, Italians, Spaniards,</hi> in Commerce.</l>
                  <l>Let's joyn our ſtars; make <hi>Jove</hi> on me reflect,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Mercury</hi> ſhall with benigne aſpect</l>
                  <l>Reflect on thee; ſhall give thee matchleſs things,</l>
                  <l>His Hat, Rod, Harp, <hi>Herculean</hi> Knot and wings.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy language with unneceſſary words,</l>
                  <l>Too many vain and fooliſh things affords.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou ſay'ſt that all things vain and fooliſh be,</l>
                  <l>That in thy riches ſeem t'indamage thee:</l>
                  <l>But if thou wilt my Muſe, my Verſes hear,</l>
                  <l>Rowſe up thy drowſie minde and make it clear</l>
                  <l>From worldly cares: A Verſe deſires to finde</l>
                  <l>A chearful heart, a clear, a candid minde.</l>
                  <l>But I dejected, frigid, indiſpos'd,</l>
                  <l>With hunger ſtupifi'd, with wants inclos'd,</l>
                  <l>Am circulating like a hungry Kite;</l>
                  <l>My mouth is ſcorch'd with thirſt, my skin (once white)</l>
                  <l>Long ſince grew black and wither'd; in my Fold</l>
                  <l>I have no Cattel, in my Purſe no Gold,</l>
                  <l>No Corn in Field: And (I thus poor and bare)</l>
                  <l>Would'ſt have me live ſecure, exempt from care?</l>
                  <l>This Med'cine is no cure for my diſtreſs;</l>
                  <l>Come, make me merry, clothe my nakedneſs,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:115715:27"/>Provide me food, my weak old age ſupply;</l>
                  <l>Thou then ſhalt hear me ſing and verſity.</l>
                  <l>Well furniſh'd houſes, Cellers full of wine,</l>
                  <l>Full veſſels, flaggons full, full food to dine,</l>
                  <l>Barns full of Corn, fair flocks that bear the Bell,</l>
                  <l>Full bags of money; Theſe all cares expell.</l>
                  <l>Then in <hi>December,</hi> in thoſe winter nights,</l>
                  <l>To ſit before the fire it much delights,</l>
                  <l>And there in th'aſhes (for a ſporting trick)</l>
                  <l>To plough up furrows with a little ſtick;</l>
                  <l>To roſt ripe Cheſtnuts there, and them all over</l>
                  <l>With embers till they roſted are, to cover;</l>
                  <l>With full fill'd glaſſes of refined wine</l>
                  <l>To quench our thirſt, to pleaſe our taſte. In fine,</l>
                  <l>Among the merry ſpinning Maids to ſit,</l>
                  <l>And hear them tell a Tale, and laught at it.</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Tityrus</hi> himſelf (as Fame doth ring)</l>
                  <l>By learn'd <hi>Mecoenas</hi> patroniz'd, did ſing</l>
                  <l>More lofty ſtrains of Farms, Fields, Cattel, Wars,</l>
                  <l>And with his high rais'd notes did reach the Stars;</l>
                  <l>Dame <hi>Fortune</hi> gave him eloquence: But us</l>
                  <l>Poor weak Plebeians, all bepatched thus,</l>
                  <l>Diſguis'd with leanneſs, fed with courſeſt grain,</l>
                  <l>The Muſes ſhun, <hi>Apollo</hi> doth diſdain.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                  <l>If Fortune, as I hop'd, my wiſh would grant,</l>
                  <l>I would, O <hi>Candidus,</hi> ſupply thy want.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <l>I would to God, <hi>Sylvanus,</hi> that thy will</l>
                  <l>Were but as prompt, as forward to fulfill</l>
                  <l>Thy promiſes, as thine eſtate doth riſe</l>
                  <l>Now great enough to give my want ſupplies.</l>
                  <l>I ſeek not <hi>Coſmus</hi> riches, nor deſire</l>
                  <l>Silk garments, Kingly fare, nor Cloaks of Tyre.</l>
                  <l>I hunger not for <hi>Aeſops</hi> coſtly diſh,</l>
                  <l>Nor for <hi>Minerva</hi>'s Buckler is my wiſh;</l>
                  <l>The Palaces I need not of that King,</l>
                  <l>To whom his iron coloured Beard did bring</l>
                  <l>A Name; or elſe if I miſtake it not,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:115715:28"/>That name by's braſen-colour'd beard he got.</l>
                  <l>Theſe things long ſince (I now remember well)</l>
                  <l>I learn'd of learned <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mber</hi> in his Cell.</l>
                  <l>I but apparel ask, I ſeek but food</l>
                  <l>Within ſome little Cottage: This more good</l>
                  <l>Will do then wealth, if of this I were ſure</l>
                  <l>It would with me, while life endures, endure.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pythag'ras</hi> Table, <hi>Codrus</hi> houſhold-ſtuff</l>
                  <l>Let me but have, and I ſhall have enough.</l>
                  <l>Oft have I found ſome that ſome hopes did ſhow,</l>
                  <l>Magnificent in words, in deeds but ſlow:</l>
                  <l>But I on thee depend, on thee but one;</l>
                  <l>If thou deceive me, then my hopes are gone:</l>
                  <l>I then ſhall mute, I tongueleſs ſhall become,</l>
                  <l>As in the Solſtice <hi>Philomel</hi> is dumb;</l>
                  <l>Then on the Poſts our arms we may ſuſpend,</l>
                  <l>The Play houſe ſhut, and give the Shows an end:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                  <l>O <hi>Candidus,</hi> haſt ſeen the City <hi>Rome?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Haſt ſeen the ſacred Synod thither come</l>
                  <l>Of Biſhops? where ſo many Poets are:</l>
                  <l>Where ſuch abundancs is of things ſo rare,</l>
                  <l>So beautiful? O 'tis a thing of eaſe</l>
                  <l>To gather wealth in ſuch fair fields as theſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou do'ſt miſtake, <hi>Sylvanus,</hi> if thou think</l>
                  <l>I covet to be rich: The Wolf doth drink</l>
                  <l>Raw blood, doth eat raw fleſh; and thinks indeed</l>
                  <l>All other Cattel as he feeds, to feed.</l>
                  <l>Thou faulty, thinkeſt others in thy fault,</l>
                  <l>And halting on the foot that thou doſt halt.</l>
                  <l>I ſeek not to be wealthy, but to live</l>
                  <l>Content with little, let them to me give</l>
                  <l>I ſhall contented be with meaneſt fare.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Romes</hi> Palaces I ſaw; but do'ſt ſuppoſe</l>
                  <l>That ever <hi>Rome</hi> did profit me with thoſe?</l>
                  <l>Dead is <hi>Auguſtus</hi> (ah) and in his Urn</l>
                  <l>Never, O never hither to return.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:115715:28"/>If <hi>Rome</hi> give any thing, ſhe gives but bables;</l>
                  <l>She takes our gold, and feeds us with her fables.</l>
                  <l>At <hi>Rome</hi> (alas) ſole Money now doth ſway,</l>
                  <l>Vertue's exil'd: but we muſt hope they ſay.</l>
                  <l>And now through all the world (<hi>Auguſtus</hi> dead)</l>
                  <l>Poor Poets onely with vain hopes are fed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                  <l>Come, ſpeak of fights, mens famous acts recite,</l>
                  <l>Speak of the Wars of Kings and men of might;</l>
                  <l>And when thou ſpeak'ſt, apply thy ſelf to them</l>
                  <l>That Scepters hold, and wear a Diadem,</l>
                  <l>That govern Kingdomes; Thou maiſt finde (perchance)</l>
                  <l>Among them ſome that will thy ſtate advance.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <l>I them ſhall finde that will me ſcoff and ſcorn,</l>
                  <l>Our Poeſie lies now ſo much forlorn,</l>
                  <l>And hath as much reſpect as have the Stews;</l>
                  <l>Why, O <hi>Sylvanus</hi> do'ſt provoke my Muſe?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                  <l>It is not ſeemly to provoke or wrong</l>
                  <l>A Poet with foul words, or laviſh tongue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <l>I cannot, I, but ſpeak the truth; but if</l>
                  <l>Thou wouldſt the truth ſhould be conceal'd, in brief,</l>
                  <l>Provoke me not with words unfitly ſpoke.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                  <l>To give good counſel is not to provoke.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <l>I'm rich in counſel, but moſt poor in gold;</l>
                  <l>How ſhall ſo poor a Poet then unfold</l>
                  <l>Fights, famous acts of men, and wars of Kings;</l>
                  <l>So poor a Poet, whoſe whole In come brings</l>
                  <l>Not means enough to buy a knife that's fit</l>
                  <l>To cut a Pipe aright with holes in it?</l>
                  <l>See what a ragged ſheath my knife is in,</l>
                  <l>The pin's dropp'd out; (it is not worth a pin)</l>
                  <l>Look on my knife which from the ſheath I draw,</l>
                  <l>It's edge is full of teeth, and like a Saw.</l>
                  <l>This yet were nothing; but where food is ſcant,</l>
                  <l>It is a great intolerable want.</l>
                  <l>Good Counſel ſtrengthens, but bad breaks ones heart,</l>
                  <l>Weakens the ſtrength, the courage doth ſubvert.</l>
                  <l>Great men will bluſh to give a gift that's ſmall,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:115715:29"/>And great they will not give; ſo none at all.</l>
                  <l>Adde, that our Kings a verſe as much affect,</l>
                  <l>As Northern winds the frondent leaves reſpect.</l>
                  <l>Or as the Southern winds indulge the Seas;</l>
                  <l>Or as cold-nipping froſts the Vineyards pleaſe.</l>
                  <l>Beſide that Kings themſelves inur'd to leiſure,</l>
                  <l>Pleaſing their ſenſes with delights and pleauſre,</l>
                  <l>What things they moſt affect, th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y moſt approve:</l>
                  <l>Hence wanton verſe is made of luſtful love,</l>
                  <l>Of ſcurrilous diſcourſe, of <hi>Ganymeds</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In Stews, of ſloth, of moſt infamous deeds;</l>
                  <l>Which for a modeſt Poet to diſpence</l>
                  <l>Were ſinful, were a capital offence.</l>
                  <l>But they whoſe warlike hands with Sword and Shield</l>
                  <l>Have fought pitch'd Battels in a bloody field;</l>
                  <l>Who man-like arm'd in ſteel their foes controll'd,</l>
                  <l>And not effeminately ſate in gold,</l>
                  <l>Lov'd the grave Muſes: And thoſe noble Kings,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe potent hands atchiev'd heroick things,</l>
                  <l>Heroick Verſes lov'd: But when (in fine)</l>
                  <l>Thoſe valiant men, thoſe Spirits Maſculine</l>
                  <l>Were once declin'd, no ſubject then was found,</l>
                  <l>Which Poets in their lofty ſtrains might ſound.</l>
                  <l>Then fell the Poets wit, then Poeſie</l>
                  <l>With all her lofty ſtrains did ruin'd lie.</l>
                  <l>But if perhaps ſome King ſhould now prepare</l>
                  <l>For bloody Wars, ſhould muſter up with care</l>
                  <l>Well armed Forces, ſhould with hot Alarms</l>
                  <l>Fierce Battels fight in honourable Arms:</l>
                  <l>If careleſs of his honour, he neglects</l>
                  <l>His Fame in Forraign Lands, or diſreſpects</l>
                  <l>Ages to come, contented with ſuch praiſe</l>
                  <l>As preſent times and his own Subjects raiſe,</l>
                  <l>Not valuing t'immortalize his Name</l>
                  <l>By Poets, in the Regiſters of Fame;</l>
                  <l>He's barbarous, and Verſes doth deteſt,</l>
                  <l>Or covetous, and doth himſelf incheſt</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:115715:29"/>Together with his gold, where drown'd he lies,</l>
                  <l>And with the burning cares of <hi>Midas</hi> fries.</l>
                  <l>And there are ſome that dare on Kings intrude</l>
                  <l>A rude, Malignant, ruſtick multitude,</l>
                  <l>Of jeſters, wantons, Paraſites, Compliers,</l>
                  <l>Adulterers, Stageplayers, Scoffing Liers,</l>
                  <l>Theſe all hate vertue; theſe a thouſand waies</l>
                  <l>Drive Poets from the King; as from their preyes</l>
                  <l>Crowes drive all other beaſts and birds, when they</l>
                  <l>Have found a new fall'n Carcaſe for their prey.</l>
                  <l>And there ſome lawleſſe, ſawcy Poets are<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who rudely bred without a Maſter, dare</l>
                  <l>What Kings affect (and Kings ſometimes affect</l>
                  <l>Ignoble things) in their weak dialect</l>
                  <l>To write, to regiſter; for Poets too</l>
                  <l>Are mad ſometimes; and theſe make much adoe,</l>
                  <l>I know not with what levity of mind,</l>
                  <l>To paſſe for Poets; Theſe, when once inclin'd</l>
                  <l>T' apply their mouths unto their trivial reeds</l>
                  <l>Themſelves applaud, and boaſt their verſe, their deeds,</l>
                  <l>Unelegant, conceitleſſe, of no prize,</l>
                  <l>Indocible, improvident, unwiſe.</l>
                  <l>He that to theſe vain fellows hearkens much,</l>
                  <l>Thinks the fault common, thinks all Poets ſuch;</l>
                  <l>So leaves the learned Poets; wanting skil</l>
                  <l>To know the true from falſe, the good from ill.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                  <l>I by the Gods, and by the <hi>Olympick</hi> pow'rs</l>
                  <l>O <hi>Candidus</hi> do ſwear, if Fates of ours</l>
                  <l>Succeſsful prove, I will thy wants ſupply,</l>
                  <l>Mean time, till better times, live happily.</l>
                  <l>Refuſe not then a little while to joyne,</l>
                  <l>For both our future goods, thine hopes with mine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ca.</speaker>
                  <l>If thus to me thou wiſh, I wiſh again</l>
                  <l>Thou, O <hi>Sylvanus,</hi> maiſt thy wiſh obtain.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                  <l>I wiſh indeed, and long it ſhall not be</l>
                  <l>Before I true performance make to thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <l>Go with a miſchief, never to return</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:115715:30"/>Moſt avaritious wretch, and quickly burn</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Midas</hi> Fever, quickly turn to gold</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Midas</hi> whatſoe're thou touch, or hold,</l>
                  <l>Or take, or taſt; ſith in the baſe eſteeem</l>
                  <l>Fair vertue, fouler then vile gold, doth ſeem.</l>
               </sp>
               <trailer>The end of the fifth Eclogue.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="eclogue">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:115715:30"/>
               <head>ECLOGUE VI. Treating of the difference between Citizens and Husbandmen. <hi>Intitled CORNIX.</hi>
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cornix</hi> deſcribes how different</l>
                  <l>The Citizens and Ruſticks be:</l>
                  <l>Then taxeth in his argument</l>
                  <l>The various Fooles of each degree.</l>
               </argument>
               <stage>The ſpeakers <hi>Cornix</hi> and <hi>Fulica.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Co.</speaker>
                  <l>NOw winter ſnows, the Northern wind doth roar</l>
                  <l>The Frozen icicles hang o're the door;</l>
                  <l>The Ploughman with his Oxen take their reſt</l>
                  <l>The ground's aſleep, and lies untill'd, undreſt:</l>
                  <l>The ſhepheard in his ruſſet Coat doth cloſe</l>
                  <l>The ſheepfolds, and doth ſluggiſhly repoſe!</l>
                  <l>Smoky <hi>Neaera</hi> ſits before the fire,</l>
                  <l>And pottage boyles; firſt Summers heat did tire,</l>
                  <l>But now 'tis prais'd: And winter praiſed then</l>
                  <l>Doth now diſpleaſe, and is disprais'd agen.</l>
                  <l>Inconſtant thus the preſent times abhor</l>
                  <l>That cold, which once they wiſh'd and hoped for.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>Good things expected ſeem more great, but leſſe</l>
                  <l>That good is thought, which preſent we poſſeſs:</l>
                  <l>As at a diſtance burning lights appear</l>
                  <l>Greater afar, and leſſer when more near.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
                  <l>Each ſeaſon hath it pleaſures, hath its joyes,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:115715:31"/>Look how the rough and ragged coated boyes,</l>
                  <l>Uncomb'd, undreſt, rejoyce when hogs are kill'd,</l>
                  <l>They take the Bladder, and till it be fill'd</l>
                  <l>With wind, their ſwelling Cheeks do puffe and blow</l>
                  <l>The Bladder like a Belly: Beans they throw</l>
                  <l>Into the Bladder, then it ſhines and ſounds,</l>
                  <l>They toſſe it up, and catch it at rebounds:</l>
                  <l>Now with their feet they kick it; by and by</l>
                  <l>Their armes imbrace it: if aloft it fly,</l>
                  <l>With ſtretchtout Fiſts they meet it, and again</l>
                  <l>Repell it: if it fall, they run amain</l>
                  <l>And mount it up; ſo toyling at their play,</l>
                  <l>Running, returning, winter's worn away:</l>
                  <l>The Country Football thus doth overcome</l>
                  <l>The winters cold; but we ſit here at home</l>
                  <l>In better caſe, under a warm thatch'd roofe)</l>
                  <l>Where (while the cold aloft is kept aloofe)</l>
                  <l>We paſſe the time, and warm our ſelves the while</l>
                  <l>Before the fire, until the milk do boyl.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>Cold winter doth our Poverty declare;</l>
                  <l>Doubtleſſe we young men all imprudent are,</l>
                  <l>And all improvident; while Summer laſts</l>
                  <l>We careleſſe walk, forgetfull of the Blaſts</l>
                  <l>Of winter, all our Coin we caſt away</l>
                  <l>Upon a fidler for a little play.</l>
                  <l>But when the Northern wind returns with Froſts</l>
                  <l>From the <hi>Moſcovian</hi> or <hi>Scythian</hi> Coaſts,</l>
                  <l>The trees unclothing, when the naked trees</l>
                  <l>All leaveleſſe ſhew the birds neſts built in theſe,</l>
                  <l>We naked then are pinch'd with cold, our back,</l>
                  <l>Feet, ſhoulders clothing, Food our bellies lack.</l>
                  <l>Winter declares our fooliſhneſſe; more wiſe</l>
                  <l>Are Citizens, their heaps of money riſe,</l>
                  <l>They warmly cloth themſelves, and furre their Coats</l>
                  <l>With skins of Foxes, Lynxes, Lambes, and Goats.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
                  <l>All men are mad; nor are we ſole in fault:</l>
                  <l>Yea rather greater madneſſe doth aſſault</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:115715:31"/>The Citizens themſelves; but yet in this</l>
                  <l>Fortune their mother, our Stepmother is.</l>
                  <l>If hapleſſe Fortune us oppreſſe, our Fate</l>
                  <l>Is madneſſe then: make me but Fortunate,</l>
                  <l>I ſhall be rich, I ſhall the chiefeſt be</l>
                  <l>Within the City, all will riſe to me,</l>
                  <l>Will liſten all: The vulgar then will ſtand,</l>
                  <l>And men of middle rank with Cap in hand,</l>
                  <l>They me wil honour; all the multitude</l>
                  <l>Will ask my Counſel: and there will intrude</l>
                  <l>Upon me for adviſe the Magiſtrate,</l>
                  <l>The People, and the Senators of State.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>O <hi>Cornix, Cornix:</hi> 'tis not Fortune: 'tis</l>
                  <l>The wiſer ſoul of man that acteth this:</l>
                  <l>Fortune can none or great, or happy make,</l>
                  <l>'Tis God that doth it; as <hi>Amyntas</hi> ſpake.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, Fortune is a God; but tell I pray</l>
                  <l>What did <hi>Amyntas</hi> of this matter ſay?</l>
                  <l>For he was wiſe and learned, he did know</l>
                  <l>The cauſe of things above, of things below,</l>
                  <l>But yet, a little e're thou tell, go ſee</l>
                  <l>The Fodderſtalls, and how the Cattle be:</l>
                  <l>Go quickly, quickly come; and heat thee ſo:</l>
                  <l>Heat after cold's more ſweet; go quickly, go.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>The ſnow's ſo deep, it reacheth to my knees:</l>
                  <l>Our houſes ſcarce will bear ſuch loads as theſe:</l>
                  <l>A towring pile, on yonder Chimnies head,</l>
                  <l>Sharp pointed, mounteth like a Pyramid.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
                  <l>Give Fodder to the Cattle in the ſtalls,</l>
                  <l>Stop up with ſtraw the Chincks about the walls;</l>
                  <l>Which done, make faſt the doors, make ſure the Fold,</l>
                  <l>Nothing doth hurt the Cattle more then cold.</l>
                  <l>What art already come? Oh, what's this haſt</l>
                  <l>So much unwonted, that thou com'ſt ſo faſt?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>Winter me careful makes in froſt for fire;</l>
                  <l>But 'tis more ſtrenuous, and I more deſire</l>
                  <l>To make my lodging in the warmeſt hey:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:115715:32"/>There in an hollow bed my ſelf to lay,</l>
                  <l>'Tis comfort after cold: I need no ſheets.</l>
                  <l>That bed is full of heat, is full of ſweets.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
                  <l>Begin, and what the diff'rent manners are</l>
                  <l>Of Citizens and Country men declare.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>Thus then, this difference in each eſtate,</l>
                  <l>Which did thoſe two ſo much diſcriminiate</l>
                  <l>Began, as our <hi>Amyntas</hi> did relate.</l>
                  <l>In the beginning when things firſt began,</l>
                  <l>The great Creator, God, Created man;</l>
                  <l>And with the woman joyning him in love,</l>
                  <l>That glorious Maker of the skies above</l>
                  <l>(For thus <hi>Amyntas</hi> called God; this name</l>
                  <l>I well remember yet) will'd them to frame</l>
                  <l>Themſelves to generate a noble breed</l>
                  <l>Of Children, taught them how to raiſe their ſeed.</l>
                  <l>They fall to work, and faithfully fulfill</l>
                  <l>The Lords command: and would to God they ſtill</l>
                  <l>Had kept it, and not broke it, as they did</l>
                  <l>By taſting the apples of the Tree forbid.</l>
                  <l>The woman is a Mother now become,</l>
                  <l>Brave boyes and girles did iſſue from her womb,</l>
                  <l>And fruitful ſhe by Childbirth ev'ry year</l>
                  <l>A Child or Children, did ſucceſsful bear:</l>
                  <l>So that ſhe multiplied the generations</l>
                  <l>Of mankind by thoſe frequent Propagations.</l>
                  <l>The Lord return'd when thrice five years were ſpent;</l>
                  <l>The woman as ſhe ſate within her Tent</l>
                  <l>Dreſſing her Children, looking out before</l>
                  <l>Perceiv'd him comming, almoſt at the door.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Adam</hi> was abſent: He ſecure did ſeed</l>
                  <l>His bleating Flocks, no baſe adul'trous breed,</l>
                  <l>No foul adult'rer was ſuſpected then:</l>
                  <l>But woman afterwards conjoyn'd to men</l>
                  <l>By multiplied Marriages, the Truſt</l>
                  <l>Between them brake, and was deceiv'd by luſt.</l>
                  <l>Then Goates were made without apparant hornes,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:115715:32"/>The jealous husband then ſuſpects and ſcornes</l>
                  <l>His chaſt (perhaps) his loyall wife: Thus they</l>
                  <l>That others wrong, think others them betray.</l>
                  <l>The mother bluſh'd: and doubting leſt (in fine)</l>
                  <l>Her many Children were a pregnant ſigne</l>
                  <l>Of too much Luſt: with ſpeediſhe puts aſide</l>
                  <l>Some of her Sons, and them with hey doth hide,</l>
                  <l>Stubble or ſtraw: The Lord by this time came</l>
                  <l>Into the Tent, bleſs'd all within the ſame:</l>
                  <l>Woman, ſaid he, produce thy children here,</l>
                  <l>She then commands her eldeſt Sons t' appear.</l>
                  <l>God ſmil'd upon them as we uſe to ſmile</l>
                  <l>On pretty Birds, or little whelpes: the while</l>
                  <l>He ſmiling ſaid unto the firſt of them,</l>
                  <l>Take thou the Scepter and the Diadem,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhalt be King: The glitt'ring ſword and ſhield</l>
                  <l>With other warlike weapons of the Field</l>
                  <l>He gave unto the ſecond: Thou, ſaith he,</l>
                  <l>A Duke, and Captain in the wars ſhalt be.</l>
                  <l>The peoples Axes, and their rods of broom,</l>
                  <l>The gentle Vine, the darts of famous <hi>Rome</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He then produc'd, and on them all a row</l>
                  <l>That then were viſible, he did beſtow</l>
                  <l>Thoſe noble gifts: when God had thus beſtow'd</l>
                  <l>Among the children there that then were ſhew'd</l>
                  <l>The Regall Rule, the places of command,</l>
                  <l>The Magiſtracy, ſilent he did ſtand,</l>
                  <l>Weighing thoſe honours he conferr'd on Man:</l>
                  <l>Mean while the woman glad that things began</l>
                  <l>So luckily, with ſpeedy poſture runs</l>
                  <l>Unto the ſheepcoats, and from thence her Sons</l>
                  <l>Which there were hid and under Fodder laid</l>
                  <l>She voluntary brings: and thus ſhe ſaid,</l>
                  <l>Theſe alſo be my Children, O no leſſe</l>
                  <l>Almighty Father theſe my Children bleſſe.</l>
                  <l>Their briſtled heads were white with chaffe, with ſtraw,</l>
                  <l>With Cobwebs foul their ſhoulders: which when ſaw</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:115715:33"/>He did not ſmile on them, but caſting down</l>
                  <l>His troubled looks o'reclouded with a Frown,</l>
                  <l>You ſmell (ſaid God) of ſtubble, earth and hey;</l>
                  <l>Yours then ſhall be the Goad, the Spade, the Clay,</l>
                  <l>Your ſhare ſhall be the Ploughſhare, yours the yokes,</l>
                  <l>Yours all the Tools of Tillage, Carts, Wheels, Spokes.</l>
                  <l>Some ſhall be Ploughmen, ſome ſhall overſee</l>
                  <l>The Cattle, ſome of you ſhall ſhepheards be.</l>
                  <l>Some ſhall be mowers, ſome ſhall dig the ground,</l>
                  <l>Some Seamen, others Heardſmen ſhall be found.</l>
                  <l>But ſome of you we'l make of Cities free,</l>
                  <l>Yet you but <hi>Botchers</hi> ſhall or <hi>Butchers</hi> be,</l>
                  <l>Bakers or skullions, or the like by Trade</l>
                  <l>Accuſtom'd to be ſordid, onely made</l>
                  <l>For daily labour; and (till death) at beſt</l>
                  <l>You, ſervile, ſhall be ſervants to the reſt:</l>
                  <l>This ſaid, th' Almighty reaſcended Heaven.</l>
                  <l>Thus ſervitude was to the Country given,</l>
                  <l>Thus, as <hi>Amyntas</hi> ſaid, the diff'rence ran</l>
                  <l>Betwixt the Citizen and Country man.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhould have wond'red if <hi>Amyntas</hi> ſpake</l>
                  <l>Ought that was right, or which for us could make:</l>
                  <l>He was a Citizen; and City youths</l>
                  <l>(That have no buſineſſe but to forge untruths</l>
                  <l>And fooliſh Fables) us inceſſant mock,</l>
                  <l>And moke poor Country men their laughin ſtock.</l>
                  <l>The Cities talkative and pratling veine,</l>
                  <l>Such Fopperies and vanities doth feigne.</l>
                  <l>Nor do they bluſh to frame theſe trifling lies</l>
                  <l>Of the Supream-ſupernall deities.</l>
                  <l>This jeſting with the Gods ('tis manifeſt)</l>
                  <l>Is rayling Blaſphemy, no pleaſing jeſt.</l>
                  <l>But art ſo witleſſe, do thy Tripes ſo ſwell</l>
                  <l>Within thy belly, that thou canſt not tell,</l>
                  <l>Nor do'ſt perceive that while with Cenſures ſharp</l>
                  <l>Theſe carpe at others, at thy ſelf they Carp?</l>
                  <l>But yet a little let's our ſelves apply</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:115715:33"/>To note the Cities Follies, leſt thine eye</l>
                  <l>Deceiv'd (perhaps) with ſhews, ſhould'ſt theſe men hold</l>
                  <l>More wiſe, more happy that in burniſh'd gold,</l>
                  <l>Rich Purple, or fine Skarlet glitt'ring ſhine,</l>
                  <l>I many men have ſeen with theſe mine eine</l>
                  <l>In brave apparrel with Majeſtick pace</l>
                  <l>Walking about the publick Market place,</l>
                  <l>Whom ſecret hunger and domeſtick want</l>
                  <l>Have ſorely pinch'd, as if concomitant.</l>
                  <l>Doubtleſſe in this the greateſt follies lie:</l>
                  <l>For feyned wealth is reall poverty:</l>
                  <l>And what doth ſloth of life, or ſluggiſhneſſe</l>
                  <l>But madneſſe in reality expreſſe?</l>
                  <l>I likewiſe have ſome Fathers ſeen (O vile,</l>
                  <l>Unworthy, wicked men) who, that the while</l>
                  <l>Themſelves may neatly live, may ſleep and play,</l>
                  <l>Their faire<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t daughters fouly do betray,</l>
                  <l>Do proſtitute to men of meaneſt race</l>
                  <l>In Brothel houſes: what more bad, more baſe;</l>
                  <l>What more perfidious, what more fooliſh ever?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>But what it otherwiſe their beſt endeavour</l>
                  <l>Could not ſupport their lives with fit ſupplies?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, ſith they have as many ſoules, and eies,</l>
                  <l>And hands as we, why ſhould they not, in ſort</l>
                  <l>Like us with fit ſupplies their lives ſupport?</l>
                  <l>And ſome there are who madly ſeek in vain</l>
                  <l>For wealth, where yet no mortal wealth could gain</l>
                  <l>From the beginning: they their braſſe and tin</l>
                  <l>Waſh with the juyce of herbs, and then begin</l>
                  <l>Their chymick diſtillations, and are bold</l>
                  <l>To think t' extract from thence moſt perfect gold.</l>
                  <l>But (ah) from thence no gold they can exhale,</l>
                  <l>Their metal with black duskineſſe is pale.</l>
                  <l>Some likewiſe are, that hidden gold to find</l>
                  <l>Under the ground, the ground have undermin'd:</l>
                  <l>Have us'd black Magick, and in inchanting ſpells,</l>
                  <l>Theſe time and labour loſe, gain nothing elſe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:115715:34"/>What more uncertain, what more vain thoſe?</l>
                  <l>What ever did more fooliſhneſſe diſcloſe?</l>
                  <l>Theſe all things, that they Country work may fly</l>
                  <l>All things I ſay wil undertake, wil try,</l>
                  <l>And to do nothing, all things will pretend:</l>
                  <l>Theſe ever are beginning, never end;</l>
                  <l>By ſinful Uſury they dare extort</l>
                  <l>Their infamous ſupplies, their baſe ſupport,</l>
                  <l>Their hooks with force, with cunning, with deceit</l>
                  <l>Of Food, of maintenance; and alwaies bait</l>
                  <l>A thouſand waies for wealth, a thouſand waies</l>
                  <l>They ſeek for honours, how themſelves to raiſe.</l>
                  <l>We Country men keep Cattle, Goats, and Sheep;</l>
                  <l>Theſe dogs, hawks, horſes, Apes, and Monkies keep.</l>
                  <l>The ſhepheard feeds his Flocks and hea<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>t theſe</l>
                  <l>Feed Hawks and Hounds; judge now which moſt doth pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>Which of theſe are more great, more noble things</l>
                  <l>O <hi>Fulick?</hi> which moſt wealth, moſt profit brings?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>If from our labours greater wealth ariſe,</l>
                  <l>Whence then have Citizens ſuch ſtore of prize?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
                  <l>They gain by fraud, by cunning and by force:</l>
                  <l>Force, cunning, fraud their labour is, their courſe.</l>
                  <l>See'ſt not (thou fool) how cruelly they preſſe</l>
                  <l>Us husbandmen, what baits for us they dreſſe;</l>
                  <l>With what great craft they catch us? to provoke</l>
                  <l>Our tongues to ſpeak, what is not to be ſpoke,</l>
                  <l>A ſacrifice they think from them proceeds,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe ſome pious, meritorious deeds,</l>
                  <l>To compaſſe which, ſtill preſt at their command</l>
                  <l>Are all their ears, their eies, their mouths, their hands.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>But how ſo wel acquainted haſt thou been</l>
                  <l>With the conditions of the Citizen?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
                  <l>I learn'd this heretofore, when I my Goats</l>
                  <l>Driving within the City from the Coats</l>
                  <l>Sold there, my milk crying up and down.</l>
                  <l>I ſojourn'd with a Baker in the Town:</l>
                  <l>A Crafty fellow, prompt to their, to guile:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:115715:34"/>That underpar'd his half bak'd-bread with File.</l>
                  <l>He skilful in the City manners there</l>
                  <l>Related this: and did, affirming, ſwear</l>
                  <l>That then the City, nothing doth reveal</l>
                  <l>More miſchief, that he there did learn to ſteal.</l>
                  <l>And ſome there are, that having great eſtate</l>
                  <l>Left by their Predeceſſors, or the Fates,</l>
                  <l>On whores profufely ſpend them. O then this,</l>
                  <l>What more obſcoene, O what more wicked is?</l>
                  <l>Come, tell me where are murtherers? where's the trade</l>
                  <l>Of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>oring us'd? where is ſedition made?</l>
                  <l>Is't not among the Citizens reſorts?</l>
                  <l>Raign not thoſe things within the City ports?</l>
                  <l>What think'ſt of Kings, that others Kingdoms gain</l>
                  <l>By blood, that force their ſubjects to be ſlain?</l>
                  <l>What of the ſouldier that dares oppoſe</l>
                  <l>His breaſt to naked ſwords? that undergoes</l>
                  <l>A thouſand dangers, one that for his pay</l>
                  <l>Hazards his life, or throws his life away?</l>
                  <l>Then this no greater madneſſe; ſeeming glory</l>
                  <l>(Though momentary, though but tranſitory)</l>
                  <l>To life's preferr'd: a little praiſe they prize</l>
                  <l>Above their lives, above their liberties.</l>
                  <l>But what is glory? what is praiſe? what's fame?</l>
                  <l>What's honour but a vain, an empty name?</l>
                  <l>'Tis but the opinion, but the voice, the vote</l>
                  <l>Of the rude vulgar, which like froth doth float.</l>
                  <l>Theſe times to come will baniſh, will forget,</l>
                  <l>All theſe will vaniſh when thy Life doth ſet:</l>
                  <l>As when the ſetting Sun at night declines,</l>
                  <l>The night comes on, the Light no longer ſhines.</l>
                  <l>They that the Seas ſail over when they may</l>
                  <l>Live ſafe at land are fools: and fools are they</l>
                  <l>That put their truſt to water and to wind:</l>
                  <l>So they that riches have, and have no mind</l>
                  <l>T'imploy their riches are but fools; and thoſe</l>
                  <l>That for their children heaps of gold repoſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:115715:35"/>But pinch themſelves, and their own bellies cheat</l>
                  <l>Are greateſt fooles: yet there's a fool as great</l>
                  <l>That what himſelf might do, leaves to be done</l>
                  <l>After his death by's ſucceſſor or Son.</l>
                  <l>They who the Starrs obſerve, and thence their Fate</l>
                  <l>Suppoſe to comprehend or calculate</l>
                  <l>Are Frantick fools: and he's more mad that pries</l>
                  <l>Into Gods nature, or his ſecrecies:</l>
                  <l>That dares upon that vaſt immortal light</l>
                  <l>Fix his but mortal, and too feeble ſight.</l>
                  <l>Our faith is better: we believe by faith</l>
                  <l>All that, though but in words the Scripture ſaith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Citizen doth ſcarce herein aſſent,</l>
                  <l>Though forc'd with reaſon and with argument:</l>
                  <l>And on the ſacred Altars one may ken</l>
                  <l>More Lamps of ours then of the Citizen.</l>
                  <l>Their faith is faithleſſe too: they daily ſet</l>
                  <l>Their minds to ſearch into the Cabinet</l>
                  <l>Of Gods decrees: But if't were fit to know</l>
                  <l>Them, or his Perſon, God would pleaſe to ſhow</l>
                  <l>Himſelf and them: but ſith his will implies</l>
                  <l>They ſhould be ſecret, what neceſſitie's</l>
                  <l>We ſhould deſire to know thoſe hidden things</l>
                  <l>Which are deni'd us by the King of Kings:</l>
                  <l>And our devotion for all pious deeds</l>
                  <l>The City Pieties excells, exceeds:</l>
                  <l>For what abundance of all ſorts of grain,</l>
                  <l>Of food, is gather'd in a day or twain</l>
                  <l>From Country men, by thoſe that miniſtring</l>
                  <l>Within the Temple ſacred Anthemes ſing?</l>
                  <l>My ſelf have ſeen things ſo collected load</l>
                  <l>Ful ſhips, which ſail'd within the walls, and rode</l>
                  <l>Within the Cities harbour: ſuch the zeal</l>
                  <l>Is of the Country for the Churces weal.</l>
                  <l>And ther' another kind of fools, a ſort</l>
                  <l>Immedicable, yet of great report,</l>
                  <l>Lawyers, Court brawlers, pleaders of a cauſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:115715:35"/>Skill'd to gain money, Tyrants of the Laws.</l>
                  <l>They ſel their Patronage for golden pay,</l>
                  <l>To trifle Cauſes out with long delay,</l>
                  <l>To make them long depend with a dilemme,</l>
                  <l>A vanity is, a Vintage is to them.</l>
                  <l>Another kind of fools on horſeback are</l>
                  <l>Unlearn'd Phyſitians, Mountibanks that dare</l>
                  <l>Touch veines, ſometimes unlawful for to touch</l>
                  <l>Theſe on diſeaſes (underſtood as much</l>
                  <l>By them, as by their horſes) will impoſe</l>
                  <l>Some new found names, their raſh adviſe to cloſe:</l>
                  <l>Theſe, though they grope in darkneſſe, ignorant</l>
                  <l>Of what they do profeſſe; yet have a grant</l>
                  <l>Sick perſons to torment, and at their wil</l>
                  <l>Unpuniſh'd, whom they cannot cure, to kill.</l>
                  <l>They that are rulers of the people, they</l>
                  <l>That govern others, making them obey,</l>
                  <l>The more command, the more of pow'r they have,</l>
                  <l>The more inſultingly they rage, they rave.</l>
                  <l>O where are pious Rulers now, O where</l>
                  <l>Do pieties and juſtice Friends appear,</l>
                  <l>Whom (once) our Fathers ſitting by the fire</l>
                  <l>Were wont to name, remember and admire.</l>
                  <l>All things go now to wrack: the Temple's ſpoil'd</l>
                  <l>Demoliſh'd, ruin'd, robb'd, defac'd, defil'd,</l>
                  <l>And of the wrongs complains: the poor lament,</l>
                  <l>Sigh, groan: The widows weep with diſcontent.</l>
                  <l>But what's the cauſe which doth theſe miſchiefs cauſe?</l>
                  <l>Becauſe baſe Luſt doth rule in ſtead of Lawes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>O <hi>Cornix,</hi> this thy fury doth tranſcend</l>
                  <l>The bounds of honeſty: thou doſt extend</l>
                  <l>All ſins againſt all men; remember well</l>
                  <l>Some harmeleſſe men ev'n in the City dwel.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
                  <l>In certain fields (I now forget their names)</l>
                  <l>Near <hi>Baleares</hi> Iles, no ſnake inflames</l>
                  <l>With ſtinging: For no ſnakes inhabit there:</l>
                  <l>Nor Owles in <hi>Creete,</hi> nor horſes will appear</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:115715:36"/>In <hi>Arecina's</hi> or <hi>Aegeria's</hi> wood,</l>
                  <l>Nor in City dwells a man that's good.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>Good men rare creatures, vertues are moſt rare,</l>
                  <l>And in few Cities, in few Countries are.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
                  <l>Th'art mad O <hi>Fulica,</hi> th'art mad: For thou</l>
                  <l>As many foes haſt in the City now</l>
                  <l>As there are Citizens: they pil and pol</l>
                  <l>Poor us without reſpect, without control,</l>
                  <l>Us they conſtrain to ſteal, and then they ſend</l>
                  <l>Our bodies to the gallows to ſuſpend.</l>
                  <l>'Tis therefore juſt, nor is't againſt the Lawes</l>
                  <l>That whatſo're of theirs comes in our clawes</l>
                  <l>We gripe, we ſhave it: and from them, from thence</l>
                  <l>What e're we gain by craft or diligence</l>
                  <l>To plume it lightly, ſoftly by degrees:</l>
                  <l>And if that any by misfortune ſees</l>
                  <l>The theft exceuſe it, if unſeen deny it.</l>
                  <l>The theft that hidden is, no wrong comes by it.</l>
                  <l>For whatſo're the Citizens poſſeſſe</l>
                  <l>Is all our labour, all our painfulneſſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou roveſt now, now the moſt aequal line</l>
                  <l>Of right and reaſon thou doſt much decline.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
                  <l>O <hi>Fulica,</hi> the wickedneſſe that raignes</l>
                  <l>In Cities all the word defiles, diſtaines.</l>
                  <l>Whence come in Summers prime thoſe horrid ſtormes,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe flouds, winds, hail, and water which deformes</l>
                  <l>The verdant Earth? I well remember, I</l>
                  <l>Have ſeen the trembling Earth a quaking lie,</l>
                  <l>Poſts ſhaking, houſes ſliding as affright,</l>
                  <l>I ſaw the Sun by day, the Moon by night</l>
                  <l>Ecclips'd, obſcur'd why do the tares ore' top</l>
                  <l>The Corn, why ſpoil wild oates our harveſt Crop?</l>
                  <l>The Vince doth wiers bear in ſtead of grapes,</l>
                  <l>Unwholſome cloudy-weather blaſts, miſ-ſhapes</l>
                  <l>The vernall flow'rs: and all theſe ills, this curſe</l>
                  <l>The City ſins produce, and will bring worſe.</l>
                  <l>Whence come tumltuous wars, and horrid armes</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:115715:36"/>Which carry with them whatſoever harms,</l>
                  <l>Whatever evil is? within the walls</l>
                  <l>Of Cities, as from their Originalls,</l>
                  <l>As from their Fountains all theſe miſchiefs ſpring.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lycaon</hi> was a Citizen, a King.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Deucalion,</hi> with his beloved wife</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fyrrha,</hi> were Country dwellers all their life.</l>
                  <l>That brought the deluge, this remov'd the ſame,</l>
                  <l>That ruin'd mankind, this did man reframe.</l>
                  <l>If ever (as they ſay) theſe goodly frames</l>
                  <l>Of skies, Earth, Seas, ſhall be conſum'd with flames</l>
                  <l>This heavy judgement doubtleſſe will come in</l>
                  <l>For ſins of Citizens, for Cities ſin.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ful.</speaker>
                  <l>O <hi>Cornix,</hi> let us put a period</l>
                  <l>To this diſcourſe: 'tis dinner time, and ſod</l>
                  <l>The pottage is: I heard the boy's e're while</l>
                  <l>Speak of the Pottage: if of Cities guile</l>
                  <l>There any thing remains unſaid, to ſay,</l>
                  <l>Then ſpeak it after dinner: come away,</l>
                  <l>Let's go to dinner: 'tis an hour for meat</l>
                  <l>Weel leave the Cities, and our pottage eat.</l>
               </sp>
               <trailer>The End of the ſixth Eclogue.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="eclogue">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:115715:37"/>
               <head>ECLOGUE VII. Treating of the Converſion of young men to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, when the Author began to take Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Orders. <hi>Intituled POLLUX.</hi>
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <l>Here <hi>Galbula</hi> the Shepheards praiſe</l>
                  <l>Mounts to the ſtars; relateth how</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pollux</hi> by ſight of ſacred raies</l>
                  <l>Converts, and doth Religion vow.</l>
               </argument>
               <stage>The ſpeakers <hi>Alphus</hi> and <hi>Galbula.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>WHat think'ſt O <hi>Galbula,</hi> that where of yore</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pollux</hi> the beſt of pipers, and before</l>
                  <l>The reſt preferr'd, now ſuddainly retir'd,</l>
                  <l>And, as't by ſome power divine inſpird,</l>
                  <l>His Pipes, Coat, Flocks and fellows he forſook,</l>
                  <l>And to religious vows himſelf betook,</l>
                  <l>His head doth wear an hood, his back a gown,</l>
                  <l>Like a field Larke he looks with tufted Crown:</l>
                  <l>Four daies before he did himſelf confine</l>
                  <l>To the religious Cloyſter, a divine,</l>
                  <l>A ſacred apparition, as alone</l>
                  <l>He fed his Cattle in the paſtures, ſhone</l>
                  <l>Moſt clear about him, which (they ſay) he ſaw;</l>
                  <l>And ever ſince from us he did withdraw.</l>
                  <l>The reſt I now remember not ywis;</l>
                  <l>But what O <hi>Galbula,</hi> what think'ſt of this?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:115715:37"/>
                  <speaker>Gal.</speaker>
                  <l>As our forefathers did affirm long ſince</l>
                  <l>(For I will utter things of conſequence,</l>
                  <l>Which learned <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mber</hi> did of yore relate)</l>
                  <l>In the beginning, when mans firſt eſtate</l>
                  <l>God did diſpoſe and order, he did will</l>
                  <l>Some ſhould be ſhepherds, ſome the ground ſhould till.</l>
                  <l>He that the ground firſt till'd, war rude, ſharp, rough,</l>
                  <l>Like the ſtiff-ſtony ground that checks the plough:</l>
                  <l>But the firſt ſhepherd was a gentle childe,</l>
                  <l>Moſt like the ſheep, the ſheep (a creature milde)</l>
                  <l>Which floweth milk, which are from choler clear:</l>
                  <l>He (gentle) to no ſhepherd was ſevere,</l>
                  <l>Oft from his flock he brought a ſacrifice</l>
                  <l>Unto the ſacred Altar: There he fries</l>
                  <l>A fatted Calf ſometimes, ſometimes a ſheep,</l>
                  <l>But oftentimes a lamb: He thus did keep</l>
                  <l>A conſtant courſe of worſhip, that thereby</l>
                  <l>He brought great honour to the Deity.</l>
                  <l>He ſo prevail'd with God, ſo well appeas'd</l>
                  <l>The Godhead, that the Deity was pleas'd</l>
                  <l>From the beginning to this time to fence</l>
                  <l>All Cattel with his careful Providence.</l>
                  <l>God then ſome ſhepherds of <hi>Aſsyria</hi> choſe,</l>
                  <l>(The names I now remember not of thoſe,</l>
                  <l>Cares ſo diſtract my minde) made kings of them,</l>
                  <l>And crown'd them with a Regal Diadem.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe (after) cloth'd in Purple and with Gold</l>
                  <l>I ſaw, they conquer'd Nations proud and bold.</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Paris</hi> ſaw three Goddeſſes (with joy)</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Ida's</hi> Mountain near to famous <hi>Troy,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Paris,</hi> or ſome one, that would (alas)</l>
                  <l>Have ſacrific'd his ſon, a ſhepherd was.</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Moſes,</hi> frighted with Coeleſtial fire,</l>
                  <l>Went bare foot on the ground to ſee, t'admire</l>
                  <l>The wonder, <hi>Moſes</hi> was a ſhepherd then,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Moſes,</hi> extracted from the wat'ry Fen.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Apollo</hi> from his Throne depos'd, exil'd</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:115715:38"/>In <hi>Greece,</hi> and wand'ring up and down the wild</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Theſſalian</hi> fields, a ſhepherd did abide,</l>
                  <l>Laying the greatneſs of his ſtate aſide.</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Chriſt</hi> was in the ſtable born, a Quire</l>
                  <l>Of Heavens Angels, glorious in attire,</l>
                  <l>Did to the ſhepherds in the ſheep cotes ſing</l>
                  <l>The birth of Earths Redeemer, Heavens King.</l>
                  <l>The ſhepherds having then that wonder heard</l>
                  <l>Of Chriſts diviner birth, did not retard,</l>
                  <l>But ran with ſpeed, the ground they lightly trod,</l>
                  <l>And were the firſt that ſaw the Son of God.</l>
                  <l>That little Infant, which on high doth reign</l>
                  <l>Sole King of kings, did to thoſe ſhepherds deign</l>
                  <l>Himſelf, his Cradle to behold, before</l>
                  <l>The Wiſe-men or the Kings did him adore.</l>
                  <l>And God himſelf, himſelf a Shepherd ſtyles,</l>
                  <l>Styles thoſe his Sheep, thoſe men who free from wiles</l>
                  <l>Are of milde nature, of a lowly minde,</l>
                  <l>Of upright heart, to no deceit inclin'd.</l>
                  <l>And leſt theſe words of mine thou ſhould'ſt conceit</l>
                  <l>As a vain dream, inſolid, wanting weight,</l>
                  <l>I'le tell thee more. As from the Town I came</l>
                  <l>Into the Countrey, I beheld the ſame</l>
                  <l>But very lately; I theſe wonders all</l>
                  <l>Saw lively painted on a Churches wall.</l>
                  <l>There Sheep were painted, painted were the Lambs,</l>
                  <l>As if down lying by their bleating Dams:</l>
                  <l>A num'rous Troop of gallant horſemen there,</l>
                  <l>Diſmounting from a Mountain, painted were,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Coroents did ſhine with burniſh'd gold,</l>
                  <l>A noble gallant ſight; which to behold,</l>
                  <l>Detain'd all paſſengers with wond'ring eyes.</l>
                  <l>No marvel then if of the Deities</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Pollux</hi> one might ſee: For thoſe above</l>
                  <l>Love Villages, they ſheep and ſheep-cotes love.</l>
                  <l>God preſent is with ſimple, ſingle breaſts,</l>
                  <l>But (with deceit diſpleas'd) deceit deteſts.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:115715:38"/>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou ſpeak'ſt the truth, if that the Paſtures prove</l>
                  <l>Unhurtful to the Cattel of our Drove.</l>
                  <l>I ſaw both Oxe and Aſſe, and Fodder-ſtall</l>
                  <l>With thoſe brave horſemen painted on the wall:</l>
                  <l>I now remember what I then did eye</l>
                  <l>Preſented there in rich Imagery;</l>
                  <l>I ſeem'd to ſee thoſe Oriental Kings</l>
                  <l>Preſenting Gifts of Gold and precious things</l>
                  <l>Unto the Babe. But one thing I intreat,</l>
                  <l>O <hi>Galbula;</hi> which, if thou know'ſt, repeat.</l>
                  <l>What Apparition was't, which did accoſt</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Pollux?</hi> Speak; think not thy labour loſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gal.</speaker>
                  <l>I do both know it, and it likes me well</l>
                  <l>To tell it: 'tis a worthy thing to tell</l>
                  <l>A thing well worth our hearing, a relation</l>
                  <l>Religious, holy, worth our imitation.</l>
                  <l>A ſharp hard-hearted Father, and a proud,</l>
                  <l>A rigid Stepmother, ſeverely bow'd</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Pollux</hi> in his youth; his youth, the time</l>
                  <l>When ſweeteſt ſweetned thoughts are in their prime.</l>
                  <l>And when inceſſant labour had at length</l>
                  <l>Much weak'ned his infirm, invalid ſtrength:</l>
                  <l>When by no means or art he could aſſwage</l>
                  <l>His Step-dames malice or his Fathers rage,</l>
                  <l>He did reſolve to run away: but yet</l>
                  <l>One thing his reſolution long did let,</l>
                  <l>And that was love; too paſſionate he mov'd,</l>
                  <l>With too too much impatience he lov'd.</l>
                  <l>Love is a Common Error, and appears</l>
                  <l>With too much vigour in our youthful years.</l>
                  <l>Love is a thing that's ſtrong, but yet more ſtrong</l>
                  <l>Is violence of love, where laſting long.</l>
                  <l>And when he was preparing to remove,</l>
                  <l>(For he was us'd t'acquaint me with his love)</l>
                  <l>With ſad aſpect, and lamentable grones,</l>
                  <l>In theſe complaints he thus his love bemones:</l>
                  <l>O Virgin, will not briniſh tears be ſhed</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:115715:39"/>From thy fair eyes, when thou ſhalt hear I'm fled?</l>
                  <l>When thou ſhalt hear, that thou ſo ſoon bereft</l>
                  <l>Of me ſo dear a friend, alone are loft?</l>
                  <l>Wilt any ſighes for my departure ſpend?</l>
                  <l>Or wilt thou, cruel, me forget thy friend?</l>
                  <l>What, can thy flaming breaſt ſo quickly freeze,</l>
                  <l>That flaming breaſt of thine, which by degrees</l>
                  <l>Inflam'd by love, ſo many times have fill'd</l>
                  <l>So many's eyes with tears for thee diſtill'd?</l>
                  <l>Wilt not thou frequent ſighes and groans exhale</l>
                  <l>From thy ſad breaſt, and wilt thou not look pale?</l>
                  <l>I ſee the Maidens eyes, her tears I ſee,</l>
                  <l>I ſee the ſorrows of her heart for me.</l>
                  <l>Alas, alas! what art can I invent</l>
                  <l>To palliate ſo great a diſcontent?</l>
                  <l>A double grief mine heart hath over-laid,</l>
                  <l>One for my ſelf, another for the Maid:</l>
                  <l>But I may weep, ſhe not: yet fire, that lies</l>
                  <l>Moſt hid, more hotly burns, more fiercely fries.</l>
                  <l>Ye Gods preſerve her ſafe for me, for mine;</l>
                  <l>That when mine exile paſt, I ſhall confine</l>
                  <l>My ſelf at home, our (yet ſucceſsleſs) love</l>
                  <l>May once at leaſt at laſt ſucceſsful prove,</l>
                  <l>Before old age too much come creeping on,</l>
                  <l>Before the vigour of our youth be gone.</l>
                  <l>Thus ſaying he went on; yet his deſire</l>
                  <l>Was to return, ſuch is the force, the fire</l>
                  <l>Of Love in youth: But now the Dice are thrown,</l>
                  <l>And his reſolv'd of flight to moſt was known.</l>
                  <l>Tir'd out with grief and travel down he ſate</l>
                  <l>Under a frondent Poplar, conſecrate</l>
                  <l>To famous <hi>Hercules;</hi> and ſitting there,</l>
                  <l>Behold a comely Virgin did appear,</l>
                  <l>Crown'd with a Maiden Coronet; her face</l>
                  <l>Hands, eyes, and habit Nymph-like, full of grace:</l>
                  <l>And to lamenting <hi>Pollux</hi> thus ſhe ſpake,</l>
                  <l>Whither (dear youth) do'ſt travel? O betake</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:115715:39"/>Thy ſelf to quick return; Return, I ſay.</l>
                  <l>Thou knew'ſt not, (ah) thou know'ſt not how the way</l>
                  <l>Deceives, or whither t'will thy ſteps miſlead:</l>
                  <l>Yet (ô) thou dar'ſt to wander, dar'ſt to tread</l>
                  <l>In pathes unknown, ſuppoſing no deceit,</l>
                  <l>No dangers in theſe verdant fields await,</l>
                  <l>Thou think'ſt all ſafe; think'ſt (like a fooliſh youth)</l>
                  <l>What pleaſes profits, falſhood tak'ſt for truth.</l>
                  <l>The ſtinging Snake collected in a round,</l>
                  <l>Lies lurking in the graſs upon the ground.</l>
                  <l>Unwary perſons ſooneſt are beguil'd.</l>
                  <l>When in the flaming fire the little Childe</l>
                  <l>His harmleſs finger thruſts, he thinks no harm</l>
                  <l>Is in the fire, he thinks it will but warm,</l>
                  <l>Until he fe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l it burn, and then by ſenſe,</l>
                  <l>He knows and fears the flaming violence.</l>
                  <l>This way with pleaſing entrance doth beguile</l>
                  <l>The paſſengers, and with delightful ſmile</l>
                  <l>Shews ſeeming joyes: but entred in, when they</l>
                  <l>Think there's no danger in that pleaſing way,</l>
                  <l>A thouſand dangers, and a thouſand ſnares</l>
                  <l>Surpriſe them in their paſſage unawares.</l>
                  <l>This path, aſſoon as yonder hill above</l>
                  <l>Th'art over paſs'd, points out a ſhady grove,</l>
                  <l>Where herds of wilde and cruel creatures have</l>
                  <l>Each one his darkſome Den, his diſmall Cave;</l>
                  <l>This path leads thither: places for their ſcite</l>
                  <l>Moſt horrid, darker then the darkeſt night.</l>
                  <l>Who ſo deceiv'd goes thither, is forbid</l>
                  <l>Thence to return, but is in darkneſs hid.</l>
                  <l>And firſt his eyes are hoodwink'd with a rag</l>
                  <l>Or fillet black as pitch; then him they drag</l>
                  <l>Through all the woods, through ſtormy brakes, and then</l>
                  <l>He's chang'd into a Monſter from a Man.</l>
                  <l>When he begins to ſpeak, he roars or lowes,</l>
                  <l>When to lift up himſelf, he thinks he bowes,</l>
                  <l>And downward goes four-footed on the ground.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:115715:40"/>Unable to behold the ſtarry round.</l>
                  <l>The lower part of this black Valley ſhows</l>
                  <l>A Lake, which Sea-like with black water flows:</l>
                  <l>Above which over-hangs a mighty Mount,</l>
                  <l>Where pitch-like waters run from cold black Fount.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe wretches hither drawn, are hurl'd from hence</l>
                  <l>Precipitate with horrid violence</l>
                  <l>Into the <hi>Stygian</hi> Lake, and deep Abyſs;</l>
                  <l>Where in devouring Whirl-pools they by <hi>Dis</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ingulph'd, immerg'd, are huri'd from the light</l>
                  <l>T'infernal <hi>Styx,</hi> and Hells eternal night.</l>
                  <l>Alas, how many ſhepherds wit their flocks</l>
                  <l>Have been inſnar'd and periſh'd on theſe rocks?</l>
                  <l>I careful ſtill unwearied here do ſtay</l>
                  <l>T'aſſiſt, and to direct a better way.</l>
                  <l>Delay not then, nor vainly ſpend thy breath,</l>
                  <l>But O betimes of near approaching death</l>
                  <l>The flatt'ring Courts abandon: Fly from hence,</l>
                  <l>Seek ſafer Coaſts of better conſequence,</l>
                  <l>Upon the private ſhore that lies oppos'd</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Cyprus,</hi> whence Mount <hi>Carmel</hi> is diſclos'd.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Carmel</hi> that famous Mount, whoſe tow'ring head</l>
                  <l>VVith ſtately Cedars is invironed.</l>
                  <l>Here th'ancient Fathers (whom none parallels)</l>
                  <l>Had at the firſt their firſt-retired Cells:</l>
                  <l>Here were their houſes made of frondent boughs</l>
                  <l>VVithin the thicked woods where <hi>Ilex</hi> grows.</l>
                  <l>And from this Mountain to your leſſer hills,</l>
                  <l>Religion was deduc'd; as brooks and rills</l>
                  <l>Flow from an endleſs unexhauſted Fount:</l>
                  <l>And you from this Original may count</l>
                  <l>A numerous, almoſt in num'rous breed,</l>
                  <l>VVhich from this one Progenitor proceed.</l>
                  <l>In theſe ſweet woods, where in abundance grows</l>
                  <l>The lofty Firre-tree, where with unctious boughs,</l>
                  <l>The fat and oily Terebinth doth ſhine</l>
                  <l>VVith ſweating Roſin, Pitch and Turpentine.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:115715:40"/>VVhen thou ſhalt happily thy life conclude,</l>
                  <l>Thine age ſhall in a moment be renew'd</l>
                  <l>VVith change of years: Then I thee thence will bring</l>
                  <l>To better places, ever flouriſhing:</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhalt Immortal be, ſhalt from theſe clods</l>
                  <l>Of earth, have fellowſhip among the Gods.</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhalt have reſidence above the bright</l>
                  <l>Refulgent ſtars, among the Nymphs in white;</l>
                  <l>Among the Nymphs of Trees, the Nymphs of Hills;</l>
                  <l>The Nymphs of Flow'rs, whence ſweet perfume diſtils;</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe heads are crown'd with odorif'rous ſlowers,</l>
                  <l>VVith odorif'rous herbs; where thou the Powers</l>
                  <l>That are above ſhalt ſee; where thou ſhalt know</l>
                  <l>VVhat heavens are above thee, what below.</l>
                  <l>This ſaid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Virgin vaniſh'd out of ſight.</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Pollux</hi> ſwore his minde was changed quite,</l>
                  <l>And that he ſuddenly was diſingag'd</l>
                  <l>From that (now conquer'd) Love wherewith he rag'd.</l>
                  <l>As flaming fire if't chance to burn the fields</l>
                  <l>Is quickly quench'd, and to the water yields,</l>
                  <l>VVhen ſwell'd with floods th'unruly River <hi>Po</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>His banks doth over-run, or overflow:</l>
                  <l>So cruel love expires, which oft in vain</l>
                  <l>His Quiver empts on thoſe, that with diſdain</l>
                  <l>Reſiſt Loves firſt beginnings, and do prove</l>
                  <l>But timorous, or but luke-warm in love.</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Pollux,</hi> thus diſcharg'd of <hi>Cupids</hi> fire,</l>
                  <l>Into the ſilent Cloiſter did retire.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Some men there are on whom the Gods do ſmile,</l>
                  <l>Yea though the men unwilling are the while:</l>
                  <l>And ſome there are whom th'angry Gods aſſault,</l>
                  <l>Although without a cauſe, without a fault.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gal.</speaker>
                  <l>VVhat power over Cattel we poſſeſs,</l>
                  <l>Th'Immortal Gods have over us no leſs.</l>
                  <l>This is enough for Countrey men to know;</l>
                  <l>Let Cities higher ſoar, and wiſer grow.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Janus</hi> the Prieſt ſo taught, when as he came</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:115715:41"/>Out of the City, and affirm'd the ſame</l>
                  <l>VVas on Record in a volum'nous Book,</l>
                  <l>VVhere it he read, whence he that doctrine took:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>The Sun is ſetting, and doth ſcarely gild</l>
                  <l>The top of <hi>Baldus:</hi> Come, let's leave the field;</l>
                  <l>'Tis time to leave it with the ſetting Sun.</l>
                  <l>Come <hi>Galbula,</hi> think not thy ſelf undone</l>
                  <l>To carry Bag and Bottle home at night;</l>
                  <l>The Bag and Bottle empti'd are but light,</l>
                  <l>To carry both at night the labour's ſmall,</l>
                  <l>Th'are pond'rous in the morning, but withall</l>
                  <l>Th'are profitable burdens. Prethee come,</l>
                  <l>My work ſhall be to drive the Cattel home.</l>
               </sp>
               <trailer>The End of the ſeventh Eclogue.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="eclogue">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:115715:41"/>
               <head>ECLOGUE VIII. <hi>Treating of the Religion of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try men,</hi> Intituled RELIGION</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <l>The Mountains <hi>Candidus,</hi> the dales</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alphus</hi> commmends: then <hi>Candidus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Virgins praiſe and Feſtivalls</l>
                  <l>That came to <hi>Pollux</hi> doth diſcuſſe.</l>
               </argument>
               <stage>The ſpeakers <hi>Candidus</hi> and <hi>Alphus:</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ca.</speaker>
                  <l>THe torrid Earth (O <hi>Alphus</hi>) now the Sun</l>
                  <l>Shines in the Summers ſolſtice looketh dun</l>
                  <l>Gaping for thirſt: and now the the ſcorching blaze</l>
                  <l>VVarns us to drive our Cattle hence to graze</l>
                  <l>Upon the mountains, where leſſe heat doth fry,</l>
                  <l>VVhere moyſt'ning dews upon the graſſe do lie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Thoſe ay'ry Mountains, and high tops of hills</l>
                  <l>I ſee far off; but what from thence diſtills,</l>
                  <l>Or what the mountains are (to ſpeak the truth)</l>
                  <l>I know not; For I alwaies from my youth</l>
                  <l>Have dwelt in vales; But tell, what fruit abounds,</l>
                  <l>Or what's produc'd upon thoſe hilly grounds?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <l>O rude, and unconceited witleſſe head;</l>
                  <l>What, waſt thou born, and haſt been ever bred</l>
                  <l>Near brooks like more-hens, or in ſlimy vales,</l>
                  <l>VVhence <hi>Phoebus</hi> ſuch offenſive Fumes, exhales</l>
                  <l>VVhere in the Bogs among the ſtinking weeds,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:115715:42"/>Among the Willows and green paper-reeds</l>
                  <l>That grow within the banks of foggy Fens,</l>
                  <l>Frogs, gnats, flies, worms have lurking holes and dens?</l>
                  <l>And dar'ſt thou then deride or vilipend,</l>
                  <l>The Mountains, from whoſe flowing founts deſcend</l>
                  <l>Such famous rivers? from whoſe Marble Mynes</l>
                  <l>Such many pieces for the Temples ſhrines</l>
                  <l>Are hew'd and poliſh'd? whoſe rich veins infold</l>
                  <l>Rare Mettals, whence is digg'd refulgent gold?</l>
                  <l>What grounds but mountainous bear fitting trees</l>
                  <l>For ſhipping? what bear Phyſick herbs but theſe?</l>
                  <l>Upon the top of <hi>Baldus</hi> heretofore</l>
                  <l>Oft-times I gath'red have black <hi>Hellebore.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>No Med'cine is more Phyſical, more fit</l>
                  <l>For Goats then this; <hi>Aegon</hi> commended it:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aegon</hi> the <hi>Valſaſine,</hi> when in the Spring</l>
                  <l>He gelt his Lambs and Swine, preſcrib'd this thing;</l>
                  <l>He then preſcrib'd it, and thus ſaid, Apply</l>
                  <l>This for a ſole and certain remedy.</l>
                  <l>Come, tell me where more Cheſtnuts are, or where</l>
                  <l>Is greater ſtore of Acorns then are there?</l>
                  <l>Upon high Mountains I my ſelf have ſeen</l>
                  <l>Clear Springs of waters, Paſtures freſh and green;</l>
                  <l>I there have Paſties ear, and from the pot</l>
                  <l>Have fill'd my ſelf with pottage fat and hot.</l>
                  <l>ſtrong people there inhabit, there the youth</l>
                  <l>Is vigorous, and of gygantick growth:</l>
                  <l>Their feet are large, like brawn their ſhoulders hard;</l>
                  <l>Their ſtiff nerv'd arms ſtrong ſinews ſtrongly guard;</l>
                  <l>Hairy their skins, hands rough, for ſervice able;</l>
                  <l>To carry burdens indefatigable.</l>
                  <l>They from thoſe Valleys to theſe Mountains high,</l>
                  <l>Reſort, and to the Naval works apply.</l>
                  <l>No kinde of men will fit the Town ſo well,</l>
                  <l>Whether you Cattel geld, or Timber fell;</l>
                  <l>Whether you cleanſe the Stables, or the draught,</l>
                  <l>Or kitchins, or ſtopp'd gutters that are fraught</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="75" facs="tcp:115715:42"/>With ſordid filth, or whether to deſcend</l>
                  <l>With longeſt ladders to the loweſt end</l>
                  <l>Of deepeſt wells to cleanſe them; theſe herein</l>
                  <l>Are expert, and for ſtrength the wager win.</l>
                  <l>But what need many words? themſelves they fit</l>
                  <l>For any labour, and accomplish it.</l>
                  <l>In kitchins ſome are Cooks, ſome make the fire,</l>
                  <l>Some turn the ſpit, ſome climb a little higher,</l>
                  <l>And ſweep the Chimnies; others carry forth</l>
                  <l>Beeves bellies to the rivers: but their worth</l>
                  <l>Excels in this, moſt skill'd they be to keep</l>
                  <l>Foul places clean, foul houſes clean to ſweep.</l>
                  <l>And, which I more admire, they run, they come</l>
                  <l>Under their burdens as not burdenſome.</l>
                  <l>This people in poor Cottages are born,</l>
                  <l>They live on ſteep hills ſides among the thorn;</l>
                  <l>And with the Goats inhabit as their gueſts,</l>
                  <l>In horrid Dens of wilde, of cruel beaſts.</l>
                  <l>Adde here, that from the tops of Mountains high</l>
                  <l>'Tis a ſhort paſſage to the ſtarry sky:</l>
                  <l>Some Mountains with their lofty Creſts aſpire</l>
                  <l>Unto the Clouds, ſome other mounting higher</l>
                  <l>Tranſcend the Clouds, and with their proud aſcent</l>
                  <l>They touch, I think, the ſpangled Firmament.</l>
                  <l>There is a place (they ſay) that Eaſtward lies.</l>
                  <l>Where from the ſeas the morning Sun doth riſe,</l>
                  <l>Which (if I have ic not forgot too ſon)</l>
                  <l>With its aſpiring top doth touch the Moon;</l>
                  <l>And that long ſince a man there liv'd and dwell'd,</l>
                  <l>But for his gluttony was thence expell'd,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe that he devour d all th'Apples there,</l>
                  <l>And none reſerv'd for mighty <hi>Jupiter.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hence the divine and holy Fathers choſe</l>
                  <l>Retired houſes, places or repoſe</l>
                  <l>Among the Mountains: This do well atteſt</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Carthuſia, Carmel, Gargan;</hi> with the reſt</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Athos, Laverne, Laureta, Sina'</hi> Mount,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:115715:43"/>High topp'd <hi>Soractis</hi> ſhady vale and Fount,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Mountains famous by the fact and fate</l>
                  <l>Of old <hi>Nurſinus,</hi> and that hill of ſtate</l>
                  <l>Towred <hi>Camaldula,</hi> whoſe ſacred head</l>
                  <l>VVith lofty Fir-trees is invironed.</l>
                  <l>The reſt I paſſe: for 'tis not mine intent</l>
                  <l>To ſpeak of all in this ſhort argument:</l>
                  <l>Celeſtial Creatures towring Mountains haunt;</l>
                  <l>Whereas the Duck, the Gooſe, the Cormorant,</l>
                  <l>The Snipe, the Bittern, Kites and mooriſh hens</l>
                  <l>Are ever padling in the foggy Fens.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Among theſe praiſes of ſo great renown</l>
                  <l>With which thou doſt the craggy Mountains Crown,</l>
                  <l>Why ſpeak'ſt thou not of corn, or of the vine?</l>
                  <l>Yet theſe two noble creatures <hi>Corne</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Are the two chiefeſt Pillars, whoſe ſupply</l>
                  <l>Supports Mans Life in his Mortality.</l>
                  <l>The Mountaineers as ſoon as corn is ſhorn</l>
                  <l>Deſcend their hills into our vales for Corn:</l>
                  <l>Men of a rigid and ſevere aſpect,</l>
                  <l>Of ſmoaky colour, ruſtick dialect,</l>
                  <l>Leane, hairy, ragged, thirſty, full of wants;</l>
                  <l>The places natur's known by the Inhabitants.</l>
                  <l>But now thou ſpeak'ſt of religious halls</l>
                  <l>Upon the Mountains, it to mind recalls</l>
                  <l>The ſtrange reports we did of <hi>Pollux</hi> hear:</l>
                  <l>What Nymph, or O what Goddeſſe did appear</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Pollux,</hi> tell (O <hi>Candid</hi>) if thou know</l>
                  <l>From our diſcourſe of hills and vales doth grow</l>
                  <l>No profit: but the benefit is great</l>
                  <l>When of Religion our diſcourſe doth treat.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy <hi>Galbula,</hi> that wont with thee to keep</l>
                  <l>To drive to graſſe the Cattle and the ſheep,</l>
                  <l>Could ſatisfie thy wiſh, thee could acquaint</l>
                  <l>With th' apparition of that Nymph-like Saint</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>He many things of <hi>Pollux</hi> did unfold,</l>
                  <l>But of that Saint-like Nymph he nothing told:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="77" facs="tcp:115715:43"/>Nor I (as I remember) did inquire:</l>
                  <l>But talking of Religion now doth fire</l>
                  <l>My ſoul, doth to my mind that Nymph recal,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe praiſe I count the greateſt praiſe of all.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ca.</speaker>
                  <l>She was no Goddeſs of the Mounts or trees,</l>
                  <l>Nor of the Muſes: ſhe was none of theſe:</l>
                  <l>But ſhe diſmounted the ſupern<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l skies,</l>
                  <l>Queen Regent of Coeleſtial deities:</l>
                  <l>She mother of the mighty Thunderer,</l>
                  <l>Deſcended Heaven, that ſhe might confer</l>
                  <l>Peace to the gaſping youth; at her command</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tethys</hi> and <hi>Ceres</hi> as attendants ſtand,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Aeolus</hi> himſelf, that ſtrongly binds</l>
                  <l>In darkſome Caves the ranging raging winds.</l>
                  <l>Her, God above the ſtars, above the Sun,</l>
                  <l>Above the glitt'ring Conſtellation</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Caſſiopey</hi> hath lift, hath bound her Front</l>
                  <l>With Oriental ſtars incircl'd on't:</l>
                  <l>And that ſhe might eternally be grac'd</l>
                  <l>The ſilver Moon under her feet he plac'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>O <hi>Candidus,</hi> thou ſpeakſt of wonders rare,</l>
                  <l>Unheard, unknown of Shepheards; but declare</l>
                  <l>What's <hi>Tethys,</hi> what's refulgent <hi>Caſſiopey?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who's <hi>Aeolus</hi> whom all the winds obey,</l>
                  <l>That bridles up the winds in concave cells?</l>
                  <l>What are thoſe horſes of the Sun? come tell's,</l>
                  <l>Great matters and unknown thou doſt unfold.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ca.</speaker>
                  <l>Some part of them are ſtars, ſome name of old.</l>
                  <l>All which when <hi>Pollux</hi> had me ſhew'd and taught,</l>
                  <l>Within a ſacred Temple he me brought,</l>
                  <l>Where all theſe things were painted on a wall:</l>
                  <l>This wall (quoth he) thee will inform of all.</l>
                  <l>The wall was painted, gilded curiouſly</l>
                  <l>With many Pictures, much Imagery;</l>
                  <l>I do not all remember, dull and weak</l>
                  <l>My memory's become: though I now ſpeak</l>
                  <l>I ſcarce remember; though I often fit</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:115715:44"/>My minde to ponder, and reponder it.</l>
                  <l>Oft to conſider, and remember well,</l>
                  <l>More ſtrong then Phyſick is, or Magick ſpell.</l>
                  <l>When with dark Clouds the skies are mask'd in black,</l>
                  <l>This Nymph can clear the Clouds, or chace them back.</l>
                  <l>She the dry'd fruits, half dead for want of rain,</l>
                  <l>Can with refreſhing ſhowers revive again,</l>
                  <l>She from the parcht-up paſtures when ſhe will</l>
                  <l>Can raiſe freſh founts, can rain on them diſtil,</l>
                  <l>And thoſe rais'd founts, or rain diſtill'd ſhe can,</l>
                  <l>When ere ſhe pleaſe, reſtrain from fields, from man.</l>
                  <l>Of barren grounds that bare no graſs ere-while,</l>
                  <l>She when ſhe will can make a fertile ſoil.</l>
                  <l>When that cold Planet, that malignant ſtar</l>
                  <l>Of luckleſs <hi>Saturn</hi> culminates ſo far</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Scorpius,</hi> and in that diſmal ſigne</l>
                  <l>Hath entertainment with his pallid ſhine,</l>
                  <l>No ſtorms of hail the Corn ſhall ſpoil, no fire</l>
                  <l>Shall houſes burn; though, when thoſe ſtars conſpire</l>
                  <l>Th'incenſed heavens (as they ſay) ſuch ſcars</l>
                  <l>Dejaculate on th'earth from th'angry ſtars.</l>
                  <l>All this that Virgin-Nymph (her Sexes Gem)</l>
                  <l>Can keep from us, and us preſerve from them</l>
                  <l>If ſhe but favour us, our harveſt Crops</l>
                  <l>Shall fill our barns and garners to the tops.</l>
                  <l>And all the pregnant Cattel of our flock</l>
                  <l>Shall bring forth Twins, and multiply the ſtock.</l>
                  <l>If Cattel thrive not, or their fleeces ſhed,</l>
                  <l>She, ſolely with the nodding of her head</l>
                  <l>Can Milk, Fleece, Lambs reſtore; can with her art</l>
                  <l>The Cattel cure, and each diſeaſe divert.</l>
                  <l>There's how no need to follow ruſtick <hi>Pan,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or any rural Gods, which fooliſh man</l>
                  <l>Did (as it is reported) heretofore</l>
                  <l>With much devotion, but in vain, adore.</l>
                  <l>In Circle of the Nymphs rich Altar there,</l>
                  <l>Wax Pictures pendant were, which ſhapes do bear</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:115715:44"/>Of Goats, Waynes, Oxen, Sheep; I did denote</l>
                  <l>And view them well; I there ſaw <hi>Janus</hi> Goat</l>
                  <l>Modell'd in wax; and I remember, I</l>
                  <l>Read on a painted Tablet (hanging by)</l>
                  <l>Inſcribed thus in Verſe, <hi>Here view the vote</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That</hi> Janus <hi>paid for his preſerved Goat.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And while I this read over by degrees,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pollux</hi> devoutly falling on his knees</l>
                  <l>Upon the Marble pavement ſtraight before</l>
                  <l>That Altar; he the Nymph did thus implore,</l>
                  <l>O Goddeſs, Governeſs of Towns and Franks,</l>
                  <l>We pray thee let not <hi>Po</hi> ſwell ore his banks:</l>
                  <l>Let not, O let not the Nocturnal Hag</l>
                  <l>Our tender Infants through black darkneſs drag:</l>
                  <l>Let not <hi>Hobgoblins,</hi> nor the walking Sprite</l>
                  <l>Frequent our ſtreets by day, nor houſe by night.</l>
                  <l>O Goddeſs, favour Husbandmen, deſtroy</l>
                  <l>The Moles, whoſe heap'd-up hills the fields annoy:</l>
                  <l>Remember (Nymph) when winter ſharply blows</l>
                  <l>To cover all the Corn with dews, with ſnows.</l>
                  <l>O let no Vermin when the Corn is ſhorn,</l>
                  <l>The next enſuing year devour the Corn.</l>
                  <l>The Northern winds from growing Figs reſtrain;</l>
                  <l>From Cranes the Beans, from Geeſe defend the grain:</l>
                  <l>From Serpents Oxen, from the ſubtle Fox,</l>
                  <l>The ſubt'ler thief, preſerve our herds, our flocks;</l>
                  <l>The fruits from Canker, Vines from hail and ſtorms;</l>
                  <l>From Wolves the Cattel keep, from herbs the worms:</l>
                  <l>Our Dogs from madneſs, from fierce flames of fire,</l>
                  <l>From Lightning keep our Villages intire.</l>
                  <l>Our Bacon from the Mice and ſouldiers keep;</l>
                  <l>From worms, and from the things that ſlowly creep,</l>
                  <l>That ſlowly creep (alas my ſtupid minde</l>
                  <l>Hath loſt the reſt, forgets what's left behinde.</l>
                  <l>But verſe hath often to my memory)</l>
                  <l>Reduc'd forgotten things: Ile turn and try</l>
                  <l>Thoſe meaſur'd numbers, I by them may chance</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="80" facs="tcp:115715:45"/>Oblivion, chace, remembrance readvance)</l>
                  <l>Our Bacon from the Mice and ſouldiers keep,</l>
                  <l>From worms, and from the ſnayles that ſlowly creep</l>
                  <l>Our gardens guard; (ſe'ſt <hi>Alphus,</hi> ſe'ſt thou not</l>
                  <l>The force of verſe; I've got what I forgot,</l>
                  <l>And now remember all the reſt in fine)</l>
                  <l>From roaring thunder keep our Buts of wine:</l>
                  <l>From cold our Ewes with yong when froſt do freeze,</l>
                  <l>Our Calves and Cattle reſcue from the Breeze;</l>
                  <l>Our hogs from ſwelling Squinzies in their throats;</l>
                  <l>From loſſe of labour in their rurall Cotes</l>
                  <l>Aſſiſt O Goddeſſe our inurbane ſwains;</l>
                  <l>O from the drone among Bees that drains</l>
                  <l>Their honeycombes defend the Bees; Defend</l>
                  <l>Our Peaſe from thieviſh birds; thine help extend</l>
                  <l>To keep the Fleeces of our ſheep from rhorne,</l>
                  <l>From Burrs to keep our wooll unshorn or ſhorn.</l>
                  <l>O Goddeſſe, O of men the governeſſe,</l>
                  <l>Poets Protectreſſe, eaſer or diſtreſſe,</l>
                  <l>Griefes med'cine, Patroneſſe of Flocks, of Cotes</l>
                  <l>I pray thee grant our Prayers, grant our votes.</l>
                  <l>Thus <hi>Pollux</hi> praid; I leaning to the poſt</l>
                  <l>Caſting my ſtretch'd out legge my staffe acroſt,</l>
                  <l>Mark'd well his words; and with great care uplaid</l>
                  <l>In my remembrance all the words he ſaid.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>O <hi>Candidus,</hi> think'ſt not that ſome reward</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pollux</hi> ſhould have for his ſo great regard,</l>
                  <l>For's pious prayers, for's religious love?</l>
                  <l>Our goodneſs doubtleſs doth goods improve,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <l>Why ſhould we not give him ſomthing for it?</l>
                  <l>That we ſhould cratefull be 'tis very fit.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Ruſtick; Thou cratefull doſt for gratefull call.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ca.</speaker>
                  <l>Cratefull between and gratefull th' ods is ſmall.</l>
                  <l>We muſt give ſomething; yet leſt twice we give,</l>
                  <l>Let Eaſter paſſe, what time the Prieſts do ſhrive</l>
                  <l>Offendors, and abſolve them from their crimes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſhall we give (a Calfe's too much theſe times)</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="81" facs="tcp:115715:45"/>A Lambe, or Hare? Our pieties intent</l>
                  <l>Is laudable, if but a gooſe be ſent.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <l>The ſeaſon ſhewes the gift: when winters ſnow</l>
                  <l>Stops hares from running, then an Hare beſtow.</l>
                  <l>A gooſe with <hi>Autumn</hi> and <hi>November</hi> ſhapes:</l>
                  <l>The Summer gifts are Filberts, Apples, Grapes.</l>
                  <l>A ſucking Kid or Lamb are for the ſpring:</l>
                  <l>Then if thou doſt perceive a whinderling</l>
                  <l>Among the late fall'n Lambs, that doth not thrive,</l>
                  <l>That will not well be ſold nor kept alive,</l>
                  <l>We'l give that gift; That gift when e're it falls</l>
                  <l>Will well enough befit their Festivalls.</l>
                  <l>And after dinner when my leave I took,</l>
                  <l>He gave me verſes, copi'd from a Book</l>
                  <l>Of all the Virgins ſolemn Faſts and Feaſts;</l>
                  <l>Thus ſaying, when Corroding care moleſts</l>
                  <l>Thy mind, theſe verſes ſing: and thou ſhalt find</l>
                  <l>Theſe verſes med'cines for thy care-ſick mind.</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Titan</hi> from the Lion doth decline,</l>
                  <l>And headlong enters into <hi>Virgo's</hi> ſigne,</l>
                  <l>Let age and youth rejoice; the virgin's plum'd</l>
                  <l>With Angels wings, is to the Gods aſſum'd.</l>
                  <l>Thrice eight daies after ſhe forſook this Earth,</l>
                  <l>Another feaſt is ſolemniz'd, the birth</l>
                  <l>Of that unſpotted Virgin: then with fires</l>
                  <l>Her Altars flame: the Prieſt adores, admires,</l>
                  <l>Offers new ſacrifices: whiles the Sun</l>
                  <l>Returns to <hi>Libra,</hi> where he ſwift doth run</l>
                  <l>Preparing t' aequiballance daies and nights,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Picenum</hi> then exults with new delights:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Epirus</hi> ſhips tranſport (with ſwelling pride)</l>
                  <l>Their Epirots on th' <hi>Adriatick</hi> Tide.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Thuſcans, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbrians, Venetians</hi> then,</l>
                  <l>With thoſe of <hi>Sicily</hi> bring wares and men;</l>
                  <l>All which in multitudes with gifts from home</l>
                  <l>Unto the Temple of <hi>Lauretta</hi> come;</l>
                  <l>Where having paid their vows, they joyfull riſe</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="82" facs="tcp:115715:46"/>And on the lofty Mountain Merchandize,</l>
                  <l>And when the Sun his longer courſe doth vary,</l>
                  <l>And in a ſhorter enters Sagittary:</l>
                  <l>When the tempeſtuous Northern wind beſtrews</l>
                  <l>The frigid fields with hoary Froſts and dews,</l>
                  <l>The Veſtalls to their private Cells confin'd,</l>
                  <l>Forgetting their own Parents, onely mind</l>
                  <l>The Virgin Saint, and with their whole intent</l>
                  <l>Her ſacred preſentation repreſent.</l>
                  <l>And when the Sun from half-horſe-Chirons bow</l>
                  <l>Flies languiſhing, and enters (as below)</l>
                  <l>The winters ſigne of Icy <hi>Capricorne,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Let men and women then themſelves adorn</l>
                  <l>In rich apparel, let them then begin</l>
                  <l>To celebrate with joy that day wherein</l>
                  <l>The Virgin was conceiv'd, that holy day</l>
                  <l>The ſacred Nymphs beginning did diſplay:</l>
                  <l>Who from her firſt beginning, from a child</l>
                  <l>With baſe Immundities was not defil'd.</l>
                  <l>When ſcorching <hi>Phoebus</hi> all inflam'd doth fly,</l>
                  <l>To cool his heat in humid <hi>Aquary,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Returning towards, and now near the ſpring</l>
                  <l>All ye that married are go ſpeedy, bring</l>
                  <l>To the Altars ſacred fire, and to the fire</l>
                  <l>Bring Frankincenſe; exalt your torches higher:</l>
                  <l>Be pompous and triumphant, for this day</l>
                  <l>The Virgin in the Temple did diſplay</l>
                  <l>Her Motherhead: strange things did then betide,</l>
                  <l>A Virgin mother there was purifi'd,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Phoebus</hi> enters <hi>Aries,</hi> the Flocks</l>
                  <l>Conductor, ſhining with his golden locks,</l>
                  <l>Beginning to diſcloſe the new-come year</l>
                  <l>With weſtern winds which blow more warm, more clear,</l>
                  <l>More hours adding to the day then night,</l>
                  <l>Let then the wing'd <hi>Paranymph</hi> inlight</l>
                  <l>The Virgins houſe, and thoſe ſtrange things he ſaid</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Annunciate</hi> unto the wondring Maid.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="83" facs="tcp:115715:46"/>This Feſtival the people drawes by flocks</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Arnus</hi> river, and the Thuſcan rocks</l>
                  <l>To ſolemnize it, at the Virgins ſhrine,</l>
                  <l>Within the Temples of the <hi>Florentine.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And then, but yet not long before that tide</l>
                  <l>The Virgin was eſpous'd, and made a Bride</l>
                  <l>This holy day the maiden Nymphs doth call</l>
                  <l>To celebrate this ſolemn Feſtival.</l>
                  <l>When the refulgent Sun is entred in</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Cancer,</hi> and the dog-ſtar doth begin</l>
                  <l>To breath diſeaſes, then ſweet incenſe burn</l>
                  <l>To celebrate that day, which did return</l>
                  <l>The Virgin-mother home, from viſiting</l>
                  <l>That other mother: then to the Altars bring</l>
                  <l>Firſt fruits of corn, and hang them round the Rood</l>
                  <l>In honour of the double Motherhood.</l>
                  <l>Theſe Verſes <hi>Pollux</hi> gave which he did write,</l>
                  <l>When in the fields he watch'd his Flock by night,</l>
                  <l>When in ſerener Nights he did ſurvay</l>
                  <l>The glittering ſtars, heavens armies in array.</l>
                  <l>He then more verſes gave; but now no more</l>
                  <l>We can repeat: the Sun below the ſhore</l>
                  <l>Declines; bright <hi>Heſperus</hi> begins t' appear</l>
                  <l>Suppreſſing <hi>Phoebus</hi> from our Hemiſphear.</l>
               </sp>
               <trailer>The End of the eighth Eclogue.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="eclogue">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:115715:47"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>ECLOGUE IX.</hi> Treating of the manner of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> written by <hi>Mantuan</hi> after his entring into Religious orders; <hi>Intituled FALCO.</hi>
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <l>When <hi>Faustulus</hi> had well ſurvai'd</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Romes</hi> frigid Paſtures, he begins</l>
                  <l>To tax the Pastors (unafray'd)</l>
                  <l>For their enormities and ſins</l>
               </argument>
               <stage>The ſpeakers <hi>Fauſtulus</hi> and <hi>Candidus.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>WHat chance, O <hi>Candidus,</hi> thee brought ſo far</l>
                  <l>From thine own Country to this place? here at</l>
                  <l>No brooks, no Paſtures, no refreſhing ſprings,</l>
                  <l>No ſheepcotes ſafe, no cooling ſhadowings:</l>
                  <l>And yet thoſe grounds are daily graz'd by ſheep.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <l>O <hi>Fauſtulus</hi> our <hi>Coridon</hi> did keep,</l>
                  <l>Great droves and herds of Cattle here, while ere</l>
                  <l>Much gaining by the Cattle he did rear;</l>
                  <l>And he perſwaded me that on theſe hills</l>
                  <l>Grew wholſom graſſe, that here were pleaſant rills,</l>
                  <l>But when I once perceiv'd theſe barren Mounts,</l>
                  <l>Theſe craggy Rocks, theſe water-wanting Founts,</l>
                  <l>That I did leave my Country, that I went</l>
                  <l>So long a journey, I did much repent.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Sith 'tis thy chance ſo ſafely with thy droves</l>
                  <l>To travell unto theſe Italian groves,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="85" facs="tcp:115715:47"/>Thou maiſt by right of former friendſhip come</l>
                  <l>Unto mine houſe, and make mine houſe thine home;</l>
                  <l>Here ſome few acres of poor ground have I,</l>
                  <l>Which ſcarcely will my livelyhood ſupply:</l>
                  <l>What e're it be, betwixt thy ſelf and me</l>
                  <l>Suppoſe it common; thou perhaps maiſt ſee</l>
                  <l>Some lucky fortune; fortune like the wind</l>
                  <l>Though variable, may to good be inclin'd.</l>
                  <l>Until the ſcorching heat doth overpaſſe,</l>
                  <l>And while our Cattle, lying on the graſſe</l>
                  <l>In the cool ſhadow, chew their Cud, come in</l>
                  <l>My Cottage, thatch'd with ſedge; on yonder pin</l>
                  <l>Hang up thy ſcrip, thy ſheepheards crook lay by,</l>
                  <l>Sit down a While; with drink refreſh thy dry,</l>
                  <l>Thy thirſty throat; drink's needful, come, aſſay</l>
                  <l>This liquor,'twill thy burning heat allay;</l>
                  <l>Here take thy cup; do not thy drink decline,</l>
                  <l>Our tongues wil be more fluent after wine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <l>What mad man in ſuch heat will drinking ſpare<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Wind cools the thirſt, and frees the mind from care,</l>
                  <l>Wine, Friendſhip, and the bodies ſtrength augments,</l>
                  <l>Contents the taſt, abandons diſcontents.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <l>This Country bears good grapes, if that the vines</l>
                  <l>Within this Country grow that made theſe wines.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fauſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Come, fill thy cup again, it is no waſt,</l>
                  <l>To drink one draught of wine is but to taſt,</l>
                  <l>The ſecond moiſts the mouth; the ſcorched throates,</l>
                  <l>The third refrigerates; the fourth denotes</l>
                  <l>Arms and Alarums to thirſt the fifth doth fight;</l>
                  <l>The ſixt doth conquer; and (as ſome do write</l>
                  <l>As old <hi>Oenophilus</hi> doth well relate)</l>
                  <l>The ſeventh over thirſt triumphs in ſtate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis ſafe to follow ſound advice; 'tis good</l>
                  <l>I imbrace grave Councellors (if underſtood)</l>
                  <l>My thirſt is quench'd; but there remains behind</l>
                  <l>My care-corroded heart, my penſive mind.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fauſt.</speaker>
                  <l>It's wine allayes<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thy thirſt, ſo 'twill in ſine</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:115715:48"/>Allay thy penſive mind; come, fill thy wine,</l>
                  <l>Come fill thy wine, and drink this med'cine cures</l>
                  <l>The grief of heart, againſt all cares enſures:</l>
                  <l>This med'cine <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf doth uſe as chief</l>
                  <l>Againſt corroding care, conſuming grief.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <l>Each work and labour hath its intervalls</l>
                  <l>Of reſt, and for repoſe and Reſpite calls:</l>
                  <l>Let reſt the flagon here a little while,</l>
                  <l>And cover it; leſt it the flies defile.</l>
                  <l>No rain by day, no dew by night's here ſeen,</l>
                  <l>Nor in dry Cottages can herbes grow green.</l>
                  <l>Fierce famine, daily labours, ſcorching air</l>
                  <l>With leaneſſe do the Flocks impeach, impair:</l>
                  <l>Their fainting ſpirits ſcarcely can ſuſtain</l>
                  <l>Their feeble bodies: their thin buttocks ſtrain</l>
                  <l>Their ſtretch'd out bones within their arid hides;</l>
                  <l>Their empty bellies clunge up to their ſides</l>
                  <l>Contract their hollow Bowells: ſee this Bam</l>
                  <l>More fearful now then is the fearfull'ſt Lamb,</l>
                  <l>More weak then is a ſheep, was wont of yore</l>
                  <l>With head and hornes the wolves to beat, to gore.</l>
                  <l>All which the luckleſſe Crow, with hapleſſe prate</l>
                  <l>Dvining, did to me prognoſticate.</l>
                  <l>But me my fervent votes too much did ſway:</l>
                  <l>I ſcarce was out of doors upon my way,</l>
                  <l>But that unlucky bird with ſad portent</l>
                  <l>Flew from my right, and to my left hand went,</l>
                  <l>And ſate a top on the ſiniſter ſide</l>
                  <l>Of my poor Cottage; where extending wide</l>
                  <l>Her craking throat, ſhe did-forbid thereby</l>
                  <l>My journey with apparant <hi>Augury.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ah hapleſſe cattle, which were wont t' abound</l>
                  <l>With Milk and young, when in your native ground</l>
                  <l>You graz'd and fed; now ſeeking graſſe in vain</l>
                  <l>You loſe more juice by going, then you gain</l>
                  <l>By feeding; here both we conſuming are,</l>
                  <l>You with bare paſture, I with bitter care.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:115715:48"/>O riches of our Country! O the Meades</l>
                  <l>Still flouriſhing! O graſſe that overſpreads</l>
                  <l>The Frondent fields! O paſtures paſt compute;</l>
                  <l>O Fertile ſoil, and never wanting fruit!</l>
                  <l>There cryſtall brooks and running Rivers glide,</l>
                  <l>Wat'ring fields, gardens, Towns on ev'ry ſide.</l>
                  <l>There are fat Cattle, Fertile fields are there;</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Sol</hi> in <hi>Cancers</hi> Tropick doth apear.</l>
                  <l>When ev'ry where the thraſhing floors reſound;</l>
                  <l>When <hi>July</hi> burns, our fields with green are crown'd;</l>
                  <l>The checquer'd hedges made of tender twigs,</l>
                  <l>Bear berries there and Apples, grapes and Figs:</l>
                  <l>There ſpring among the thornes ſweet ſmelling flowers;</l>
                  <l>O the delightful ſhades of woods and bowers!</l>
                  <l>O the ſoft whiſpers, gentle murmurs there,</l>
                  <l>Which (I remember) thou and I did hear</l>
                  <l>In the cool ſhadows of the Turtles grones,</l>
                  <l>The ſwallows chatt'ring, and the tuneful tones</l>
                  <l>Which muſick-making <hi>Philomel</hi> did ſing,</l>
                  <l>When firſt the ſhrubs with graſſe-hoppers did ring!</l>
                  <l>The gentle air by leaves of trees increaſt</l>
                  <l>Breath'd pleaſing murmurs from the bluſhing <hi>Eaſt.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>There the wild Cherry trees producing berries.</l>
                  <l>Spread out their branches laded all with Cherries;</l>
                  <l>I lying on the ground, ſaw where I lay</l>
                  <l>The skipping cattle to rejoice and play;</l>
                  <l>I ſaw the frisking Lambes leap here and there,</l>
                  <l>And butting with their horns to run Carrere.</l>
                  <l>When ſlept, I had upon the graſſy ground,</l>
                  <l>Sometimes with face erect my Pipe I'd ſound,</l>
                  <l>Or with my voice would ſing; ſomet-mes i'd pick</l>
                  <l>The ripened ſtrawberries which the<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e grew thick.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fauſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou then might'ſt happy live, then fortunate</l>
                  <l>Thou mighteſt be call'd; but that thy good estate</l>
                  <l>Decauſe thou then did'ſt underprize (For thou</l>
                  <l>Bidſt never of misfortunes taſt till now)</l>
                  <l>Thee therefore thy good fortune left; but when</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:115715:49"/>She comes again (if e're ſhe come agen)</l>
                  <l>As with their wiers Vines on all that's near</l>
                  <l>Catch hold, and cloſely to th' next elmes adhere:</l>
                  <l>So catch her faſt, nor looſe her caught: her face</l>
                  <l>She changeth oft, ſhe comes and goes apace,</l>
                  <l>She's never conſtant; like Nocturnal haggs</l>
                  <l>Who walk (they ſay) by night diſguiſ'd in raggs</l>
                  <l>Through diſmal ſhades; and as her face doth vary,</l>
                  <l>So doth her mind rejoice when things miſcarry.</l>
                  <l>What ſhe did give, ſhe takes; nor doth ſhe advance.</l>
                  <l>Her acts with judgement, but doth all by chance</l>
                  <l>She doth repel, repulſe, deſpite, deſpiſe</l>
                  <l>All thoſe that are too fearful, or too wiſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <l>As oft as on my memory recoyle</l>
                  <l>The delicacies of my Native ſoyle;</l>
                  <l>So many tortures in contented ſort</l>
                  <l>I cannot bear. But whither doth tranſport</l>
                  <l>Me my diſquiet mind. Now, 'drench'd with gall</l>
                  <l>Of ſad misfortunes, I to mind recall</l>
                  <l>My former happy times; which thoughts do vex</l>
                  <l>My penſive ſoul, and me do more perplex.</l>
                  <l>Now <hi>May</hi> comes in, and in my Country now</l>
                  <l>The lowly Brooms, the lofty vines do blow</l>
                  <l>Along the banks of <hi>Po,</hi> the paſtures ſides</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Mincius</hi> with ſilver'd water glides:</l>
                  <l>There now the Corn is ear'd; with bloſſoms red,</l>
                  <l>Pomegranate trees now there are all beſpread:</l>
                  <l>The frondent Alder there (this month of <hi>May</hi>)</l>
                  <l>Doth ſweet-white Flowers on each hedge diſplay.</l>
                  <l>But here as yet the Mountains are not ſeen</l>
                  <l>Beginning to bud forth with any green.</l>
                  <l>And if the ground ſo backward proves in ſpring,</l>
                  <l>What will cold winter and hot ſummer bring,</l>
                  <l>When hoary winter doth cold froſts repeat,</l>
                  <l>And Summers Solſtice burns with raging heat?</l>
                  <l>Yet here ſome heards of ſmooth-skin'd cattle are,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſoft unwrinkl'd necks the yoke ne'r bare,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="89" facs="tcp:115715:49"/>Whoſe lofty Front aſpires with double horn,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe wanton breaſts on dainty beds are born:</l>
                  <l>Unleſſe theſe Fodder eat that's good, that's choic'ſt</l>
                  <l>Their bodies cannot be ſo fat, ſo moiſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>This herd of Cattle that advance their Creſt</l>
                  <l>Higher then th'earth, and higher then the reſt</l>
                  <l>That have long jointed thighes, devour up all:</l>
                  <l>Firſt graſſe, then leaves of trees, anon the tall,</l>
                  <l>The topmoſt branches of the greeneſt groves;</l>
                  <l>But theſe poor Cattle, theſe infeebled droves</l>
                  <l>That onely graze the ground for their repaſt,</l>
                  <l>Are in theſe barren fields compell'd to faſt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ca.</speaker>
                  <l>But what need words? all creatures are the ſame,</l>
                  <l>For ſtill the greater do the leſſer tame.</l>
                  <l>Wolves feed on Lambs, Eagles on Pidgeons prey;</l>
                  <l>The Dolphins in the Seas courſe, chaſe away</l>
                  <l>The ſmaller fiſhes. How comes this about?</l>
                  <l>A moſt prodigious thing it is no doubt.</l>
                  <l>If thou theſe places at a diſtance ken</l>
                  <l>From ſome high Rock, thou wilt ſuppoſe them then</l>
                  <l>Fat paſtures, full of graſſe: but come more near,</l>
                  <l>More bare theſe places, and more baſe appear.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rome</hi> is the ſame to men as is an owl</l>
                  <l>To birds; ſhe ſitting as the Queen of fowl,</l>
                  <l>And proudly nodding on ſome wither'd ſtock</l>
                  <l>Calls multitudes of Birdes, which thither Flock</l>
                  <l>All ignorant of fraud; where in amaze</l>
                  <l>At her foul head, great eies and ears they gaze</l>
                  <l>They wonder at her hook'd beaks threatning top</l>
                  <l>And on the branches while they skip and hop</l>
                  <l>Now here, now there, the Nets intangle ſome,</l>
                  <l>The limetwigs others; all that thither come</l>
                  <l>Are overcome, are made the Fowlers prey,</l>
                  <l>And to be roſted, thence are born away.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ca.</speaker>
                  <l>O this is pretty; nor at any time</l>
                  <l>Could any thing be ſpoke more fit, more prime.</l>
                  <l>But O look yonder where a ſnake doth thruſt</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="90" facs="tcp:115715:50"/>Himſelf with crooked windings through the duſt,</l>
                  <l>And thirſty with his thruſt out tongue doth beat</l>
                  <l>The liquid aire, to cool his ſcorching heat.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>O <hi>Candidus,</hi> what I forewarn thee now</l>
                  <l>Remember well: when thou the go'ſt through,</l>
                  <l>Guard with thine hat thine eies, for there the brakes</l>
                  <l>Extend ſharp pointed thornes which bite like ſnakes,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe crooked Brambles cloaks and cloths do tear:</l>
                  <l>Lay not thy ſheephook down, nor yet forbear</l>
                  <l>To bear hard ſtones, and arm thy ſelf with thoſe,</l>
                  <l>Leſt on a ſuddain thee new foes oppoſe.</l>
                  <l>Cover thy feet with ſhoes: for there the brakes</l>
                  <l>Are full of horrid and invenom'd ſnakes;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe bitter bitings kill: and now more long,</l>
                  <l>More hot the daies, their poyſon is more ſtrong.</l>
                  <l>A thouſand wolves, as many Foxes dwell</l>
                  <l>In dens within theſe vales; and which to tell</l>
                  <l>Is ſtrange and fearful, I my ſelf have ſeen</l>
                  <l>(This climate is ſo violent and keen)</l>
                  <l>Ev'n men themſelves transform'd into the ſhapes</l>
                  <l>Of wolves, and wolfe like acting cruel rapes</l>
                  <l>Of their own Flocks; and O with too much blood</l>
                  <l>Of their own Cattle drench'd, as with a Flood.</l>
                  <l>The neighbourhood obſerve and laugh at thoſe,</l>
                  <l>But nor deteſt the ſin, nor it oppoſee.</l>
                  <l>And Monſters oft in wond'rous formes appear,</l>
                  <l>Which th'ill aſpected Earth produceth here.</l>
                  <l>And oftentimes the dogs ſo madly rage,</l>
                  <l>That they with cruelties, with bloody ſtrage</l>
                  <l>Outſtrip the Wolves themſelves; and they which wont</l>
                  <l>To guard the Flocks, and thence all vermine hunt,</l>
                  <l>Are vermine turn'd, and hoſtilely prepar'd</l>
                  <l>Devour thoſe ſheep which they themſelvs ſhould guard.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aegypt</hi> (as't is reported) heretofore</l>
                  <l>Some certain Beaſts did for their Gods adore:</l>
                  <l>Their Superſtition, yet is leſſe then ours:</l>
                  <l>Here, not ſome certain beaſts, but all have Towers,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:115715:50"/>Fanes, Altars; doubtleſſe a moſt hateful thing</l>
                  <l>To God and nature: who made man a King,</l>
                  <l>And ſubordain'd (as hiſtories record)</l>
                  <l>All earthly Creatures unto man their Lord.</l>
                  <l>And oft a ſickly Summer enters here,</l>
                  <l>Which doth produce a pestilentiall year:</l>
                  <l>Then in the field the fainting cattle lie,</l>
                  <l>Caſt down and dead: the Lambes do bleat and die</l>
                  <l>Under their mothers Udders; Oxen tire,</l>
                  <l>Suppreſt with heavy burdens, and expire.</l>
                  <l>Nor hath the ſickneſſe mean, nor cure the Peſt:</l>
                  <l>But this houſe doth that houſe infect, infeſt,</l>
                  <l>The next houſe from the next attracteth death:</l>
                  <l>And thus the plague gains daily ſtrength and breath.</l>
                  <l>This plague wild Beaſts doth yet but ſeldom kill,</l>
                  <l>But ſweeps away the better Cattle ſtill;</l>
                  <l>The wolves with ſharpned teeth and rav'nous throats</l>
                  <l>Keep Feſtivalls within our ſheepleſſe Cotes:</l>
                  <l>And with our loſſes are theſe beaſts inrich'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ca.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas, alas; what fury me bewitch'd?</l>
                  <l>What headlong madneſſe hither poor me drew?</l>
                  <l>Great madneſſe 'tis to credit, to purſue</l>
                  <l>Deceitful fame: when I but underſtood,</l>
                  <l>But heard of Roman hills, of <hi>Tybers</hi> flood,</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Romes</hi> fair buildings (by the mouth of Fame)</l>
                  <l>My mind was all inflam'd to ſee the ſame,</l>
                  <l>And there among ſo many things of praiſe</l>
                  <l>To ſpend the ſhort remainder of my daies,</l>
                  <l>I madly came with half my Flocks; my Tents,</l>
                  <l>My ſheepheards tools, mine houſhold implements,</l>
                  <l>My milk pailes, pans, pots, kettles, beechen vates,</l>
                  <l>Wherein the maid her Cheeſes circulates,</l>
                  <l>Over high hills I brought: and now my coſt,</l>
                  <l>And now my labour all at laſt is loſt.</l>
                  <l>O whither ſhall I turn? what ſhall I do?</l>
                  <l>The paſtures which I brought my cattle to;</l>
                  <l>The Fodder which I hop'd for, is deni'd:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="92" facs="tcp:115715:51"/>So many chances are on ev'ry ſide,</l>
                  <l>So many dangers; I muſt (in diſtreſſe)</l>
                  <l>Return into my Country, muſt confeſſe</l>
                  <l>Mine ill-advis'd attempt, and muſt retreat</l>
                  <l>Ore ſtony Mountains through laborious heat.</l>
                  <l>Ah hapleſſe ſheep; O ſhepheard, from afar</l>
                  <l>Miſguided hither by ſome luckleſſe ſtar!</l>
                  <l>Much better had it been t' have never known</l>
                  <l>This Country, but t' have ſtaid within thine own;</l>
                  <l>Securely there in ſome refreſhing Cave</l>
                  <l>T' have ſpent thy daies till age brought on thy grave,</l>
                  <l>And there to ſit, and there thy Flock to feed</l>
                  <l>With wholſome graſſe which our rich paſtures breed</l>
                  <l>Along the banks where ſilver <hi>Padus</hi> glides,</l>
                  <l>Or where fair <hi>Atheſis</hi> from <hi>Trent</hi> divides,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Verona's</hi> ſoil; Or in the fields more green,</l>
                  <l>More known, where chryſtal <hi>Mincius</hi> runs between,</l>
                  <l>Or where ſwift-running <hi>Abdua</hi> doth dance</l>
                  <l>On glaſſy waters to the Realm of <hi>France.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Thee thine, and me mine own credulity</l>
                  <l>Doth oft deceive; I've ſeen men mounted high</l>
                  <l>Upon the top of Fortune, when their pride</l>
                  <l>Would higher clime to tumble down beſide</l>
                  <l>Their expectation, and could never riſe.</l>
                  <l>Experience makes men wary, makes men wiſe;</l>
                  <l>Theſe try before they truſt; they follow not</l>
                  <l>All ſpecious things; the better things have got</l>
                  <l>The letter praiſe; there where (I do confeſſe)</l>
                  <l>Some that their names retain, their Fames no leſſe.</l>
                  <l>All things do by viciſſitudes excel</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Cities whereof <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mber</hi> us'd to tell,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Troy, Luna, Adria, Salvia</hi> have but names,</l>
                  <l>Time hath expung'd the reſt of all their Fames.</l>
                  <l>If (now perhaps) our Country doth decreaſe</l>
                  <l>In greatneſſe, yet her goodneſſe doth not ceaſe.</l>
                  <l>There's none in all the world but knows how great</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Romes</hi> glory ſits in her majeſtick ſeat;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="93" facs="tcp:115715:51"/>Indeed the fame thereof remains alone,</l>
                  <l>But all the former benefits are gone.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe unexhauſted Founts which wont of yore</l>
                  <l>To water all theſe paſtures with their ſtore,</l>
                  <l>Want water now themſelves; their arid veines</l>
                  <l>Exhauſted are; no cloud upon them raines.</l>
                  <l>No grounds here <hi>Tyber</hi> waters with his Flucts;</l>
                  <l>Conſuming time our ancient Aqueducts</l>
                  <l>Hath totn in pieces; Time (that all devoures)</l>
                  <l>Hath ruin'd all our Caſtles, all our Towers,</l>
                  <l>Hence, hence; O far, far hence ye Goats avant,</l>
                  <l>Here's onely pining Famine, pinching want.</l>
                  <l>Yet (as 'tis fam'd, and as our ſelves have ſeen)</l>
                  <l>Here dwells a gallant ſhepheard on a green,</l>
                  <l>Who from a Princely bird his name derives;</l>
                  <l>One rich in ſheep and paſtures, one who thrives,</l>
                  <l>Who for his verſe th' old Poets doth excell,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Orpheus,</hi> that <hi>Orpheus,</hi> who from Hell</l>
                  <l>Fetching his wife, attracted with his ſong</l>
                  <l>The trees and ſtones to follow him along.</l>
                  <l>He for all vertue, for all pious deeds</l>
                  <l>All other <hi>Latians</hi> excells, exceeds,</l>
                  <l>As much as <hi>Po</hi> doth <hi>Tiberis</hi> excell,</l>
                  <l>Or as ſweet Roſes ſtinking weeds for ſmell;</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Abdua Macra,</hi> or as willows high,</l>
                  <l>Low Bullruſhes, tall Poplars, Organy.</l>
                  <l>We count him like that Prince, to whom of yore</l>
                  <l>Learn'd <hi>Tytirus</hi> for twice ſix daies (or more)</l>
                  <l>The ſacred Altars ſmoak'd with ſweet perfumes;</l>
                  <l>Hee's keeper of the ſheep, no wolfe preſumes</l>
                  <l>To worry them; more watchful he's, more wiſe</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Juno's Argus</hi> with his hundred eies,</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Daphnis</hi> he's more learn'd; and not alone</l>
                  <l>More learn'd then him, but then that leaned one</l>
                  <l>Who kept ('tis ſaid) of old among the ſwains</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Admetus</hi> herds in the <hi>Theſſalian</hi> plaines.</l>
                  <l>He's worthy to take charge of all the breed</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:115715:52"/>Of <hi>Salenus</hi> Maſter, worthy to ſucceed</l>
                  <l>That venerable Father, who to keep</l>
                  <l>Th' Aſſyrian Flock, to feed th' Aſſyrian ſheep</l>
                  <l>Forſook his nets, forſook his ſhip, forſook</l>
                  <l>His All; and to the ſheep himſelf betook.</l>
                  <l>He can the Flock defend, can cure their wounds,</l>
                  <l>Can madefie the drought of parched grounds,</l>
                  <l>Freſh paſtures he can give unto the Flock,</l>
                  <l>He can the Fountains open and unlock;</l>
                  <l>The Favour he can impetrate of <hi>Jove,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And from the Flock can thieves and wolves remove.</l>
                  <l>If he the favour ſtay; But, if he frownes;</l>
                  <l>Hence <hi>(Candid)</hi> with thy ſheep to better downs.</l>
               </sp>
               <trailer>The End of the ninth Eclogue.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="eclogue">
               <head>
                  <hi>ECLOGUE X.</hi> Treating of the Controveſies between the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant and non-Obſervant Friers, written by <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuan</hi> after his taking Religious Ord<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs; <hi>Intituled BEMBUS.</hi>
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <l>The Poet now the difference</l>
                  <l>Of falſe and true Religion notes:</l>
                  <l>And rightly doth diſtinguiſh thence</l>
                  <l>Yhe ſheep of <hi>Carmel</hi> from the goates.</l>
               </argument>
               <stage>The ſpeakers <hi>Candidus, Bembus, Batrachus, Myrnix.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ca.</speaker>
                  <l>GReat diſcord <hi>(Bembus)</hi> hath aroſe between</l>
                  <l>The ſhepheards of the Galilaean green,</l>
                  <l>And the rough Mountaineers of <hi>Paleſtine;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To this ſide <hi>Batrachus</hi> doth moſt incline,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Myrmix</hi> to that; their arguments are fit</l>
                  <l>For diſputation; both, themlſelves ſubmit</l>
                  <l>Unto thy Judgement; briefly they'l declare</l>
                  <l>Their Arguments, that thou thine ear wilt ſpare,</l>
                  <l>And if no greater buſineſſe thee withhold,</l>
                  <l>Thou Father art of Prophets, know'ſt of old</l>
                  <l>To ſettle brawlings, diſcords to compoſe,</l>
                  <l>And with fair language foul debates to cloſe.</l>
                  <l>Thou likewiſe (as 'tis Fam'd) haſt drank the wine</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Hippocrene,</hi> haſt ſeen the Muſes nine,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Goddeſſes who keep that ſacred Fount,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Eurotas</hi> Lawrells, and <hi>Parnaſſus</hi> Mount,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="96" facs="tcp:115715:53"/>Haſt ſeen where ſelf <hi>Apollo</hi> with his boughes</l>
                  <l>Offrondent Lawrel did ſurround thy brows,</l>
                  <l>Where many gifts he did on thee confer,</l>
                  <l>His harpe, his Lute, his Iv'ry dulcimer.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Be</speaker>
                  <l>Come, freely ſpeak; ſith now this freez'ng day</l>
                  <l>Compells us by the warmer fire to ſtay;</l>
                  <l>While winter bars our Flocks to range the grounds,</l>
                  <l>While <hi>Boreas</hi> his frigid blaſts reſounds,</l>
                  <l>While bitter froſts benum the better ſoile,</l>
                  <l>While Icicles hang dangling at the tile,</l>
                  <l>While Rivers with their frozen waters keep</l>
                  <l>Their dull and drowſie Channells, as aſleep</l>
                  <l>Under their Icie pavements; we condemn</l>
                  <l>All leiſures which no buſineſſe act in them.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <l>We ſhepheards, hapleſſe men, in ſummers ſhine</l>
                  <l>Walk ſtragling; careful leſt out Flocks ſhould pine;</l>
                  <l>But when cold weather makes us keep within,</l>
                  <l>Then diſcontents and brawling-ſtrifes begin.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
                  <l>They that preſume authentick Rites to change</l>
                  <l>At their own pleaſure, and themſelves eſtrange</l>
                  <l>From Laws obſervance, theſe thoſe parties are,</l>
                  <l>O <hi>Myrmix,</hi> who beget domeſtick war.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Be.</speaker>
                  <l>And is your ſtrife about the authentick rites,</l>
                  <l>The cuſtomes of (thoſe ancient Proſelytes)</l>
                  <l>Your Fathers? Then, O <hi>Batrachus,</hi> declare</l>
                  <l>What are thoſe rites, and what thoſe cuſtomes are.</l>
                  <l>Declare why from Phoenician ſoil you came</l>
                  <l>To this our Country; I well knew the ſame,</l>
                  <l>I ſaw thoſe Paſtures, I thoſe fields have ſeen</l>
                  <l>With unexhauſted moiſture cloth'd in green.</l>
                  <l>There from the top of <hi>Carmels</hi> Mount doth ſpring</l>
                  <l>A Fount of Chriſtall waters, watering</l>
                  <l>With bubbling ſtreams the thick adjoyning woods.</l>
                  <l>I ſaw the River <hi>Jordan,</hi> in whoſe Floods</l>
                  <l>That great and famous ſhepheard, heretofore</l>
                  <l>His ſheep immerging cur'd their cureleſſe ſore.</l>
                  <l>This River riſing, running down the ſides</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="97" facs="tcp:115715:53"/>Of <hi>Libanus,</hi> with full fill'd current glides</l>
                  <l>Along the <hi>Galilaean</hi> fields, and makes</l>
                  <l>An ample Sea with its conjoyned Lakes:</l>
                  <l>And running thence again, it makes again</l>
                  <l>With its united floods a ſpacious Main,</l>
                  <l>Near to that City, which (as ſtories Fame)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tiberius Tiberia's</hi> did name:</l>
                  <l>And running thence again, at length it falls</l>
                  <l>(Leaving behind the <hi>Jerichonian</hi> walls)</l>
                  <l>Into th'infamous Lake <hi>Aſphaltites.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By this, and by ſuch other things as theſe</l>
                  <l>'Tis prov'd enough that we theſe Coaſts have ſeen;</l>
                  <l>This ſpeak, and end at length your ſtrife, your ſpleen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Myr.</speaker>
                  <l>Bold <hi>Batrachus</hi> doth ſtill himſelf obtrude</l>
                  <l>With braſen face, and more then raſhly rude,</l>
                  <l>Prefers himſelf to me with great oſtent.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bat.</speaker>
                  <l>I nor obtrude my ſelf, nor argument,</l>
                  <l>But, as commanded by the Judge, proceed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bem.</speaker>
                  <l>Lay down thy ſheephook <hi>Myrmix,</hi> and (with ſpeed)</l>
                  <l>Thine alſo <hi>Batrachus</hi> lay down; your parts</l>
                  <l>You muſt not plead with arms, but upright hearts.</l>
                  <l>Speak <hi>Batrachus; Myrmix</hi> the while forbear,</l>
                  <l>That you may better anſwer what you hear.</l>
                  <l>He's mad that's cholerick; and he that's mad</l>
                  <l>Is of ſo much impatience, is ſo bad,</l>
                  <l>That not his heart he can, nor tongue reſtrain,</l>
                  <l>His acts are fooliſh, and his words are vain.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bat.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bembus,</hi> I will relate, I will recall</l>
                  <l>Our Anceſtors and their originall,</l>
                  <l>We from <hi>Aſſyria</hi> came, as <hi>Candid</hi> prov'd:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Elias</hi> is our Father, we remov'd</l>
                  <l>All kinde of ill from ſhepherds with ſtrong arms,</l>
                  <l>VVho fire from heaven brought with heavenly charms</l>
                  <l>Of fervent prayers. Thither and, or higher</l>
                  <l>Aſcended in a Chariot of fire.</l>
                  <l>A Noble this, this is an ancient Line</l>
                  <l>Of famous Parentage, almoſt divine.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:115715:54"/>All other ſhepherds whereſoere inliv'd,</l>
                  <l>Are but as Rivers from our Founts deriv'd:</l>
                  <l>We gave thrm Laws, we taught them th'art to breed,</l>
                  <l>To feed their flocks; they then muchmore exceed</l>
                  <l>In ſin, who being Prime in Order looſe</l>
                  <l>Their Primacy, while unadvis'd they chooſe,</l>
                  <l>And inconſiderate attempts purſue,</l>
                  <l>We roots, boughs, others are: and we ('tis true)</l>
                  <l>Are alſo boughs which from the root did ſprout</l>
                  <l>Of our forefathers, now with age worn out.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Elias</hi> to the ſhepherds gave a ſure,</l>
                  <l>A never-erring art, whereby to cure</l>
                  <l>Their crazy flocks, whereby to learn to know</l>
                  <l>What fodder hurts, what ſtorms or winds did blow:</l>
                  <l>Of healthful, of infectious years he told,</l>
                  <l>Omitting nothing that concern'd the fold.</l>
                  <l>But that ſame fountain which did flow while-ere</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Carmels</hi> Mount ſo Chryſtaline, ſo clear,</l>
                  <l>With changed current ('tis apparent) now</l>
                  <l>Doth Southward run, where Eaſtward it did flow</l>
                  <l>In times of yore; th'old channel yet is ſeen.</l>
                  <l>Theſe Innovators (changing what hath been)</l>
                  <l>Have made new courſes, have that old forſook,</l>
                  <l>Which our forefathers wiſely gave the brook.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Myr.</speaker>
                  <l>What's that to thee, whether the rivers ſource</l>
                  <l>Run in a newer or an older courſe,</l>
                  <l>So that it overflowing overſpreads</l>
                  <l>With fertile waters the contiguous Meads?</l>
                  <l>And why do'ſt of heav'ns Clime complain? The ſun</l>
                  <l>His daily race in Southern skies doth run;</l>
                  <l>The Vine that Southward grows beſt wine diſtils,</l>
                  <l>Beſt Grapes are gathered from the <hi>Lybian</hi> hills.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bat.</speaker>
                  <l>And thoſe beſt Ewe-trees are that northward grow,</l>
                  <l>A River therefore beſt ſhould northward flow.</l>
                  <l>A ſhepherd art? and (mad man) careleſs grown</l>
                  <l>Of thy poor flock (as if 'twere not thine own)</l>
                  <l>Thou talk'w of Vines; as if an equal line</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="99" facs="tcp:115715:54"/>Did regulate a flock, and dreſs a Vine;</l>
                  <l>As though thou didſt not know, or couldſt not finde</l>
                  <l>A difference in waters, graſs and winde;</l>
                  <l>And what ill winds unto the Cattel blow</l>
                  <l>From Southern Climates, learn of <hi>Rome</hi> to know.</l>
                  <l>If South-winds hurtleſs be, why then, O why</l>
                  <l>Are <hi>Modens</hi> fleeces of a dusky dye?</l>
                  <l>Why ſnow-like white is all <hi>Clitumnus</hi> breed?</l>
                  <l>Why for fine wooll doe <hi>Mantua's</hi> flocks exceed</l>
                  <l>All other ſheep? And why's <hi>Verona's</hi> fleece,</l>
                  <l>Next unto <hi>Mantua's,</hi> the fined peece?</l>
                  <l>Whence come thoſe multiplicities of things</l>
                  <l>In various forms? The reaſon (doubtleſs) ſprings</l>
                  <l>From nothing elſe, then from the divers kinds</l>
                  <l>Of operations in graſs, waters, winds.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bem.</speaker>
                  <l>I prethee <hi>Candidus</hi> hence quickly take</l>
                  <l>Theſe ſhepherds ſheep-hooks; I perceive they'l make</l>
                  <l>Fierce wars this day: Take them in private hence,</l>
                  <l>And hide them under yonder ſedgy fence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bat.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bembus,</hi> I ſpeak to thee; while heretofore</l>
                  <l>We liv'd together, which our Cattel bore</l>
                  <l>One common mark, alas, what ſhame, alas,</l>
                  <l>How many miſchiefs did our Cattel paſs?</l>
                  <l>Unlawful 'twas our ſheep to waſh, to ſhear</l>
                  <l>At the firſt ſeaſons (as 'tis us'd) of th'year:</l>
                  <l>The thorns unfleec'd, and naked made our ſheep,</l>
                  <l>The briars tore their naked backs with deep,</l>
                  <l>With bloody ſcars; their skins with ſcabs were rent,</l>
                  <l>Conſuming humours made them peſtilent,</l>
                  <l>And ulcers all their bodies o're did creep.</l>
                  <l>It therefore much concerns what herbage ſheep</l>
                  <l>Do feed upon, what kinde of waters they</l>
                  <l>Do drink, and in what region they ſtay.</l>
                  <l>Come, tell me, <hi>Myrmix,</hi> tell me why the wooll</l>
                  <l>Hath loſt its former colour? once leſs dull.</l>
                  <l>What gave unto the flock theſe fleeces new?</l>
                  <l>Why are thoſe Cattel of a blacker hue,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="100" facs="tcp:115715:55"/>VVhich brighter were in better times? 'tis ſtrange:</l>
                  <l>Their manners changing made their fleeces change.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bembus,</hi> I now to thee return; and will</l>
                  <l>Endevour brevity: but Ile diſtill</l>
                  <l>The truth, that ſo the ſentence thou ſhalt give</l>
                  <l>May merit honour and for ever live.</l>
                  <l>The judgements thine: I will the truth purſue;</l>
                  <l>A true relation makes the judgement true.</l>
                  <l>Pond'ring theſe miſchiefs, able ſcarce to bear</l>
                  <l>So many loſſes which ſo frequent were,</l>
                  <l>VVe came unto the Fountain, and from thence</l>
                  <l>To ſearch the River was my providence.</l>
                  <l>Thy providence, O <hi>Myrmix,</hi> was the while</l>
                  <l>To look a Birds Neſt, or in Hunters toyle</l>
                  <l>To take a frisking Goar, or nimble Roe,</l>
                  <l>Fit gifts to give to thy beloved Froe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Myr.</speaker>
                  <l>See'ſt <hi>Bembus</hi> with what open ſcoffs he jeers?</l>
                  <l>This matter I ſuppoſe (as well appears)</l>
                  <l>Hands muſt decide, not tongues; and 'tis my wont</l>
                  <l>VVith blows not words to batter ſuch affront.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <l>To ſpeak the truth, O <hi>Batrachus,</hi> thy tongue</l>
                  <l>Runs faſter then is fit: Thou do'ſt him wrong.</l>
                  <l>Bad language whets on choller; ſcoffing words</l>
                  <l>The minde imbitter, cut more ſharp then ſwords.</l>
                  <l>Thou dealſt not with a Childe, nor think we can</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Myrmix</hi> is an undervalued man;</l>
                  <l>'Tis danger to ſpeak what ſhould not be ſpoke,</l>
                  <l>And men with ſawcy language to provoke.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bat.</speaker>
                  <l>Excuſe me, <hi>Myrmix,</hi> I did mean thine Aunt:</l>
                  <l>But, by what errour a Concomitant</l>
                  <l>I nam'd, know not: Pardon my miſtake.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Myr.</speaker>
                  <l>I pardon it: But yet beware thou make</l>
                  <l>No more miſtakes: Beware, provoke no more.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bat.</speaker>
                  <l>A ſtream of running water leaping ore</l>
                  <l>A lofty Rock, delv'd with its fall a Lake,</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe pent up waters did a level make</l>
                  <l>VVithin the Banks: The Lake with darkſome trees</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="101" facs="tcp:115715:55"/>Was overſhadowed, and under theſe</l>
                  <l>Briars and Thorns thick growing in a brake</l>
                  <l>Did round incloſe the melancholly Lake.</l>
                  <l>A thouſand shapes of ven'mous things I ſpy'd</l>
                  <l>Within the Lake, a thouſand more beſide</l>
                  <l>Crawling along the banks, along the brim</l>
                  <l>Of thoſe black waters up and down did ſwim:</l>
                  <l>A thouſand more did through the wood decline</l>
                  <l>Unto the Lake with motion Serpentine.</l>
                  <l>Amaz'd, in haſte back to the Cotes I ran,</l>
                  <l>And with my three tooth'd fork I there began</l>
                  <l>To turn the ſtraw: when O behold, a Snake</l>
                  <l>Erects his head, and doth great hiſſing make.</l>
                  <l>With his three-forked tongue, his jaws were ſwell'd:</l>
                  <l>A Scorpion his invenom'd claws upheld;</l>
                  <l>A Toad big belli'd crawling there I ſaw,</l>
                  <l>And a fell Viper hiſſing in the ſtraw.</l>
                  <l>O fatal places, ſaid I, not alone</l>
                  <l>Fatal to ſheep but ſhepherds; Ile be gone.</l>
                  <l>Forthwith my flock dividing, I forſook</l>
                  <l>That diſmal place, and my ſad ſelf betook</l>
                  <l>To ſeek out better paſtures; and I led</l>
                  <l>New Rivers from the Fountains firſt found head</l>
                  <l>Through that old tract, and in thoſe fields, thoſe ways.</l>
                  <l>Where firſt the roſie-colour'd Morn diſplays</l>
                  <l>Her bluſh, when <hi>Phoebus</hi> at his re-aſcent</l>
                  <l>Inflames the Saffron-tinctur'd Orient.</l>
                  <l>Here fruitful were my Cattel, Paſtures here</l>
                  <l>Were flouriſhing, the bubling waters clear,</l>
                  <l>Unſtain'd with filth, and undefil'd with mire:</l>
                  <l>Theſe are the places, whither did retire</l>
                  <l>Our ſage forefathers, here they firſt did dwell.</l>
                  <l>The ruines yet are extant of their Cell:</l>
                  <l>Old wells of water, rotten Poſts of wood</l>
                  <l>Pitch'd in the ground, which there divided stood</l>
                  <l>Sev'n foot apart; an hearth for fire, an hall</l>
                  <l>Surrounded with a ruinated wall.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:115715:56"/>
                  <speaker>Myr.</speaker>
                  <l>Inconſtant men affect new-fangled things;</l>
                  <l>New Paſtures therefore, and unheard-of Springs</l>
                  <l>Thou ſeek'ſt and feign'ſt; and doſt theſe things deviſe</l>
                  <l>An author to be deem'd of Novelties.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bat.</speaker>
                  <l>Grave men affect their own; which is the cauſe</l>
                  <l>VVhy <hi>Myrmix</hi> too too much himſelf withdraws</l>
                  <l>From gravity: This newneſs is not new,</l>
                  <l>But moſt authentick oldneſs, ſolid, true:</l>
                  <l>Religion, practis'd in the pious lives</l>
                  <l>Of our forefathers, now reſtor'd, revives:</l>
                  <l>Which too too foully was corrupted, both</l>
                  <l>By thine own looſeneſs, and thy Sects known ſloth.</l>
                  <l>If therefore ruin'd houſes one rebuild,</l>
                  <l>Or of a barren make a fruitful field,</l>
                  <l>Shouldſt thou be Judge, he ſhall condemned be.</l>
                  <l>Another Tree we plant, but yet that Tree</l>
                  <l>Which fruitleſs was we prune, and on the ſtock</l>
                  <l>Which was grown old (and barren like a block)</l>
                  <l>We graft new Ciences, and with our care</l>
                  <l>Make fruitful that which fruitleſs was and bare.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Myr.</speaker>
                  <l>Though there thy Cattel eat fat-feeding graſs,</l>
                  <l>And drink untroubled waters, yet (alas)</l>
                  <l>Too many Lambs there with their Dams are dead,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Carkaſes have Wolves and Ravens fed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bat.</speaker>
                  <l>Theſe I confeſs, theſe Cattel which have ta'ne</l>
                  <l>The peſtilent infection of thy bane,</l>
                  <l>Infect beholders ev'n from far: ſo much</l>
                  <l>Of poiſon's in them, and the force is ſuch,</l>
                  <l>Such and ſo great of your invenom'd art,</l>
                  <l>That more and more I wiſh from hence to part,</l>
                  <l>Hence to depart: But O, this ill alone</l>
                  <l>My flock indures, that yet it is not gone</l>
                  <l>Into the vaſt waſte Wilderneſs, not yet</l>
                  <l>Can far enough into the deſerts get</l>
                  <l>(Within ſome Cave, ſome: unfrequented Rock)</l>
                  <l>Retir'd from you, from your infected flock.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Myr.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou <hi>Batrachus</hi> inventeſt many lies</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="103" facs="tcp:115715:56"/>Againſt our flocks: Thou ſure art over-wiſe,</l>
                  <l>Art over-careful of anothers Tribe,</l>
                  <l>And raſhly do'ſt unto thy ſelf aſcribe</l>
                  <l>Unjuſt Cenſoriouſneſs: Why ſhould not I</l>
                  <l>VVho keep great ſtore of Cattel this eſpy</l>
                  <l>As well as thou? what, is mine houſe (mine own)</l>
                  <l>Onely to thee, to thy Companions known?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bat.</speaker>
                  <l>Becauſe that th' <hi>Aethiopians</hi> tawny skins</l>
                  <l>Are colli'd all with black, that colour wins</l>
                  <l>Repute with them; Nor do they beauty lack,</l>
                  <l>Nor are diſdain'd becauſe their skins are black:</l>
                  <l>Their faces all, are all alike; who blames</l>
                  <l>Anothers face, his own therein defames:</l>
                  <l>Your ſheep and ſhepherds have the like reflect,</l>
                  <l>Like Peſt, l<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke ſcabs, like colour, like aſpect.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bem.</speaker>
                  <l>Forbear, your cauſe is underſtood, forbear;</l>
                  <l>The day declines, The Suns ſwift Chariotteer</l>
                  <l>Is whirl'd below, beyond yon tops of hills.</l>
                  <l>Hear, O ye Rivulets of ancient Rills,</l>
                  <l>Ye that derive by long antiquity</l>
                  <l>From great Progenitors your Progeny;</l>
                  <l>Hear what our judgement is, and O imbrace</l>
                  <l>This our impartial ſentence in your caſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Myr.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou <hi>Batrachus</hi> do'ſt me too much provoke</l>
                  <l>VVith peremptory language, baſely ſpoke.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bat.</speaker>
                  <l>Not I, but thy bad cauſe provokes thee more,</l>
                  <l>Thy guilty minde juſt judgement doth abhor.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <l>VVhen 'tis high time to lay debate aſide,</l>
                  <l>Your madneſs ſtirs new ſtrife, anew you chide.</l>
                  <l>This quarrel then with everlaſting hate</l>
                  <l>Perpetually ſhall live, beyond your fate.</l>
                  <l>VVhat weakneſs, O what madneſs doth pervert</l>
                  <l>Your ſenſes thus, doth vex your head, your heart?</l>
                  <l>VVhat, bluſh you not, ſo rudely to behave</l>
                  <l>Your ſelves before a Judge ſo great, ſo grave?</l>
                  <l>Hear then without diſtemper, hate, or ſpleen,</l>
                  <l>That final ſentence which you twain between</l>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:115715:57"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115715:57"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="104" facs="tcp:115715:58"/>
The learned <hi>Bembus</hi> ſhall pronounce, and it</l>
                  <l>Account authentick, and thereto ſubmit.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bem.</speaker>
                  <l>Trace out that path, thoſe ancient ways tranſact</l>
                  <l>Of your forefathers, keep that Older tract.</l>
                  <l>Recall your wandring flocks within their Pales,</l>
                  <l>From Dens of ſavage Beaſts, from Rocks, from Vales.</l>
                  <l>And in thoſe older fields, that ancient Plain</l>
                  <l>Erect your ſhepherds Cottages again.</l>
               </sp>
               <trailer>The end of the fifth Eclogue.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <head>THE EPILOGUE To the Readers.</head>
            <l>SO, now 'tis done: <hi>Commend it,</hi> or <hi>Come mend it:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Be not offended at it, but defend it:</l>
            <l>Nor at the Workman, or the Work, repine,</l>
            <l>Scene, Author, Actors, all are tranſmarine.</l>
            <l>No Perſons, as this <hi>Book</hi> doth them inſtyle,</l>
            <l>Dwell in this <hi>Little World, Great Britains Ile:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Our Natives are ſo farre from them in this,</l>
            <l>As from the World our Ile divided is.</l>
            <l>then Cenſure not: but in t'your ſelves deſcend,</l>
            <l>And <hi>There,</hi> what <hi>Here</hi> you finde amiſs, amend.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho: Harvey</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:115715:58"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
